<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Familiar letters. Vol. I. Written by the Right Honourable John, late Earl of Rochester, to the Honble Henry Savile, Esq; and other letters, by persons of honour and quality. With letters written by the most ingenious  Mr. Thomas Otway, and Mrs. K. Phillips. Publish'd from their original copies. With modern letters, by Tho. Cheek, Esq; Mr. Dennis, and Mr. Brown.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 240 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 121 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05023</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1745A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R182831</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">51784625</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 51784625</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05023)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2710:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Familiar letters. Vol. I. Written by the Right Honourable John, late Earl of Rochester, to the Honble Henry Savile, Esq; and other letters, by persons of honour and quality. With letters written by the most ingenious  Mr. Thomas Otway, and Mrs. K. Phillips. Publish'd from their original copies. With modern letters, by Tho. Cheek, Esq; Mr. Dennis, and Mr. Brown.</title>
                  <author>Rochester, John Wilmot, Earl of, 1647-1680.</author>
                  <author>Sidney, Algernon, 1622-1683.</author>
                  <author>Otway, Thomas, 1652-1685.</author>
                  <author>Cheek, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Phillips, Katherine, fl. 1658.</author>
                  <author>Brown, Thomas, 1663-1704.</author>
                  <author>Ayloffe, W. (William).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>3d ed., with additions.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[16], 223 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Sackett ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bound and filmed preceeding Wing R1748 (Familiar letters vol. II).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Universität Göttingen Bibliothek.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English letters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Love-letters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:2"/>
            <p>Familiar Letters:</p>
            <p>VOL. I.</p>
            <p>Written by the Right Honourable <hi>John,</hi> late Earl of ROCHESTER, TO THE Hon<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> 
               <hi>Henry Savile,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> And other LETTERS, by <hi>Perſons of Honour and Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH LETTERS Written by the moſt Ingenious Mr. <hi>THOMAS OTWAY,</hi> AND Mrs. <hi>K. PHILLIPS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſh'd from their Original Copies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Modern LETTERS, by <hi>THO. CHEEK,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Mr. <hi>DENNIS,</hi> And Mr. <hi>BROWN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Third Edition, with Additions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Sackett</hi> at the <hi>Heart and Bible</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:3"/>
            <head>TO D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> RADCLIFF.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have preſum'd (tho' I knew at the ſame time how hainouſly I treſpaſs'd against You in doing ſo) to inſcribe Your Name to the following <hi>Collection of Letters.</hi> As You were no ſtranger to that Excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe Pieces Compoſes, by far, the most valuable part of it, ſo I was ſatisfy'd that every thing, from ſo Celebrated a Hand, wou'd be acceptable and welcome to You; and in that Confidence, made bold to give You the Trouble of this Addreſs. My Lord <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> has left ſo eſtabliſh'd a Reputation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, that he needs no officious Pen to ſet out his Worth, eſpecially to You, who were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted ſo perfectly well with all his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Qualities, that made him the Delight and Envy of both Sexes, and the Ornament of our Iſland. In every thing of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's writing, there's ſomething ſo happily expreſs'd, the Graces are ſo numerous, yet ſo unaffected, that I don't wonder why all the
<pb facs="tcp:175033:4"/>Original Touches of ſo imcomparable a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter have been enquir'd after, with ſo Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and General a Concern. Most of his other Compoſitions, eſpecially thoſe in Verſe, have long ago bleſs'd the Publick, and were receiv'd with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Delight and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which gives me Encouragement to believe that his Letters will find the like Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. Tho' most of them were written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on private Occaſions, to an Honourable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who was ſo happy in his Lordſhip's Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, with no intention to be ever made publick; yet that conſtant good Sence, which is all along viſible in them, the Juſtice of the Obſervations, and the peculiar Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Style, are Reaſons ſufficient, why they ſhould no longer be conceal'd in private Hands. And indeed, at this time, when the private Plate of the Nation comes abroad to relieve the preſent Exigences, it ſeems but juſt, that ſince the Dearth of <hi>Wit</hi> is as great as that of <hi>Money,</hi> ſuch a Treaſure of ſo good Sence and Language, ſhou'd no longer be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in <hi>Oblivion.</hi> With this difference, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, That whereas our Plate, before it can circulate in our Markets, muſt receive the Royal Stamp, muſt be melted down, and take another Form; theſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvaluable Remains want no Alterations to recommed them;
<pb facs="tcp:175033:4"/>they need only be taken from the Rich Mines where they grew; for their own Intrinſick Value ſecures them, and his Lordſhip's Name is ſufficient to make them Current.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Letters</hi> by other Hands, that make up this Volume, ſome of them were written by Gentlemen that are wholly ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to me; and others belong to thoſe that are ſo much better known in the World than my ſelf, that I can ſay nothing upon this Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but what falls vaſtly ſhort of their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. But I cannot forbear ſaying ſomething of Mr. <hi>Otway</hi>'s: They have that Inimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Tenderneſs in them, that I dare oppoſe them to any thing of Antiquity: I am ſure few of the preſent Age can pretend to come up to them. The Paſſions, in the raiſing of which, he had a Felicity peculiar to himſelf, are repreſented in ſuch lively Colours, that they cannot fail of affecting the moſt inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Hearts, with pleaſing Agitations. I cou'd wiſh we had more Pieces of the ſame Hand; for I profeſs an intire Veneration to his Memory, and always look'd upon him as the only Perſon, almoſt, that knew the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Springs and Sources of Nature, and made a true uſe of them. Love, as it is generally manag'd by other Hands, is either raving and <hi>Enthuſiaſtical,</hi> or elſe dull and languiſhing:
<pb facs="tcp:175033:5"/>In him alone 'tis true Nature, and at the ſame time inſpires us with Compaſſion and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. After this, I will not venture to ſay any thing of my own Trifles that bring up the Rear. Some of 'em were written long ago, and now huddled in haſte; the rest had a little more Care and Labour beſtow'd upon them. If they contribute in the leaſt to your Entertainment, which was my only Deſign in publiſhing them, I have attain'd my Ends: I have ſome others by me, which I may, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, publiſh hereafter, if theſe meet with any tolerable Succeſs.</p>
            <p>I need not (and I am ſure I cannot) make You a better <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> than to acquaint the World, that You were happy in my Lord <hi>Rocheſter's</hi> Friendſhip, that he took plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Your Converſation; of which even his Enemies muſt allow him to have been the beſt Judge, and that in the Politeſt Reign we can boaſt of in <hi>England.</hi> The Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo impartial a Judge, who was in his Time, a Scourge to all Blockheads, by what Names or Titles ſoever dignified, or diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, is above all the Incenſe that a much better Hand than mine can preſume to offer: Shou'd I put out all the Dedication Sails, as 'tis the way of moſt Authors, I cou'd ſoon erect You into a Great <hi>Hero,</hi> and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer;
<pb facs="tcp:175033:5"/>and tell how often You have trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed over inveterate Diſtempers, and reſtor'd the Sick to that only Bleſſing, that makes Life ſupportable. I cou'd tell how, by Your ſingle Merit, You have baffled a Faction form'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt You with equal Malice and Ignorance; I cou'd tell what marks of Munificence You have left behind You, in the Place that was honour'd with Your Education; and how ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly ready You are to ſerve Your Friends upon all Occaſions. But after all, the higheſt thing I will pretend to ſay of You, is, That You were eſteem'd, and valu'd, and lov'd by my Lord <hi>Rocheſter.</hi> 'Tis true, as there never was any Conſpicuous Merit in the World, that had not (like <hi>Hercules</hi>) Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to encounter, ſo You have had Your ſhare of them; but, Heaven be prais'd, Your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, with all their vain Endeavours, have only ſerved to fix Your Intereſt, and advance Your Reputation: Tho' I know You hear of nothing with more uneaſineſs, than of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours You do; yet I cannot omit to tell, and indeed I am vain upon it, That You have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended ſo low, as to divert thoſe Hours You cou'd ſteal from the Publick, with ſome of my Trifles, that You have been pleaſed to think favourably of them, and rewarded them. For all which Obligations, I had no other way
<pb facs="tcp:175033:6"/>of expreſſing my Gratitude but this; which, I am afraid will but inflame the Reckoning, inſtead of paying any part of the Debt: But this has been the conſtant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage in all Ages of <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> and, like <hi>Senators</hi> that take Bribes, we have Antiquity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality to plead in our Excuſe. But I forget that You are all this while in pain, till the <hi>Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> releaſes You: Therefore I have nothing but my Wiſhes to add, That You, who have been ſo happy a Reſtorer of Health to others, may ever enjoy it Your Self, that Your Days may be always pleaſant, and Your Nights eaſie, and that You'll be pleas'd to forgive this Preſumption in</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, and moſt Obliged Servant, T. BROWN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:6"/>
            <head>THE BOOKSELLER'S <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving (by the Aſſiſtance of a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Friend) procured the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Letters,</hi> that were written by the late Incomparable Earl of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> (the Originals of all which I preſerve by me, to ſatisfie thoſe Gentlemen, who may have the Curioſity to ſee them under his Lordſhip's Hand) I was encouraged to trouble others of my Friends, that had any Letters in their Cuſtody, to make this <hi>Collection,</hi> which I now publiſh.</p>
            <p>Indeed the Letters that were written by the above-mention'd Honourable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, have ſomething ſo happy in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Style, that I need not loſe my Time to convince the World they are genuine. I may ſay the ſame of Mr. <hi>Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi>'s Letters, that they are full of Life and Paſſion, and ſufficiently diſcover their Author. And that this <hi>Collection</hi> might be compleat, I got ſome that were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Fam'd <hi>Orinda,</hi> Mrs. <hi>Katherine
<pb facs="tcp:175033:7"/>Phillips,</hi> to be added to the reſt; together with others by ſome Gentlemen now living, that the <hi>Reader</hi> might have a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Entertainment.</p>
            <p>Our Neighbouring Nations, whom I don't believe we come ſhort of in any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, have printed ſeveral Volumes of Letters, which met with publick Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation; I am ſatisfied, that if the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>England</hi> wou'd be as free, and Communicative to part with theirs, we might ſhew as great a number, and as good a Choice as they have done. It has been uſed as an Objection againſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing things of this Nature, That, if they are written as they ought to be, they ſhou'd never be made publick. But I hope this <hi>Collection</hi> will diſarm that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; for tho' the <hi>Reader</hi> may not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand every particular Paſſage, yet there are other things in them that will make him ſufficient Amends.</p>
            <p>I have only a word more to add: Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Noiſe of this <hi>Collection,</hi> ſeveral Gentlemen have been ſo kind, as to ſend me in Materials to compoſe a Second, which is now printed; and, on the Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Second, I have procured as many of the Lord <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s the Duke of <hi>Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingham,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:175033:7"/>and Sir <hi>George Etheridge,</hi> which will almoſt make a Third Volume, which if I can compleat, it ſhall be publiſh'd next <hi>Trinity-Term;</hi> and therefore thoſe Gentlemen that have any Curious Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by them, written by thoſe Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Perſons, and are willing to oblige the Publick, by letting them come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, are deſired to ſend them to me, who will take Care to have them faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Tranſcrib'd for the Preſs, and Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Third Volume; which will be intirely theirs, and no Modern one mixt with them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:8"/>
            <head>A TABLE Of all the LETTERS in this Volume.</head>
            <list>
               <item>SEveral Letters by the late Earl of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> to the Honourable <hi>Henry Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> from <hi>p. 1.</hi> to <hi>p. 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Earl of <hi>L</hi>—'s Letter to the Honourable <hi>Algernoon Sidney, p. 51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Algernoon Sidney</hi>'s Letter againſt Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Government, <hi>p. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Two Letters by another Hand, to Madam— from <hi>p. 67.</hi> to. <hi>p 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Love Letters by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Otway,</hi> from <hi>p. 73.</hi> to <hi>87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter from—to Mr. <hi>G</hi>— <hi>p. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter to the Duke of <hi>Vivone,</hi> by the Fam'd Monſieur <hi>Boileau.</hi> Tranſlated by <hi>Thomas Cheek</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
                  <hi>p. 91.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter by Mr. <hi>Dennis,</hi> ſent with Monſieur <hi>Boileau</hi>'s Speech to the Academy of <hi>Paris,</hi> upon his Admiſſion, <hi>p. 102.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Monſieur <hi>Boileau</hi>'s Speech to the Academy. Tranſlated by Mr. <hi>Dennis, p. 106.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Letters of Courtſhip to a Woman of Quality, from <hi>p. 118.</hi> to <hi>p. 133.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter of Reproach to a Woman of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, <hi>p. 134.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:175033:8"/>
               <item>A Letter of Buſineſs to a Merchat's Wife in the City, <hi>p. 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Letters by the late celebrated Mrs. <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Phillips,</hi> from <hi>p. 137.</hi> to <hi>152.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter to Mr. <hi>Herbert, p. 152.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter to <hi>C. G.</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> in <hi>Covent-garden, p. 156.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Perjur'd Mrs.— <hi>p. 163.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the Honble —in the <hi>Pall-mall, p. 168.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter to my Lady— <hi>p. 173.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Conſolatory Letter to an <hi>Eſſex-Divine,</hi> upon the Death of his Wife, <hi>p. 179.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Let to the fair <hi>Lucinda</hi> at <hi>Epſom, p. 183.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To the ſame at <hi>London, p. 185.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To <hi>W. Knight,</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> at <hi>Ruſcomb,</hi> in <hi>Berk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, p. 189.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a Gentleman that fell deſperately in Love, and ſet up for a <hi>Beau</hi> in the 45th Year of his Age, <hi>p. 197.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Anſwer, <hi>p. 200.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter to his Honoured Friend, Dr. <hi>Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> at the <hi>Bath, p. 202.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter to Mr. <hi>Raphſon,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>R. Society,</hi> upon occaſion of Dr. <hi>Conner</hi>'s Book, entituled, <hi>Phyſica Arcana, ſeu Tractat. de Myſtico Corporum Statu;</hi> to be Printed by Mr. <hi>Briſcoe, p. 213.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Letter to the L<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>North and Grey, p. 218.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To a Friend in the Country, <hi>p. 221.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:9"/>
            <head>Books printed for, and ſold by <hi>R. Wellington.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN <hi>Italian</hi> Voyage, or a compleat Journey thro' <hi>Italy,</hi> in 2 Parts; with the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of the People, and a Deſcription of the Chief Towns, Churches, Monaſteries, Tombs, Libraries, Palaces, Villa's, Gardens, Pictures, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and Antiquities; as alſo of the Intereſt, Government, Riches, Forces, &amp;c. of all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with Inſtructions concerning Travels; the ſecond Edition, very much enlarged, by a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Hand; price 5 Shillings.</p>
            <p>The whole Works of that Excellent <hi>Practic. Phyſician</hi> Dr. <hi>Tho. Sydenham,</hi> wherein not only the Hiſt. and Cure of acute Diſeaſes are treated of, after a new and accurate Method; but alſo the ſhorteſt and ſafeſt way of curing moſt Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Diſeaſes, tranſlated from the Original <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> by <hi>John Pechey,</hi> of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians;</hi> price 5 Shillings.</p>
            <p>A General Treatiſe of the Diſeaſes of Infants and Children, collected from the beſt Authors, viz. <hi>Etmuller, Willis,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>John Pechey,</hi> of the <hi>College</hi> of <hi>Phiſicians;</hi> price 1 Shilling and 6 d.</p>
            <p>The Family-Phyſician, or a choice Collection of Remedies for all Diſeaſes incident to Human Bodies, whether internal or external, uſeful in Families, and ſerviceable to Country People: To which is added the <hi>Engliſh Wine-Cellar,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beſt Method for making <hi>Engliſh Wines,</hi> and <hi>Metheglin,</hi> with a Collection of <hi>Coſmetick</hi> Remedies, for the preſerving the Beauty and Complection of Ladies, never before publiſh'd, by <hi>George Harman, Philo-Chymist,</hi> Servant to Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi> till he died; price 3 Shill.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:175033:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Familiar Letters, By the Right Honourable, JOHN, LATE Earl of <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">VOL. I.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>DO a Charity becoming one of your pious Principles, in preſerving your humble Servant <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> from the imminent Peril of Sobriety; which for want of good Wine, more
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:175033:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>than Company, (for I can drink like a Hermit betwixt God and my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) very like to befal me: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Pains I have formerly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>to wean you from your pernicious Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of Diſcretion and Wiſdom!</hi> And, if you have a grateful Heart, (which is a Miracle amongſt you Stateſmen) ſhew it, by directing the Bearer to the beſt Wine in <hi>Town;</hi> and pray let not this higheſt Point of <hi>Sacred Friendſhip</hi> be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd <hi>ſlightly,</hi> but go about it <hi>with all due deliberation and care, as holy Prieſts to Sacrifice, or as diſcreet Thieves to the wary performance of Burglary and Shop-lifting.</hi> Let your well-diſcerning Pallat (the beſt Judge about you) travel from Cellar to Cellar, and then from Piece to Piece, till it has lighted on Wine <hi>fit for its noble Choice and my Approbation.</hi> To engage you the more in this matter, know, I have laid a Plot may very probably betray you to the Drinking of it. My Lord — will inform you at large.</p>
               <p>Dear <hi>Savile!</hi> as ever thou doſt hope to <hi>out-do Machiavel,</hi> or <hi>equal Me,</hi> ſend ſome good Wine! So may thy wearied
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:175033:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Soul at laſt find Reſt, no longer hov'ring 'twixt th' unequal Choice of <hi>Politicks</hi> and <hi>Lewdneſs!</hi> Maiſt thou be admir'd and lov'd for thy <hi>domeſtick Wit; belov'd</hi> and <hi>cheriſh'd</hi> for thy <hi>foreign Intereſt</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:175033:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU cannot ſhake off the Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man intirely; for, I percieve, you have no Opinion of a Letter, that is not almoſt a Gazette: Now, to me, who think the World as giddy as my ſelf, I care not which way it turns, and am fond of no News, but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of my Friends, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of their Kindneſs to me, which is the only Error I wiſh to continue in 'em: For my own part, I am not at all ſtung with my Lord <hi>M</hi>—'s mean Ambition, but I aſpire to my Lord <hi>L</hi>—'s generous Philoſophy: They who would be great in our little Government, ſeem as ridiculous to me as School-boys, who, with much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, and ſome danger, climb a Crab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, venturing their Necks for Fruit, which ſolid Pigs would diſdain, if they
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175033:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>were not ſtarving. Theſe Reflections, how idle ſoever they ſeem to the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, if taken into conſideration, would ſave you many a weary Step in the Day, and help <hi>G</hi> —<hi>y,</hi> to many an Hours ſleep, which he wants in the Night: But <hi>G</hi>—<hi>y</hi> would be rich; and, by my troth, there is ſome ſence in that: Pray remember me to him, and tell him, I wiſh him many Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, that his Soul may find reſt. You write me word, That I'm out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with a certain Poet, whom I have ever admir'd, for the diſproportion of him and his Attributes: He is a Rarity which I cannot but be fond of, as one would be of a Hog that could fiddle, or a ſinging Owl. If he falls upon me at the Blunt, which is his very good Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon in Wit, I will forgive him, if you pleaſe, and leave the Repartee to <hi>Black Will,</hi> with a Cudgel. And now, Dear <hi>Harry,</hi> if it may agree with your Affairs, to ſhew your ſelf in the Country this Summer, contrive ſuch a Crew toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as may not be aſham'd of paſſing by <hi>Woodſtock;</hi> and, if you can debauch Alderman <hi>G</hi>—<hi>y,</hi> we will make a ſhift to delight his Gravity. I am ſorry for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175033:12"/>the declining D—ſs, and would have you generous to her at this time; for that is true Pride, and I delight in it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ROCHESTER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:175033:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>Dear</hi> SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THIS Day I receiv'd the <hi>unhappy News</hi> of my own <hi>Death and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</hi> But, hearing what <hi>Heirs</hi> and <hi>Succeſſors</hi> were decreed me in <hi>my Place,</hi> and <hi>chiefly</hi> in <hi>my Lodgings,</hi> it was no ſmall Joy to me, that <hi>thoſe Tydings</hi> prove <hi>untrue;</hi> my Paſſion <hi>for Living,</hi> is ſo encreas'd, that I omit <hi>no Care of my ſelf;</hi> which, <hi>before,</hi> I never thought <hi>Life worth the trouble of taking.</hi> The King, who knows me to be a <hi>very ill-natur'd Man,</hi> will not think it <hi>an eaſie matter</hi> for me <hi>to die,</hi> now I <hi>live chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly out of ſpight.</hi> Dear Mr. <hi>Savile,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford me ſome News from your <hi>Land of the Living;</hi> and though I have little Curioſity to hear who's <hi>well,</hi> yet I would be <hi>glad</hi> my few <hi>Friends</hi> are <hi>ſo,</hi> of whom <hi>you</hi> are no more <hi>the leaſt</hi> than <hi>the lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi> I have <hi>better Compliments</hi> for you,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175033:13"/>but that may not look ſo ſincere as I would have you believe I am, when I profeſs my ſelf,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your faithful, affectionate, humble Servant, <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>Adderbury, <hi>near</hi> Banbury, <date>Feb. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>My Service to my Lord <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:175033:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am in a great ſtraight what to write to you; the ſtile of <hi>Buſineſs</hi> I am not vers'd in, and you may have forgot <hi>the familiar one</hi> we us'd hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. What Alterations <hi>Miniſtry</hi> makes in Men, is not to be imagined; though I can truſt with confidence all thoſe <hi>You</hi> are liable to, <hi>ſo well I know you,</hi> and <hi>ſo perfectly I love</hi> you. We are in ſuch a <hi>ſetled Happineſs,</hi> and ſuch <hi>merry Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> in this place, that, if it were not for <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> I could paſs my time very well, between <hi>my own Ill-nature,</hi> which inclines me very little to pity the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of <hi>malicious miſtaken Fools,</hi> and the <hi>Policies of the Times,</hi> which expoſe <hi>new Rarities</hi> of <hi>that kind</hi> every day. The News I have to ſend, and the ſort alone which could be ſo to <hi>you,</hi> are things <hi>Gyaris &amp; carcere digna;</hi> which I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:175033:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>dare not truſt to <hi>this pretty Fool, the Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> whom I heartily recommend to your <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Protection,</hi> and <hi>whoſe Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> will recommend him more; and truly, if it might ſuit with your <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter,</hi> at your times of leiſure, to Mr. <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi>'s Acquaintance, the happy Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence would be <hi>Singing,</hi> and in which your <hi>Excellence</hi> might have a ſhare not unworthy <hi>the greateſt Embaſſadors,</hi> nor to be deſpis'd even by a <hi>Cardinal-Legate;</hi> the <hi>greateſt and graveſt</hi> of <hi>this Court</hi> of <hi>both Sexes</hi> have taſted his <hi>Beauties;</hi> and, I'll aſſure you, <hi>Rome</hi> gains upon us <hi>here</hi> in <hi>this point</hi> mainly; and there is no part of the <hi>plot</hi> carried with ſo much <hi>Secreſie</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour</hi> as <hi>this.</hi> Proſelytes, of conſequence, are daily made, and Lord <hi>S</hi>—'s <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment</hi> is no <hi>check</hi> to any. An account of Mr. <hi>George Porter</hi>'s <hi>Retirement,</hi> upon News that Mr. <hi>Grimes,</hi> with <hi>one Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man more,</hi> had invaded <hi>England,</hi> Mr. <hi>S</hi>—'s Apology, for making Songs on the Duke of <hi>M.</hi> with his <hi>Oration-Conſolatory</hi> on my Lady <hi>D</hi>—'s Death, and a <hi>Politick Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertation</hi> between my Lady <hi>P</hi>—<hi>s</hi> and Capt. <hi>Dangerfield,</hi> with many other <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Treatiſes</hi> of the <hi>like nature,</hi> are things worthy your peruſal; but I durſt not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:175033:14"/>ſend 'em to you <hi>without leave,</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what <hi>Conſequence</hi> it might draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>Circumſtances</hi> and <hi>Character;</hi> but if they will admit <hi>a Correſpondence</hi> of that <hi>kind,</hi> in which <hi>alone</hi> I dare preſume to think my ſelf <hi>capable,</hi> I ſhall be very <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious</hi> in that way, or any <hi>other,</hi> to keep you from <hi>forgetting,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt affectionate, obliged, humble Servant, <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>White-hall,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Nov.</hi> 1. —79.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:175033:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WEre I as <hi>Idle</hi> as <hi>ever,</hi> which I ſhou'd not fail of being, if Health permitted; I wou'd write a ſmall <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance,</hi> and make <hi>the Sun</hi> with his <hi>diſhrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd Rays</hi> gild the Tops of <hi>the Palaces in Leather-lane:</hi> Then ſhou'd <hi>thoſe vile En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanters</hi> Barten <hi>and</hi> Ginman, lead forth their <hi>Illuſtrious Captives in chains of Quickſilver,</hi> and confining 'em by <hi>Charms</hi> to <hi>the loathſome Banks of a dead lake of Diet-drink;</hi> you, as my Friend, ſhou'd break the horrid Silence, and ſpeak <hi>the moſt paſſionate Fine things</hi> that ever <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick Lover</hi> utter'd; which being <hi>ſoftly</hi> and <hi>ſweetly</hi> reply'd to by Mrs. <hi>Roberts,</hi> ſhou'd <hi>rudely</hi> be <hi>interrupted</hi> by <hi>the envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> F—. Thus wou'd I lead the <hi>mournful Tale</hi> along, till <hi>the gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bath'd</hi> with the <hi>Tribute</hi> of his Eyes, <hi>the Names</hi> of ſuch <hi>unfortunate Lovers</hi>—
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:175033:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſenſible, that it is <hi>Natural</hi> for you to be <hi>kind</hi> to me, and can <hi>never more</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of it.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>I am your faithful, oblig'd, humble Servant,</hi> ROCHESTER.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Biſhop-Stafford,</hi> 
                     <date>Apr. 5. 80.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:175033:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE, Embaſſador in <hi>FRANCE. Begun,</hi> White-hall, May 30th, 79<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>'TIS neither <hi>Pride</hi> or <hi>Neglect</hi> (for I am not of <hi>the new Council,</hi> and I love you <hi>ſincerely</hi>) but <hi>Idleneſs</hi> on one ſide, and not <hi>knowing</hi> what to ſay on the <hi>other,</hi> has hindred me from writing to you, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo <hi>kind a Letter,</hi> and <hi>the Preſent</hi> you ſent me, for which I return you at laſt my humble Thanks. <hi>Changes</hi> in <hi>this place</hi> are <hi>ſo frequent,</hi> that <hi>F</hi>—<hi>himſelf</hi> can now no longer give an account, why this was done <hi>to Day,</hi> or what will enſue to <hi>Morrow;</hi> and <hi>Accidents</hi> are <hi>ſo extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant,</hi> that my Lord <hi>W</hi>— intending to <hi>Lie,</hi> has, with a <hi>Prophetick Spirit, once told truth.</hi> Every Man <hi>in this Court</hi> thinks he ſtands fair for <hi>Miniſter;</hi> ſome give it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:175033:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>to <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> others to <hi>Hallifax;</hi> but Mr. <hi>Waller</hi> ſays <hi>S</hi>—does all; I am ſure my Lord <hi>A</hi>—does little, which your Excellence will eaſily believe. And now the War in <hi>Scotland</hi> takes up all the Diſcourſe of <hi>Politick Perſons.</hi> His Grace of <hi>Lauderdale</hi> values himſelf upon the <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and tells the King, It is very <hi>auſpicious</hi> and <hi>advantageous to the drift of the preſent Councils:</hi> The reſt of the <hi>Scots,</hi> and eſpecially D. <hi>H</hi>—are very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive after <hi>News</hi> from <hi>Scotland,</hi> and really make <hi>a handſome Figure</hi> in <hi>this Conjuncture</hi> at <hi>London.</hi> What the D. of <hi>Monmouth</hi> will effect, is now the general <hi>Expectation,</hi> who took <hi>Post unexpectedly,</hi> left <hi>all</hi> that had offer'd their Service in <hi>this Expedition,</hi> in <hi>the lurch;</hi> and, being attended only by Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong,</hi> and Mr. <hi>C</hi>—will, without queſtion, have the <hi>full Glory</hi> as well of the <hi>Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> as the <hi>Military Part</hi> of this <hi>Action entire to himſelf.</hi> The moſt <hi>Profound Politicians</hi> have weighty <hi>Brows,</hi> and <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Aſpects</hi> at preſent, upon a <hi>Report</hi> crept abroad, <hi>That Mr.</hi> Langhorn, <hi>to ſave his Life, offers a Diſcovery of</hi> Prieſts, <hi>and</hi> Jeſuits <hi>Lands, to the value of Fourſcore and ten thouſand Pounds a Year;</hi> which being
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:175033:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>accepted, it is fear'd, <hi>Partiſans</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakers</hi> will be found out to advance a conſiderable Sum of <hi>Money,</hi> upon this <hi>Fund,</hi> to the <hi>utter Interruption of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> and the <hi>Deſtruction of many hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Deſigns.</hi> This, I muſt call <hi>God</hi> to witneſs, was never hinted to me in <hi>the least</hi> by Mr. <hi>P</hi>— to whom I beg you will give me your hearty Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Thus much to afford you a taſte of my <hi>ſerious Abilities,</hi> and to let you know I have a great <hi>Goggle-eye</hi> to <hi>Buſineſs:</hi> And now I cannot deny you a ſhare in the <hi>high ſatisfaction</hi> I have receiv'd at the account which flouriſhes here of your high <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> at <hi>Paris: Charenton</hi> was never ſo honour'd, as ſince your <hi>Reſidence</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> to that <hi>Degree,</hi> that it is not doubted if the <hi>Parliament</hi> be ſitting at your Return, or otherwiſe the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Common-Council,</hi> will petition the <hi>King</hi> you may be <hi>Dignified</hi> with the <hi>Title of that place,</hi> by way of <hi>Earldom,</hi> or <hi>Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as his</hi> Majeſty <hi>ſhall think most proper to give, or you accept.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>S</hi>— is a Man of that <hi>Tenderneſs of Heart, and approv'd Humanity,</hi> that he will doubtleſs be highly <hi>afflicted</hi> when he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:175033:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>hears of the <hi>unfortunate Pilgrims,</hi> tho' he appears <hi>very obdurate</hi> to the <hi>Complaints</hi> of <hi>his own best Concubine,</hi> and <hi>your fair Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman M</hi>—who now ſtarves. The Packet inclos'd in your laſt, I read with all the ſence of Compaſſion it merits, and if I can prove ſo unexpectedly happy to ſucceed in my <hi>Endeavours</hi> for that Fair Unfortunate, ſhe ſhall have a ſpeedy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. I thank <hi>God,</hi> there is yet a <hi>Harry Savile</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> with whom I drink your Health laſt Week, at Sir <hi>William Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventry</hi>'s: and who, in <hi>Features, Proportion</hi> and <hi>Pledging,</hi> gives me ſo <hi>lively</hi> an <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Your ſelf,</hi> that I am reſolv'd to retire into <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> and enjoy him till <hi>Shiloe</hi> come, or <hi>You</hi> from <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ROCHESTER.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Ended</hi> 
                     <date>the 25th of June, 1679.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:175033:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ANY kind of Correſpondence with ſuch a Friend as You, is very agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and therefore You will eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, I am very ill when I loſe the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of writing to You: But Mr. <hi>Povy</hi> comes into my Mind, and hinders far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Compliment: In a plainer way I muſt tell You, I pray for <hi>Your happy Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> but was not at all ſorry for Your <hi>glorious Diſgrace,</hi> which is an Honour, conſidering the <hi>Cauſe.</hi> I wou'd ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the <hi>Serious</hi> part (as You were pleas'd to call it) of Your <hi>former</hi> Letter; but it will diſgrace my <hi>Politicks</hi> to differ from yours, who have wrought now ſome time under the <hi>best</hi> and <hi>keenest Stateſmen</hi> our <hi>Cabinet</hi> boaſts of: But, to confeſs the Truth, my Advice to the Lady You wot of, has ever been this, <hi>Take Your Meaſures just contrary to Your</hi> Rivals, <hi>live in Peace with all the World, and eaſily with the</hi> King:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:175033:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Never be ſo Ill-natur'd to ſtir up his Anger against others, but let him forget the uſe of a Paſſion, which is never to do You good: Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh his Love where-ever it inclines, and be aſſur'd You can't commit greater Folly, than pretending to be Jealous; but, on the contrary, with Hand, Body, Head, Heart, and all the Faculties You have, contribute to his Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure all You can, and comply with his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires throughout: And, for new Intrigues, ſo You be at one end, 'tis no matter which: Make Sport when You can, at other times help it.</hi> — Thus I have given You an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how unfit I am to give the Advice You propos'd: Beſides this, You may judge, whether I was a good <hi>Pimp,</hi> or no. But ſome thought <hi>otherwiſe;</hi> and ſo truly I have renounc'd <hi>Buſineſs;</hi> let abler Men try it. More a great deal I would ſay, but upon this Subject; and, for this time, I beg this may ſuffice, from</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble and most affectionate faithful Servant, <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:175033:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>'TIS not that I am the idleſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture living, and only chuſe to imploy my Thoughts rather upon my Friends, than to languiſh all the Day in the tediouſneſs of doing nothing, that I write to You; but owning, that (tho' You excel moſt Men in Friendſhip and good Nature) You are not quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from all Humane Frailty; I ſend this to hinder You from forgetting a Man who loves You very heartily. The <hi>World,</hi> ever ſince I can remember, has been ſtill ſo inſupportably the ſame, that 'twere vain to hope there were any alterations; and therefore I can have no <hi>Curioſity</hi> for <hi>News;</hi> only I wou'd be glad to know if the <hi>Parliament</hi> be like to ſit any time; for the <hi>Peers</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> being grown of late Years very conſiderable in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I wou'd make one at the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>Livy</hi> and Sickneſs has a littlein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd me to <hi>Policy;</hi> when I come to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:175033:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Town, I make no queſtion but to change that <hi>Folly</hi> for ſome leſs; whether <hi>Wine</hi> or <hi>Women</hi> I know not; according as my <hi>Conſtitution</hi> ſerves me: Till when (Dear <hi>Harry</hi>) Farewel! When You Dine at my Lord <hi>Liſle</hi>'s, let me be remembred.</p>
               <p>Kings and Princes are only as Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, as what they <hi>pretend</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent; but apparently as frail as Thoſe they Govern.— This is a Seaſon of Tribulation; and I piouſly beg of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty <hi>God,</hi> that the <hi>ſtrict ſeverity</hi> ſhewn to one ſcandalous <hi>Sin</hi> amongſt us, may expiate for all grievous <hi>Calamities.</hi>— So help them <hi>God,</hi> whom it concerns!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:175033:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF Sack and Sugar be a ſin,</hi> God <hi>help the Wicked;</hi> was the Saying of a merry fat Gentleman, who liv'd in Days of <hi>Yore,</hi> lov'd a Glaſs of <hi>Wine,</hi> wou'd be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with a Friend, and ſometimes had an unlucky Fancy for a Wench. Now (dear Mr. <hi>Savile</hi>) forgive me, if I confeſs, that, upon ſeveral occaſions, you have put me in Mind of this fat <hi>Perſon,</hi> and now more particularly, for thinking upon your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Circumſtances, I cannot but ſay with my ſelf, If loving a pretty Woman, and hating <hi>Lautherdale,</hi> bring Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and <hi>Pox,</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> have mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on poor <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>S</hi>—<hi>s!</hi> But, by this time, all your Inconveniences (for, to a Man of your very good Sence, no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Accidents are more) draw very near their end: For my own part, I'm taking pains not to die, without knowing how to live on, when I have brought it about: But moſt Human Affairs are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:175033:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>on at the ſame <hi>Non-ſenſical</hi> rate, which makes me, (who am now grown <hi>Superſtitious</hi>) think it a Fault to laugh at the <hi>Monkey</hi> we have here, when I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his <hi>Condition</hi> with <hi>Mankind.</hi> You will be very Good-natur'd, if you keep your Word, and write to me ſometimes: And ſo Good-night, dear Mr. <hi>Savile.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ROCHESTER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:175033:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHether <hi>Love, Wine,</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> (which rule you by turns) have the preſent <hi>Aſcendant,</hi> I cannot pretend to determine at this diſtance; but <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature,</hi> which waits about you with more diligence than <hi>Godfrey</hi> himſelf, is my <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity,</hi> that you are <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmindful</hi> of your ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Friends: To be from you, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by you at once, is a <hi>Misfortune</hi> I never was criminal enough to <hi>merit,</hi> ſince to the Black and Fair <hi>Counteſs,</hi> I villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly <hi>betray'd</hi> the Daily Addreſſes of your divided Heart: You forgave that upon the <hi>firſt Bottle,</hi> and upon the <hi>ſecond,</hi> on my Conſcience, wou'd have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd <hi>them, and the whole Sex;</hi> Oh! <hi>That ſecond Bottle</hi> (Harry!) <hi>is the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſt, Wiſeſt, and moſt Impartial Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Friend we have;</hi> tells us truth of <hi>Our ſelves,</hi> and forces Us to ſpeak Truths
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:175033:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>others;</hi> baniſhes <hi>Flattery</hi> from our <hi>Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Diſtruſt</hi> from our <hi>Hearts,</hi> ſets us above the <hi>mean Policy of Court-Prudence;</hi> which makes us lie to one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>all Day,</hi> for fear of being <hi>Betray'd</hi> by each other <hi>at Night.</hi> And (before <hi>God</hi>) I believe the <hi>erranteſt Villain breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is honeſt as long as that Bottle lives,</hi> and few of <hi>that Tribe</hi> dare venture upon him, at leaſt, among the <hi>Courtiers</hi> and <hi>Stateſmen.</hi> I have ſeriouſly conſider'd one thing, That the three Buſineſſes of this Age, <hi>Women, Politicks,</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> the <hi>laſt</hi> is the only Exerciſe at which you and I have not prov'd our ſelves <hi>errant Fumblers:</hi> If you have the <hi>Vanity</hi> to think <hi>otherwiſe;</hi> when we meet, let us appeal to Friends of <hi>both Sexes,</hi> and as they ſhall determine, live and die <hi>their Drunkards,</hi> or <hi>entire Lovers.</hi> For, as we mince the Matter, it is hard to ſay which is the moſt <hi>tireſome Creature, Loving Drunkard,</hi> or the <hi>Drunken Lover.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you ventur'd Your fat <hi>Buttock a Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop</hi> to <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> I doubt not but thro' extream <hi>Galling,</hi> you now lie Bed-rid of the <hi>Piles,</hi> or <hi>Fiſtula</hi> in <hi>Ano,</hi> and have the leiſure to write to your Country Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:175033:22"/>which if you omit, I ſhall take the Liberty to conclude you <hi>very Proud. Such a Letter</hi> ſhou'd be directed to me at <hi>Adderbury,</hi> near <hi>Banbury,</hi> where I intend to be within theſe three Days. From</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your obedient humble Servant,</hi> Rochester.</signed>
                  <dateline>Bath, <date>
                        <hi>the</hi> 22d <hi>of</hi> June</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:175033:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHether <hi>Love,</hi> or the <hi>Politicks</hi> have the greater Intereſt in your Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>France,</hi> becauſe it is argu'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>wiſer</hi> Men, I will not conclude upon; but hoping ſo much from your Friendſhip, that, without reſerve, you will truſt me with the time of your ſtay in <hi>Paris;</hi> I have writ this to aſſure you, if it can continue a Month, I will not fail to wait on you there. My Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are to improve this Winter, for the Improvement of my Parts in <hi>Foreign Countries;</hi> and if the <hi>Temptation</hi> of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, be added to the <hi>Deſies</hi> I have already, the Sin is ſo ſweet, that I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to embrace it, and leave out of my Prayers, <hi>Libera nos a malo— For thine is,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ROCHESTER.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Oxford,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb.</hi> 5.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:175033:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>'TIS not the <hi>Leaſt</hi> of my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, that I think you love me; but the <hi>Firſt</hi> of all my <hi>Pretenſions</hi> is to make it appear, that I faithfully endeavour to <hi>deſerve</hi> it. If there be a <hi>Real good</hi> upon Earth, 'tis in the <hi>Name of FRIEND,</hi> without which all others are meer fantaſtical. How few of us are fit ſtuff to make that thing, we have daily the melancholly Experience.</p>
               <p>However, dear <hi>Harry!</hi> Let us not give out, nor deſpair of bringing that about, which, as it is the moſt difficult, and rare Accident of Life, is alſo the beſt; nay, (perhaps) the only good one. This Thought has ſo entirely poſſeſs'd me ſince I came into the Country,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:175033:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>(where, only, one can think; for, you at Court think not at all; or, at leaſt, as if you were ſhut up in a Drum; as you think of nothing, but the Noiſe that is made about you) that I have made many Serious Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon it, and, amongſt others, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd one Maxime, which I deſire, ſhou'd be communicated to our Friend Mr. <hi>G</hi>—; That, <hi>We are bound in</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality <hi>and common</hi> Honeſty, <hi>to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour after Competent Riches;</hi> ſince it is certain, that few Men, if any, uneaſie in their Fortunes, have prov'd firm and clear in their Friendſhips. A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poor Fellow, is a very poor Friend; and not one of a thouſand can be good natur'd to another, who is not pleas'd within himſelf. But while I grow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Proverbs, I forget that you may impute my Philoſophy to the <hi>Dog-days,</hi> and living alone. To prevent the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences of Solitude, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I intend to go to the <hi>Bath</hi> on Sunday next, in Viſitation to my Lord Treaſurer. Be ſo Politick, or be ſo Kind, (or a little of both, which is better) as to ſtep down thither, if
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:175033:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>famous Affairs at <hi>Windſor,</hi> do not detain you. Dear <hi>Harry,</hi> I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Hearty, Faithful, Affectionate, Humble Servant, <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>If you ſee the Dutcheſs of <hi>P</hi>— ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry often, take ſome opportunity to talk to her about what I ſpoke to you at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:175033:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF it were the Sign of an honeſt Man, to be happy in his Friends, ſure I were mark'd out for the worſt of Men; ſince no one ne'er loſt ſo many as I have done, or knew to make ſo few. The Severity you ſay the Dutcheſs of <hi>P</hi>— ſhews to me, is a proof, that 'tis not in my power to deſerve well of Any-body; ſince (I call Truth to witneſs) I have never been guilty of an Errour, that I know, to her: And this may be a Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you, that remain in the Miſtake of being kind to me, never to expect a grateful Return; ſince I am<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo utterly ignorant how to make it: To value you in my Thoughts, to prefer you in my Wiſhes, to ſerve you in my Words; to obſerve, ſtudy, and to obey you in all my Actions, is too little; ſince I have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed all this to her, without ſo much
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:175033:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>as an Offenſive Accident. And yet ſhe thinks it juſt, to uſe me ill. If I were not malicious enough to hope ſhe were in the wrong, I muſt have a very melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly Opinion of my ſelf. I wiſh your Intereſt might prevail with her, as a Friend of her's, not mine, to tell how I have deſerv'd it of her, ſince ſhe has ne'er accus'd me of any Crime, but of being Cunning; and I told her, Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body had been Cunninger than I, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade her ſo. I can as well ſupport the Hatred of the whole World, as Any<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body, not being generally fond of it. Thoſe whom I have oblig'd, may uſe me with Ingratitude, and not afflict me much: But to be injur'd by thoſe who have oblig'd me, and to whoſe Service I am ever bound; is ſuch a Curſe, as I can only wiſh on them who wrong me to the Dutcheſs.</p>
               <p>I hope you have not forgot what <hi>G</hi>—<hi>y</hi> and you have promis'd me; but within ſome time you will come and fetch me to <hi>London:</hi> I ſhall ſcarce think of coming, till you call me, as not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving many prevalent Motives to draw me to the Court, if it be ſo that my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:175033:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>has no need of my Service, nor my Friends of my Company.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Shepheard</hi> is a Man of a fluent Stile, and coherent Thought; if, as I ſuſpect, he writ your Poſtſcript.</p>
               <p>I wiſh my Lord <hi>Hallifax</hi> Joy of every Thing, and of his Daughter to boot.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Rochester.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:175033:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU, who have known me theſe ten Years the Grievance of all prudent Perſons, the By-word of Stateſmen, the Scorn of ugly Ladies, which are very near All, and the irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable Averſion of fine Gentlemen, who are the Ornamental Part of a Nation, and yet found me ſeldom ſad, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe weighty Oppreſſions; can you think that the loving of lean Arms, ſmall Legs, red Eyes and Noſe, (if you will conſider that trifle too) can have the power to depreſs the Natural <hi>Alacrity</hi> of my careleſs Soul; eſpecially upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving a fine Letter from Mr. <hi>Savile,</hi> which never wants Wit, and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature; two Qualities able to tranſport my Heart with Joy, tho' it were break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? I wonder at <hi>M</hi>—'s flaunting it in Court with ſuch fine Clothes; ſure he is an alter'd Perſon ſince I ſaw him;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:175033:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>for, ſince I can remember, neither his own ſelf, nor any belonging to him, were ever out of Rags: His Page alone was well cloath'd of all his Family, and that but in appearance: for, of late he has made no more of wearing Second-hand <hi>C</hi>—<hi>ts,</hi> than Second-hand <hi>Shooes;</hi> tho' I muſt confeſs, to his Honour, he chang'd 'em oftner. I wiſh the <hi>King</hi> were ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly advis'd about a main Advantage in this Marriage, which may poſſibly be omitted; I mean, the ridding his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of ſome old Beauties, and young Deformities, who ſwarm, and are a Grievance to his Liege People. A Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince ought to behave himſelf like a Kite, who is allow'd to take one Royal Chick for his Reward; but then 'tis expected, before he leaves the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, his Flock ſhall clear the whole Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of all the Garbage and Carrion many Miles about. The <hi>King</hi> had never ſuch an Opportunity; for the <hi>Dutch</hi> are very foul Feeders, and what they leave he muſt never hope to be rid of unleſs he ſet up an Intrigue with the <hi>Tartars</hi> or <hi>Coſſacks.</hi> For the Libel you ſpeak of, upon that moſt unwitty Generation, the preſent <hi>Poets,</hi> I rejoyce in it with all my Heart,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:175033:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſhall take it for a Favour, if you will ſend me a Copy. He cannot want Wit utterly, that has a Spleen to thoſe Rogues, tho' never ſo dully expreſs'd. And, now dear Mr. <hi>Savile,</hi> forgive me, if I do not wind up my ſelf with an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Period.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ROCHESTER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:175033:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THo' I am almoſt <hi>Blind,</hi> utterly <hi>Lame,</hi> and ſcarce within the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable hopes of ever ſeeing <hi>London</hi> again, I am not yet ſo wholly mortified and dead to the taſte of all Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, not to be extreamly reviv'd at the receipt of a kind Letter from an Old Friend, who in all probability might have laid me aſide in his Thoughts, if not quite forgot me by this time. I ever thought you an extraordinary Man, and muſt now think you ſuch a Friend, who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Courtier, as you are, can love a Man, whom it is the great Mode to hate. Catch Sir <hi>G. H.</hi> or Sir <hi>Carr,</hi> at ſuch an ill-bred Proceeding, and I am miſtaken: For the hideous Deportment, which you have heard of, concerning running naked, ſo much is true, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:175033:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>we went into the River ſomewhat late in the Year, and had a Frisk for forty Yards in the Meadow, to dry our ſelves. I will appeal to the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Duke,</hi> if they had not done as much; nay, my Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> and the <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> both, when they were <hi>School-boys?</hi> And, at theſe Years, I have heard the one Declai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med like <hi>Cicero,</hi> the others Preached like St. <hi>Auſtin:</hi> Prudenter Perſons, I conclude, they were, ev'n in Hanging-ſleeves, than any of the flaſhy Fry, (of which I muſt own my ſelf the moſt unſolid) can hope to appear, ev'n in their ripeſt Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
               <p>And now, (Mr. <hi>Savile</hi>) ſince you are pleas'd to quote your ſelf for a grave Man of the number of the Scandalizd, be pleas'd to call to Mind the Year 1676, when two large fat <hi>Nudities</hi> led the <hi>Coranto</hi> round <hi>Roſamond</hi>'s fair Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, while the poor violated <hi>Nymph</hi> wept to behold the ſtrange Decay of Manly Parts, ſince the Days of her dear <hi>Harry</hi> the Second: P— ('tis confeſs'd) you ſhew'd but little of; but for A—and B—, (a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:175033:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Oſtentation! God</hi> wot) you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd more of that Naſtineſs in your two Folio Volumes, than we altogether in our ſix Quarto's. <hi>Pluck therefore the Beam out of thine own Eye,</hi> &amp;c. And now 'tis time to thank you for your kind inviting me to <hi>London,</hi> to make <hi>Dutch-men</hi> merry; a thing I would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, like, killing <hi>Punaiſes,</hi> the filthy Savour of <hi>Dutch-mirth</hi> being more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible. If <hi>GOD,</hi> in Mercy, has made 'em huſh and melancholly, do not you rouze their ſleeping <hi>Mirth,</hi> to make the Town mourn; the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> is exalted above 'em, and I cou'd wiſh my ſelf in Town to ſerve him in ſome refind Pleaſures; which, I fear, you are too much a <hi>Dutch-man</hi> to think of.</p>
               <p>The beſt preſent I can make at this time is the Bearer, whom I beg you to take care of, that the <hi>King</hi> may hear his Tunes, when he is eaſie and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate; becauſe I am ſure they will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him extreamly: And may he ever have <hi>Harmony</hi> in his Mind, as this Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low will pour it into his Ears: May
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:175033:29"/>he dream pleaſantly, wake joyfully, love ſafely, and tenderly, live long and happily; ever pray (Dear <hi>Savile</hi>) <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n-Bougre laſsé qui era toute ſa foutue reſte de Vie,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Voſtre fidel Amy &amp; tres humble Serviteur,</hi> ROCHESTER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:175033:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THAT Night I receiv'd by Yours the ſurprizing Account of my Lady <hi>Dutcheſs</hi>'s more than ordinary In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt me, I was newly brought in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> dead of a Fall from my Horſe, of which I ſtill remain Bruis'd and Bed-rid, and can now ſcarce think it a Happineſs that I ſav'd my Neck. What ill <hi>Star</hi> reigns over me, that I'm ſtill mark'd out for <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> and only us'd barbarouſly to thoſe I am obligd to! Had I been troubleſom to her in pinning the Dependance of my <hi>Fortune</hi> upon her Solicitations to the <hi>King,</hi> or her Unme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Recommendations of me to ſome Great Man, it would not have mov'd my Wonder much, if ſhe had ſought any Occaſion to be rid of a uſeleſs Trouble: But, a Creature, who had already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivd of her all the Obligations he ever could pretend to, except the continuance
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:175033:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>of her good Opinion, for the which he reſolv'd, and did direct every ſtep of his Life in Duty and Service to her, and all who were concern'd in her; why ſhould ſhe take the Advantage of a falſe idle Story, to hate ſuch a Man; as if it were an Inconveniency to her to be harmleſs, or a Pain to continue juſt? By that <hi>God</hi> that made me, I have no more offended her in Thought, Word, or Deed, no more imagin'd or utter'd the leaſt Thought to her Contempt or Prejudice, than I have plotted <hi>Treaſon,</hi> conceal'd Arms, Train'd Regiments for a <hi>Rebellion.</hi> If there be upon <hi>Earth</hi> a Man of <hi>Common Honeſty,</hi> who will juſtifie a Tittle of her Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I am contented never to ſee her. After this, ſhe need not forbid me to come to her, I have little Pride or Pleaſure in ſhewing my ſelf where I am accus'd of a Meanneſs I were not capable of, even for her Service, which would prove a ſhrewder Tryal of my <hi>Honeſty,</hi> than any Ambition I ever had to make my Court to. I thought the Dutcheſs of <hi>P</hi>— more an Angel than I find her a Woman; and as this is the firſt, it ſhall be the moſt malicious thing I will ever ſay of her. For her generous Reſolution of not hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:175033:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>me to the <hi>King,</hi> I thank her; but ſhe muſt think a Man much oblig'd, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the calling of him Knave, to ſay ſhe will do him no farther Prejudice. For the Counteſs of <hi>P</hi>—, whatever ſhe has heard me ſay, or any body elſe, of her, I'll ſtand the <hi>Teſt</hi> of any Impartial Judge, 'twas neither injurious nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly; and how ſevere ſoever ſhe pleaſes to be, I have always been her humble Servant, and will continue ſo. I do not know how to aſſure my ſelf the D. will ſpare me to the <hi>King,</hi> who would not to you ; I'm ſure ſhe can't ſay I ever injur'd you to her; nor am I at all afraid ſhe can hurt me with you; I dare ſwear you don't think I have dealt ſo indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly in my Service to her, as to doubt me in the Friendſhip I proſeſs to you. And, to ſhew you I rely upon yours, let me beg of you to talk once more with her, and deſire her to give me the fair hearing ſhe wou'd afford any Footman of hers, who had been complain'd of to her by a leſs-worthy Creature, (for ſuch a one, I aſſure my ſelf, my Accuſer is) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be for her Service, to wrong the moſt faithful of her Servants; and then I ſhall be proud of mine. I would not be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:175033:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>run down by a Company of Rogues, and this looks like an Endeavour towards it: Therefore, Dear <hi>Harry,</hi> ſend me word, how I am with other Folks; if you viſit my Lord Treaſurer, name the Calamity of this matter to him, and tell me ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely how he takes it: and, if you hear the <hi>King</hi> mention me, do the Office of a Friend, to</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:175033:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SAVILE,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THE Louſineſs of Affairs in this Place, is ſuch (forgive the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly Phraſe! Expreſſions mult de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the Nature of things expreſs'd) 'tis not fit to entertain a private Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, much leſs one of a publick Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter with the Retail of them; the general Heads, under which this whole Iſland may be conſider'd, are Spies, Beggars and Rebels, the Tranſpoſitions and mixtures of theſe, make an agreeable Variety; Buſie <hi>Fools,</hi> and Cautious <hi>Knaves</hi> are bred out of them, and ſet off wonderfully; tho' of this latter ſort, we have fewer now than ever, <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> being the only Vice in decay amongſt us, few Men here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble their being Raſcals; and no Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man diſowns being a Whore. Mr. <hi>O</hi>— was try'd two Days ago for <hi>Buggery,</hi> and clear'd: The next Day he brought
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:175033:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Action to the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> againſt his Accuſer, being attended by the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and other Peers, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Seven, for the Honour of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Cauſe.</hi> I have ſent you here with a Libel, in which my own ſhare is not the leaſt; the <hi>King</hi> having perus'd it, is no ways diſſatisfied with his: The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is apparent Mr.—, his Patron my L— having a Panegyrick in the midſt; upon which happen'd a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Quarrel between his L—, and Mrs. <hi>B</hi>— at the Dutcheſs of <hi>P</hi>—; ſhe call'd him, The Heroe of the Libel, and complimented him upon having made more Cuckolds, than any Man alive; to which he anſwer'd, She very well knew one he never made, nor never car'd to be imploy'd in making.— Rogue and Bitch enſued, till the <hi>King,</hi> taking his Grand-father's Character upon him, became the Peace-maker. I will not trouble you any longer, but beg you ſtill to Love</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your faithful, humble Servant, <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:175033:32"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> HENRY SAVILE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>HARRY,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU are the <hi>Only</hi> Man of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that keep <hi>Wit</hi> with your <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> and I am happy in a <hi>Friend</hi> that excels in both; were your <hi>Good-nature</hi> the leaſt of your <hi>Good Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities,</hi> I durſt not preſume upon it, as I have done; but I know you are ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely concern'd in ſerving your Friends truly, that I need not make an <hi>Apology</hi> for the trouble I have given you in this Affair.</p>
               <p>I daily expect more conſiderable Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of your Friendſhip, and have the <hi>Vanity</hi> to think, I ſhall be the better for your growing poorer.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, when you pleaſe to diſtinguiſh from <hi>Proſers</hi> and <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and comply with <hi>Roſers</hi> and <hi>Bull,</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:175033:33"/>not forgetting <hi>John Stevens,</hi> you ſhall find me</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most Ready and most Obedient Servant, <hi>ROCHESTER.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>
                  <hi>The End of the late Earl of</hi> Rocheſter<hi>'s Letters.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:175033:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE <hi>E. of</hi> L—<hi>'s LETTER</hi> To the Honourable ALGERNOON SIDNEY.</head>
            <p>DIſuſe of Writing has made it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie to me, Age makes it hard, and the Weakneſs of Sight and Hand, makes it almoſt impoſſible. This may excuſe me to <hi>Every-body,</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to <hi>You,</hi> who have not invited me much unto it, but rather have given me cauſe to think, that you were willing to ſave me the labour of Writing, and your ſelf the trouble of Reading my Letters: For, after you had left me ſick, ſolitary and ſad, at <hi>Penſhurſt,</hi> and that you had reſolved to undertake the Employment wherein you have lately been, you nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came to give me a <hi>Farewel,</hi> nor did ſo much as ſend one to me, but only writ a wrangling Letter or two concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:175033:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mony, and <hi>Hoskins,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Honywood</hi>'s Horſe; and tho' both before and after your going out of <hi>England,</hi> you writ to divers other Perſons, the firſt Letter that I received from you, was dated, as I remember, the 13th of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptember;</hi> the ſecond in <hi>November,</hi> wherein you take notice of your Mother's Death; and if there were one more, that was all, until Mr. <hi>Sterry</hi> came, who made ſuch haſte from <hi>Penſhurſt,</hi> that coming very late at Night, he would not ſtay to Dine the next Day, nor to give me time to <hi>Write.</hi> It is true, that ſince the Change of Affairs here, and of your Condition there, your Letters have been more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent; and if I had not thought my Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence better both for you and my ſelf, I would have written more than once or twice unto you; but tho', for ſome Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, I did forbear, I failed not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire others to write unto you, and with their <hi>own,</hi> to convey the beſt Advice that my little Intelligence, and weak Judgment could afford; particularly not to expect <hi>New Authorities nor Orders from hence, not to ſtay in any of the places of your Negotiation, not to come into</hi> England, <hi>much leſs to expect a Ship to be ſent for you;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:175033:34"/>or to think, that an Account was, or wou'd be expected of you here,</hi> unleſs it were of <hi>Matters very different from your Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions there; that it wou'd be beſt for you preſently to diveſt your ſelf of the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of a</hi> Publick Miniſter, <hi>to diſmiſs all your Train, and to retire into ſome ſafe place, not very near, nor very far from</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>that you might hear from your Friends ſometimes.</hi> And for this I advis'd <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> where I hear you are, by your Man <hi>Powel,</hi> or by them that have receiv'd Letters from you, with Preſents of Wine and Fiſh, which I do not reproach nor envy.</p>
            <p>Your laſt Letter to me had no Date of Time or Place; but by another at the ſame time to Sir <hi>John Temple,</hi> of the 28th of <hi>July,</hi> as I remember, ſent by Mr. <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonden,</hi> I gueſs that mine was of the ſame Date: By thoſe that I have had, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that you have been miſadvertiz'd; for tho' I met with no Effects, nor Marks of Diſpleaſure, yet I find no ſuch Tokens or Fruits of <hi>Favour,</hi> as may give me ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Credit</hi> for thoſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings</hi> and <hi>Good Offices,</hi> which, perhaps you expect of me.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:175033:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> And now I am again upon the Point of retiring to my poor Habitation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for my ſelf no other Deſign, than to paſs the ſmall remainder of my Days in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently and quietly; and if it pleaſe <hi>GOD,</hi> to be gathered in Peace to my Fathers. And concerning you, what to reſolve in my ſelf, or what to adviſe you, truly I know not: For you muſt give me leave to remember of how little Weight my Opinions and Counſels have been with you, and how unkindly and unfriend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you have rejected thoſe Exhortations and Admonitions, which in much Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Kindneſs I have given you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many Occaſions, and in almoſt every thing, from the higheſt to the loweſt, that hath concern'd you; and this you may think ſufficient to diſcourage me from putting my Advices into the like Danger: Yet, ſomewhat I will ſay: And, Firſt, I think it unfit, and (perhaps) as yet, unſafe for you to come into <hi>England;</hi> for, I believe, <hi>Powel</hi> hath told you, that he heard, when he was here, <hi>That you were likely to be excepted out of the General Act of Pardon and Oblivion:</hi> And tho' I know not what you have done, or ſaid here or there, yet I have ſeveral ways
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:175033:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>heard, That there is as ill an Opinion of you, as of any, even of thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the late <hi>King:</hi> And when I thought there was no other Exception to you, than your being of the other Party, I ſpoke to the General in your behalf, who told me, That very ill Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces had been done you, but he would aſſiſt you as much as juſtly he could; and I intended then alſo to ſpeak to Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body elſe; you may gueſs whom I mean: But ſince that, I have heard ſuch things of you, that in the doubtfulneſs only of their being true, no Man will open his Mouth for you. I will tell you ſome Paſſages, and you ſhall do well to clear your ſelf of them. It is ſaid, That the Univerſity of <hi>Copenhagen</hi> brought their <hi>Album</hi> unto you, deſiring you to write ſomething therein, and that you did <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere in albo</hi> theſe Words,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Manus haec inimica Tyrannis,</l>
               <l>Enſe petit placida cum Libertate quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem:</l>
            </q>
            <p>And put your Name to it. This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but be publickly known, if it be true. It is ſaid alſo, That a <hi>Miniſter,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:175033:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>who hath married a Lady <hi>Laurence</hi> here of <hi>Chelſey,</hi> but now dwelling at <hi>Copen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hagen,</hi> being there in Company with you, ſaid, I think you were none of the late <hi>King's</hi> Judges, nor guilty of his Death, meaning our <hi>King. Guilty!</hi> ſaid you; <hi>Do you call that Guilt? Why, 'twas the juſteſt and braveſt Action that ever was done in</hi> England, <hi>or any where elſe;</hi> with other Words to the ſame effect. It is ſaid alſo, That you having heard of a Deſign to ſeize upon you, or to cauſe you to be taken Priſoner, you took notice of it to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> himſelf, and ſaid, <hi>I hear there is a Deſign to ſeize upon me: But who is it that hath that Deſign?</hi> Eſtce noſtre Bandit. By which you are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to mean the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this, it is reported, That you have been heard to ſay many ſcornful and contemptuous things of the <hi>King</hi>'s Perſon and Family; which unleſs you can juſtifie your ſelf, will hardly be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given or forgotten: For, ſuch Perſonal Offences make deeper Impreſſions than Publick Actions either of <hi>War</hi> or <hi>Treaty.</hi> Here is a <hi>Reſident,</hi> as he calls himſelf, of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> whoſe Name (as I
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:175033:36"/>hear) is <hi>Pedcombe;</hi> he hath viſited me, and offered his readineſs to give you any Aſſiſtance in his Power or Credit with the Embaſſadour, Mr. <hi>Alfield,</hi> who was then expected, and is now arrived here, and hath had his firſt Audience. I have not ſeen Mr. <hi>Pedcombe</hi> ſince; but, within a few Days, I will put him in Mind of his Profeſſion of <hi>Friendſhip</hi> to you, and try what he can or will do. Sir <hi>Robert Honywood</hi> is alſo come hither; and, as I hear, the <hi>King</hi> is graciouſly pleaſed to admit him to his Preſence, which will be ſomewhat the better for you, becauſe then the Exceptions againſt your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment and Negotiation, wherein you were Colleague, will be remov'd, and you will have no more to anſwer for, than your own particular Behaviour. I believe Sir <hi>Robert Honywood</hi> will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious enough to procure Satisfaction to the <hi>Merchants</hi> in the Buſineſs of <hi>Mony,</hi> wherein he will have the Aſſiſtance of Sir <hi>John Temple;</hi> to whom I refer you, for that, and ſome other things.</p>
            <p>I have little to ſay to your Complaints of your Siſter <hi>Strayford</hi>'s unequal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to your Affection and Kindneſs,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:175033:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>but that I am ſorry for it, and that you are well enough ſerv'd, for beſtowing ſo much of your Care where it was not due, and neglecting them to whom it was due, and I hope you will be wiſer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. She and her Husband have not yet paid the Thouſand Pounds, whereof you are to have your part, by my Gift; for ſo, I think, you are to underſtand it, tho' your Mother deſired it; and if for the Payment thereof, your being in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or in ſome Place not far off, be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, as ſome pretend, for the Sealing of ſome Writings, I think that, and other Reaſons, ſufficient to perſwade you to ſtay a while where you are, that you may hear frequently from your Friends, and they from you. I am wholly againſt your going into <hi>Italy</hi> as yet, till more may be known of your Condition; which, for the preſent, is hard; and, I confeſs, that I do not yet ſee any more man this, that either you muſt live in Exile, or very privately here; and (perhaps) not ſafely; for tho' the Bill of <hi>Indemnity</hi> be lately paſſed, yet if there be any particular and great Diſpleaſure againſt you, as I fear there is, you may feel the Effects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of from the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> and receive
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:175033:37"/>Affronts from the Inferiour: Therefore you were beſt to ſtay at <hi>Hamburgh,</hi> which, for a Northern Scituation, is a good place, and healthful. I will help you as much as I can in diſcovering and informing you of what concerns you; tho', as I began, ſo I muſt end, with tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, That Writing is now grown troubleſome to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate</hi> Le—</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 30. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:175033:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Honourable <hi>Algernoon Sidney</hi>'s LETTER, Againſt <hi>BRIBERY,</hi> AND ARBITRARY GOVERNMENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">Written to his Friends, in Anſwer to Theirs, perſwading his Return to <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am ſorry I cannot in all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form my ſelf to the Advices of my Friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if theirs had any joint-concernment with mine, I would will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſubmit my Intereſt to theirs; but
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:175033:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>when I alone am intereſted, and they only adviſe me to come over as ſoon as the <hi>Act of Indemnity</hi> is paſs'd, becauſe they think it is beſt for me, I cannot wholly lay aſide my own Judgment and Choice. I confeſs, we are naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to delight in our own Country, and I have a particular Love to mine; I hope I have given ſome Teſtimony of it; I think that being exil'd from it is a great Evil, and would redeem my ſelf from it with the loſs of a great deal of my Blood: But when that Country of mine, which us'd to be eſteem'd a Paradiſe, is now like to be made a Stage of Injury, the Liberty which we hoped to eſtabliſh oppreſs'd, all manner of Prophaneneſs, Looſeneſs, Luxury, and Lewdneſs ſet up in its heighth; inſtead of Piety, Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, Sobriety, and Modeſty, which we hoped <hi>GOD,</hi> by our Hands, would have introduc'd; the Beſt of our Nation made a Prey to the Worſt; the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Court, and Army corrupted, the People enſlav'd, all things Vendible, and no Man ſafe, but by ſuch evil and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous means as Flattery and Bribery; what Joy can I have in my own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in this Condition? Is it a Pleaſure
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:175033:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſee all that I love in the World, ſold and deſtroy'd? Shall I renounce all my old Principles, learn the vile Court-arts, and make my Peace by bribing ſome of them? Shall their Corruption and Vice be my Safety? Ah! no; better is a Life among Strangers, than in my own Country upon ſuch Conditions. Whil'ſt I live I will endeavour to preſerve my Liberty; or, at leaſt, not conſent to the deſtroying of it. I hope I ſhall die in the ſame Principle in which I have lived, and will live no longer than they can preſerve me. I have in my Life been guilty of many Follies, but, as I think of no meanneſs, I will not blot and defile that which is paſt, by endeavouring to provide for the future. I have ever had in my Mind, that when <hi>God</hi> ſhould caſt me into ſuch a Condition, as that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſave my Life, but by doing an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent thing, He ſhews me the time is come wherein I ſhould reſign it. And when I cannot live in my own Country, but by ſuch means as are worſe than dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in it, I think He ſhews me, I ought to keep my ſelf out of it. Let them pleaſe themſelves with <hi>making the King glorious,</hi> who think a <hi>Whole People</hi> may juſtly be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:175033:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſacrific'd for the Intereſt and Pleaſure of <hi>One Man,</hi> and <hi>a few of his Followers:</hi> Let them rejoyce in their Subtilty, who by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the former Powers, have gain'd the Favour of this, not only preſerv'd, but advanc'd themſelves in theſe dangerous Changes. Nevertheleſs (perhaps) they may find the <hi>King</hi>'s Glory is their Shame, his Plenty the Peoples Miſery; and that the gaining of an Office, or a little Mony, is a poor Reward for deſtroying a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! (which if it were preſerv'd in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Vertue, would truly be the moſt glorious in the World) and that others may find they have, with much Pains, purchas'd their own Shame and Miſery, a dear Price paid for that which is not worth keeping, nor the Life that is accompanied with it: the Honour of <hi>Engliſh Parliaments</hi> have ever been in making the Nation Glorious and Happy, not in ſelling and deſtroying the Intereſt of it, to ſatifie the Luſts of one Man. Miſerable Nation! that, from ſo great a heighth of Glory, is fallen into the moſt deſpicable Condition in the World, of having all its Good depending upon the Breath and Will of the vileſt Perſons in it! cheated and ſold by them they truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed!
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:175033:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>Infamous Traffick, equal almoſt in Guilt to that of <hi>Judas!</hi> In all preceding Ages, <hi>Parliaments</hi> have been the Pillars of our Liberty, the ſure Defenders of the Oppreſſed: They, who formerly could bridle <hi>Kings,</hi> and keep the Ballance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual between them and the People, are now become the Inſtruments of all our Oppreſſions, and a Sword in his Hand to deſtroy us: They themſelves, led by a few intereſted Perſons, who are willing to buy Offices for themſelves by the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the whole Nation, and the Blood of the moſt Worthy and Eminent Perſons in it. Deteſtable Bribes, worſe than the Oaths now in faſhion in this Mercenary Court! I mean to owe neither my Life nor Liberty to any ſuch Means; when the innocence of my Actions will not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect me, I will ſtay away till the Storm be overpaſs'd. In ſhort, where <hi>Vane, Lambert</hi> and <hi>Haſlerigg</hi> cannot live in Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I cannot live at all. If I had been in <hi>England,</hi> I ſhould have expected a Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them: or, tho' they may be the firſt, as being more eminent than I, I muſt expect to follow their Example, in Suffering, as I have been their Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Acting. I am moſt in Amaze at the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:175033:40"/>miſtaken Informations that were ſent to me by my Friends, full of Expectations, of Favours, and Employments. Who can think, that they, who impriſon them, would employ me, or ſuffer me to live, when they are put to death? If I might live, and be employ'd, can it be expected that I ſhould ſerve a <hi>Government</hi> that ſeeks ſuch deteſtable Ways of Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf? Ah! no; I have not learnt to make my own <hi>Peace,</hi> by perſecuting and betraying my <hi>Brethren,</hi> more inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and worthy than my ſelf: I muſt live by juſt Means, and ſerve to juſt Ends, or not at all, after ſuch a Manifeſtation of the Ways by which it is intended the <hi>King</hi> ſhall govern. I ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced any Place of Favour into which the <hi>Kindneſs</hi> and <hi>Induſtry</hi> of my <hi>Friends</hi> might have advanc'd me, when I found thoſe that were better than I, were only fit to be deſtroy'd. I had formerly ſome <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> the fraudulent <hi>Proclamation</hi> for <hi>Indemnity,</hi> increaſed the <hi>Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of thoſe three <hi>Men;</hi> and turning out of all the <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> contrary to <hi>Promiſe,</hi> confirm'd me in my <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> not to return.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:175033:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> To conclude: The <hi>Tide</hi> is not to be diverted, nor the <hi>Oppreſsd</hi> deliverd; but <hi>God,</hi> in his time, will have <hi>Mercy</hi> on His <hi>People;</hi> he will ſave and defend them, and avenge the <hi>Blood</hi> of thoſe who ſhall now periſh, upon the Heads of thoſe, who, in their <hi>Pride,</hi> think nothing is able to oppoſe them. Happy are thoſe whom <hi>God</hi> ſhall make <hi>Inſtruments</hi> of his <hi>Juſtice</hi> in ſo Bleſſed a <hi>Work.</hi> If I can live to ſee that <hi>Day,</hi> I ſhall be ripe for the <hi>Grave,</hi> and able to ſay with Joy, <hi>Lord! Now let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test thou thy Servant depart in Peace,</hi> &amp;c. [So Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigg</hi> on <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Death.] Farewel my Thoughts, as to <hi>King</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> depending upon their Actions. No Man ſhall be a more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Servant</hi> to him than I, if he make the <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Proſperity</hi> of his <hi>People</hi> his <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> none more his <hi>Enemy,</hi> if he doth the contrary. To my particular <hi>Friends</hi> I ſhall be conſtant in all Occaſions, and to You</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>A most affectionate Servant,</hi> A. SIDNEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:175033:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <p>I Have News to tell You: You got a new Subject Yeſterday; tho, after all, (perhaps) it is no more News to You, than it would be to the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> or the <hi>French King:</hi> For You <hi>(Madam)</hi> either find or make Subjects where-ever You go. It is impoſſible to ſee You, without ſurrendring ones Heart to You; and he that hears You talk, and can ſtill preſerve his Liberty, may (for ought I know) revive the Miracle of the <hi>Three Children</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and call for a <hi>Chamlet</hi> Cloak to keep him warm in the midſt of a <hi>Fiery Furnace.</hi> But really <hi>(Madam)</hi> I am none of thoſe <hi>Miracle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers;</hi> I am true <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> like the reſt of my <hi>Sex;</hi> and, as I make no Scruple to own my <hi>Paſſion</hi> to You, ſo You <hi>(Madam)</hi> without incurring the Danger of being queſtiond by the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> may pretend to all the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of a Conqueror. My Comfort is, that all Mankind, ſooner or
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:175033:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>later, muſt wear you Chains; for You have <hi>Beauty</hi> enough to engage the niceſt Heart, tho You had no Wit to ſet it off: And You have ſo plentiful a ſhare of the laſt, that were You wholly deſtitute of the former, as I have already found to my Coſt, You have but too much, You could not fail of harming the moſt Inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. For my own part, I confeſs my ſelf an <hi>Admirer,</hi> or, if You pleaſe, an <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> of Your <hi>Beauty:</hi> But I am a Slave, a meer downright effectual Slave to Your Wit. Your very <hi>Converſation</hi> is infinitely more delicious than the <hi>Fruition</hi> of any other Woman.</p>
               <p>Thus, my Charming Sovereign, I here profeſs my ſelf You devoted <hi>Vaſſal</hi> and <hi>Subject.</hi> I promiſe You eternal <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Allegiance:</hi> It is neither in my Power nor Will to depoſe You; and I am ſure it is not in Your Nature to affect <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> Sway. Tho if you do, <hi>(Madam) God</hi> knows, I am a true Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land-man;</hi> I ſhall never rebel againſt you in Act or Thought, but only have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Prayers and Tears, and ſtill ſtick to my <hi>Paſſive Obedience.</hi> Perhaps, <hi>Madam,</hi> youll tell me, I have talked
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:175033:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>more than comes to my ſhare; but being <hi>Incognito,</hi> I aſſume the Liberty of a <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querader;</hi> and, under that Protection, think my ſelf ſafe. But, alas, did You know how I languiſh for You, I dare ſwear (my Charming <hi>Sylvia!</hi>) You would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſome Pity upon</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>AMYNTAS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:175033:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <p>I Have never had the Happineſs of Your converſation but once, and then I found You ſo very charming, that I have wore Your lovely <hi>Idea</hi> ever ſince in my Mind. But it is not without the leaſt Aſtoniſhment, that I receiv'd the News of what befel You tother Day; it ſtill makes me tremble, and leaves a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Impreſſion behind it, not eaſie to be imagin'd. For Heaven's ſake, <hi>Madam,</hi> what could urge You to ſo cruel a Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, that might have prov'd irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably fatal to Your ſelf, and matter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Affliction to Your <hi>Friends?</hi> What Harm have I, and a Thouſand more of Your Adorers done You, that You ſhould ſo terribly revenge the ſuppoſed Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of another upon them? Or, Why ſhould You, whom <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Wit</hi> have put in a Capacity to ſubdue our whole <hi>Sex,</hi> lay to Heart the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkindneſs</hi> of one <hi>Lover,</hi> who may proceed to a new <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> when You pleaſe? If I had <hi>Vanity</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:175033:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>enough to aſpire to be Your <hi>Privy-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor,</hi> I wou'd e'en adviſe You to bury the Remembrance of what is paſt, and either to puniſh all Mankind, as You ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily may, tho I need not inſtruct. You how; or elſe to chuſe ſome happy <hi>Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite</hi> out of the <hi>Throng</hi> of Your <hi>Servants,</hi> and ſhower Your <hi>Favours</hi> upon him. If <hi>Sincerity</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> may bid for the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Your <hi>Heart,</hi> I can help You to one that thoroughly underſtands Your <hi>Worth,</hi> and accordingly values it; that would be damn'd before he would aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don You for the greateſt <hi>Princeſs</hi> in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe;</hi> that would chearfully die for Your ſake, and yet only lives out of Hopes, that he may one Day merit Your <hi>Eſteem</hi> by his <hi>Services.</hi> I fancy, <hi>Madam,</hi> You now demand of me, where this ſtrange Monſter of <hi>Fidelity</hi> is to be ſound? Know then, that he lives within leſs than a hundred Miles of <hi>Red-Lyon-Square;</hi> and that his Name is, (Oh! par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Inſolence of this <hi>Diſcovery</hi>) his Name is</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>AMYNTAS.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:175033:44"/>
                  <p>There is another Letter that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies this, and was written a Week ago; which I had not Courage enough to lay at Your Feet till now.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:175033:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LOVE-LETTERS,</hi> BY Mr. THOMAS OTWAY.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My TYRANT!</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Endure too much Torment to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and have endur'd it too long not to make the ſevereſt Complaint. I love You, I dote on You; <hi>Deſire</hi> makes me mad, when I am near You; and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair,</hi> when I am from You. Sure, of all Miſeries, <hi>Love</hi> is to me the moſt intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: it haunts me in my <hi>Sleep,</hi> perplexes me when waking; every melancholly Thought makes my <hi>Fears</hi> more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and every delightful one makes my <hi>Wiſhes</hi> more unruly. In all other uneaſy <hi>Chances</hi> of a Mans Life, there is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:175033:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Recourſe</hi> to ſome kind of <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour</hi> or another: In <hi>Wants,</hi> we apply our ſelves to out <hi>Friends;</hi> in <hi>Sickneſs,</hi> to <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians:</hi> but <hi>Love,</hi> the Sum, the Total of all <hi>Misfortunes,</hi> muſt be endurd with <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence;</hi> no <hi>Friend</hi> ſo dear to truſt with ſuch a <hi>Secret,</hi> nor <hi>Remedy</hi> in <hi>Art</hi> ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to remove its <hi>Anguiſh.</hi> Since the firſt Day I ſaw You, I have hardly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd one <hi>Hour</hi> of perfect <hi>Quiet:</hi> I lov'd You early; and no ſooner had I beheld that ſoft bewitching <hi>Face</hi> of Yours, but I felt in my <hi>Heart</hi> the very Foundation of all my <hi>Peace</hi> give way: But when You became anothers, I muſt confeſs, that I did then rebel, had fooliſh <hi>Pride</hi> enough to promiſe my ſelf, I would in time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my <hi>Liberty:</hi> In ſpight of my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlav'd <hi>Nature,</hi> I ſwore againſt my ſelf, I would not love You: I affected a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, ſtifled my <hi>Spirit,</hi> and would not let it bend, ſo much as once to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braid You, each Day it was my chance to ſee or to be near You: With ſtubborn <hi>Sufferance,</hi> I reſolv'd to bear, and brave your <hi>Power:</hi> nay, did it often too, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully. Generally with <hi>Wine,</hi> or <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> I diverted or appeas'd the <hi>Daemon</hi> that poſſeſs'd me; but when at Night,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:175033:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>returning to my unhappy Self, to give my <hi>Heart</hi> an Account why I had done it ſo unnatural a <hi>Violence,</hi> it was then I always paid a treble <hi>Interest</hi> for the ſhort Moments of <hi>Eaſe,</hi> which I had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd; then every treacherous Thought roſe up, and took Your part, nor left me till they had thrown me on my Bed, and open'd thoſe <hi>Sluces</hi> of Tears, that were to run rill <hi>Morning.</hi> This has been for ſome Years my beſt <hi>Condition:</hi> Nay, <hi>Time</hi> it ſelf, that decays all things elſe, has but encreas'd, and added to my Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. I tell it You, and charge You to believe it, as You are generous, (which ſure You muſt be, for every thing, except Your Neglect of me, perſwades me that You are ſo) even at this time, tho' other Arms have held You, and ſo long treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd on thoſe dear Joys that only were my Due; I love You with that Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit, that Purity of Truth, and that Sincerity of Heart, that I could ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice the neareſt <hi>Friends,</hi> or <hi>Intereſts</hi> I have on <hi>Earth,</hi> barely but to pleaſe You: If I had all the <hi>World,</hi> it ſhould be Yours; for with it I could be but miſerable, if You were not mine. I appeal to Your ſelf for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> if through the whole Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:175033:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>of my Life, I have done any one thing that might not let You ſee how ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute your <hi>Authority</hi> was over me. Your <hi>Commands</hi> have been always ſacred to me; Your <hi>Smiles</hi> have always tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and Your <hi>Frowns</hi> awd me. In ſhort, You will quickly become to me the greateſt <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> or the greateſt <hi>Curſe,</hi> that ever Man was doom'd to. I cannot ſo much as look on You without <hi>Confuſion; Wiſhes</hi> and <hi>Fears</hi> riſe up in war within me, and work a curs'd <hi>Diſtraction</hi> through my Soul, that muſt, I am ſure, in time have wretched <hi>Conſequences:</hi> You only can, with that <hi>Healing-Cordial, Love,</hi> aſſwage and calm my <hi>Torments;</hi> pity the Man then that would be proud to die for You, and cannot live without You, and allow him thus far to boaſt too, that (take out <hi>Fortune</hi> from the Balance) You never were belov'd or courted by a Creature that had a nobler or juſter Pretence to Your <hi>Heart,</hi> than the Unfortunate, and (even at this time) Weeping</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>OTWAY.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:175033:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <p>IN Value of Your <hi>Quiet,</hi> tho' it would be the utter <hi>Ruine</hi> of my own, I have endeavoured this Day to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf never more to trouble you with a Paſſion that has tormented me ſufficiently already, and is ſo much the more a Torment to me, in that I perceive it is become one to You, who are much dearer to me than my ſelf. I have laid all the Reaſons my diſtracted Condition would let me have recourſe to, before me: I have conſulted my <hi>Pride,</hi> whether after a <hi>Rival</hi>'s Poſſeſſion, I ought to ruine all my <hi>Peace</hi> for a <hi>Woman</hi> that another has been more bleſt in, tho' no Man ever loved as I did: But <hi>Love,</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious <hi>Love!</hi> o'erthrows all that, and tells me, it is his Nature never to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; he ſtill looks forward from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Hour, expecting ſtill new <hi>Dawns,</hi> new riſing <hi>Happineſs,</hi> never looks back, never regards what is paſt, and leſt behind him, but buries and forgets it quite in the hot fierce purſuit of <hi>Joy</hi> before him: I have
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:175033:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſulted too my very ſelf, and find how careleſs <hi>Nature</hi> was in framing me; ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned me haſtily with all the moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Inclinations and Deſires, but omitted the <hi>Ornaments</hi> that ſhould make thoſe <hi>Qualities</hi> become me: I have conſulted too my Lot of <hi>Fortune,</hi> and find how fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhly I wiſh Poſſeſſion of what is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, all the World's too cheap for it; yet ſtill I love, ſtill I dote on, and cheat my ſelf, very content, becauſe the Folly pleaſes me. It is Pleaſure to think how Fair you are, tho' at the ſame time worſe than Damnation, to think how Cruel: Why ſhould you tell me you have ſhut your Heart up for ever? It is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unworthy of your ſelf, ſounds like <hi>Reſerve,</hi> and not ſo much <hi>Sincerity,</hi> as ſure I may claim even from a little of your Friendſhip. Can your Age, your Face, your Eyes, and your Spirit bid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to that ſweet Power? No, you know better to what end <hi>Heaven</hi> made you, know better how to manage Youth and Pleaſure, then to let them die and pall upon your Hands. 'Tis me, 'tis only me you have barr'd your Heart againſt. My Sufferings, my Diligence, my Sighs, Complaints, and Tears are of no power
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:175033:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>with your haughty Nature; yet ſure you might at leaſt vouchſafe to pity them, not ſhift me off with groſs, thick, home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpun <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> the common <hi>Coin</hi> that paſſes betwixt Worldly <hi>Intereſts:</hi> muſt that be my <hi>Lot!</hi> Take it Ill-natur'd, take it; give it to him who would waſte his <hi>Fortune</hi> for you; give it the Man would fill your Lap with Gold; court you with Offers of vaſt rich Poſſeſſions; give it the Fool that hath nothing but his <hi>Money</hi> to plead for him: <hi>Love</hi> will have a much nearer <hi>Relation,</hi> or none. I ask for <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Happineſs;</hi> you bid me Welcome to your <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> it is like ſeating me at your Side-table, when I have the beſt Pretence to your Right-hand at the Feaſt. I Love, I Doat, I am Mad, and know no meaſure; nothing but Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams can give me eaſe; the kindeſt <hi>Love,</hi> or moſt provoking <hi>Scorn:</hi> Yet even your <hi>Scorn</hi> would not perform the Cure, it might indeed take off the edge of <hi>Hope,</hi> but damn'd <hi>Deſpair</hi> will gnaw my <hi>Heart</hi> for ever. If then I am not odious to your Eyes, if you have <hi>Charity</hi> enough to value the <hi>Well-being</hi> of a Man that holds you dearer than you can the Child your Bowels are moſt fond of, by that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:175033:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſweet <hi>Pledge</hi> of your firſt ſofteſt <hi>Love,</hi> I charm and here conjure you to pity the diſtracting <hi>Pangs</hi> of mine; pity my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet <hi>Days,</hi> and reſtleſs <hi>Nights;</hi> pity the <hi>Frenzy</hi> that has half poſſeſt my <hi>Brain</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, and makes me write to you thus ravingly: The <hi>Wretch</hi> in <hi>Bedlam</hi> is more at peace than I am! And if I muſt never poſſeſs the <hi>Heaven</hi> I wiſh for, my next deſire is, (and the ſooner the better) a clean-ſwept Cell, a merciful Keeper, and your Compaſſion, when you find me there.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Think and be Generous.</q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:175033:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <p>SInce you are going to quit the World, I think my ſelf oblig'd, as a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that World, to uſe the beſt of my Endeavours to divert you from ſo ill-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur'd an Inclination: Therefore, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon your Viſits will take up ſo much of this Day, I have debarrd my ſelf the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of waiting on you this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, that I may take a time you are more Miſtreſs of, and when you ſhall have more leiſure to hear, if it be poſſible for any Arguments of mine to take place in a Heart, I am afraid too much har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den'd againſt me: I muſt confeſs it may look a little extraordinary, for one under my Circumſtances, to endeavour the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming your good Opinion of the World, when it had been much better for me, one of us had never ſeen it: For <hi>Nature</hi> diſpoſed me from my <hi>Creation</hi> to <hi>Love,</hi> and my <hi>Ill Fortune</hi> has condemn'd me to <hi>Doat</hi> on one, who certainly could never have been <hi>deaf</hi> ſo long to ſo faithful a Paſſion, had <hi>Nature</hi> diſpoſed her from her
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:175033:49"/>
                  <hi>Creation</hi> to hate any thing but me. I beg you to forgive this Trifling, for I have ſo many Thoughts of this nature, that 'tis impoſſible for me to take Pen and Ink in my Hand, and keep 'em quiet, eſpecially when I have the leaſt pretence to let you know, you are the cauſe of the ſevereſt Diſquiets that ever touch'd the Heart of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>OTWAY.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:175033:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <p>COuld I ſee you without Paſſion, or be abſent from you without Pain, I need not beg your Pardon for this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing my Vows, that I love you more than <hi>Health,</hi> or any <hi>Happineſs</hi> here, or hereafter. Every thing you do is a new Charm to me; and tho' I have languiſh'd for ſeven long tedious Years of Deſire, jealouſly and deſpairing; yet every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute I ſee you, I ſtill diſcover ſomething new and more bewitching. Conſider how I love you; what would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, or enterprize for you? I muſt have you mine, or I am miſerable; and nothing but knowing which ſhall be the happy Hour, can make the reſt of my Life that are to come tolerable. Give me a word or two of <hi>Comfort,</hi> or reſolve ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to look with common <hi>Goodneſs</hi> on me more, for I cannot bear a kind Look, and after it a cruel Denial. This Minute my Heart akes for You: and, if I cannot
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:175033:50"/>have a Right in Yours, I wiſh it would ake till I could complain to You no longer.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Remember Poor</hi> OTWAY.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:175033:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <p>YOU cannot but be ſenſible, that I am blind, or You would not ſo openly diſcover what a ridiculous Tool You make of me. I ſhould be glad to diſcover whoſe ſatisfaction I was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd to this Morning; for I am ſure Your own <hi>Ill-Nature</hi> could not be guilty of inventing ſuch an <hi>Injury</hi> to me, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to try how much I could bear, were it not for the ſake of ſome <hi>Aſs,</hi> that has the Fortune to pleaſe You: In ſhort, I have made it the Buſineſs of my Life, to do You Service, and pleaſe You, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, by any way to convince You of the unhappy <hi>Love</hi> I have for ſeven Years toil'd under; and Your whole Buſineſs is to pick ill-natur'd <hi>Conjectures</hi> out of my harmleſs <hi>freedom</hi> of <hi>Converſation,</hi> to vex and gall me with, as often as You are pleasd to divert Your ſelf at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of my Quiet. Oh, thou <hi>Tormentor!</hi> Could I think it were <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> how ſhould I humble my ſelf to be juſtify'd;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:175033:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>I cannot bear the thought of being made a <hi>Property</hi> either of another Man's <hi>Good Fortune,</hi> or the <hi>Vanity</hi> of a Woman that deſigns nothing but to plague me.</p>
               <p>There may be Means found ſometime or other, to let you know your <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:175033:51"/>
               <head>To Madam—</head>
               <p>YOU were pleas'd to ſend me word you would meet me in the <hi>Mall</hi> this Evening, and give me further. Satisfaction in the Matter you were ſo unkind to charge me with; I was there, but found you not; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beg of you, as you ever would wiſh your ſelf to be eaſed of the higheſt Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it were poſſible for your Nature to be ſenſible of, to let me ſee you ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time to Morrow, and ſend me word, by this Bearer, where, and at what Hour, you will be ſo juſt, as either to acquit or condemn me; that I may, hereafter, for your ſake, either bleſs all your bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sex;</hi> or, as often as I henceforth think of you, curſe Womankind for ever.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:175033:52"/>
            <head>Mr.—to Mr. <hi>G</hi>—</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear <hi>G</hi>—,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS I hope to be ſav'd, and that's a bold word in a Morning, when our Conſciences, like Children, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways moſt uneaſie; when the Light of Nature flaſhes upon us with the Light of the Day, and makes way for the calm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of Thought, that eternal Foe to Quiet; but, I thank my Stars, I have ſhook that <hi>Snake</hi> out of my Boſom, and made Peace with that Domeſtick Enemy <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and ſo much the more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous by being ſo—</p>
            <p>—But, as I was going to ſay, your Letter has put new Life into me, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd me from the Damp, that Solitude and bad Company has flung me into; 'tis as hard to find a Man of <hi>Senſe</hi> here, as a handſom Woman: A company of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try 'Squires round a Table, is like a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Waiters round a dead Corps, they are always ridiculouſly ſober and grave, or, which is worſe, impertinently loud:
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:175033:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Wine,</hi> that makes the gay Man of the Town brisk and ſprightly, only ſerves to pluck off their Vail of <hi>Baſhfulneſs,</hi> a Mask that <hi>Fools</hi> ought always to wear; and which, once off, makes them as nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous, as a Bare-fac'd Lady of the <hi>Pit;</hi> they are as particular in their Stories, as a <hi>Lawyer</hi> in his <hi>Evidence,</hi> and husband their <hi>Tales,</hi> as well as they do their <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys:</hi> In ſhort, as Madam <hi>Olivia</hi> ſays, they are my Averſion of all Averſions.</p>
            <p>You may eaſily imagine, I have too much of the Men, but on my word, I have too little of the Women: Full of <hi>Youth, Vigour</hi> and <hi>Health,</hi> I lye follow; and, like the <hi>Veſtal Virgins;</hi> am damn'd to <hi>Coldneſs</hi> and <hi>Chaſtity</hi> in the midſt of Flames. <hi>God</hi> knows what hard ſhifts I uſe, my Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand often does, what (like Acts of <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>) I'm aſham'd my Left-hand ſhou'd know. As much as I deſpiſe the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of theſe <hi>Fops,</hi> I court it out of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of being alone, not daring to truſt my ſelf to ſo dangerous a Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as my ſelf. 'Tis in theſe cool Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of <hi>Solitude</hi> that we conſpire Cuckol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom againſt our Friend, Treaſon againſt the State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the <hi>Devil</hi> of <hi>Lust</hi> and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:175033:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Ambition,</hi> like other <hi>Evil Spirits,</hi> only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to us when we are alone.</p>
            <p>The talking of the <hi>Devil,</hi> puts me in Mind of the <hi>Parſons:</hi> I had the <hi>Benefit of the Clergy</hi> this Week; I mean the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of two honeſt unbigotted <hi>Parſons;</hi> I drank a Bowl to the <hi>Manes</hi> of our Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal <hi>Friend;</hi> one that was as witty as <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> and diſcover'd more <hi>Truths,</hi> than ever <hi>Time</hi> did: One that was born to unchain the <hi>World,</hi> that ſtruggl'd with <hi>Myſteries,</hi> as <hi>Hercules</hi> did with <hi>Monſters;</hi> and, like him too, fell by a <hi>Diſtaff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſo mournful a Subject, I'gad I'll make you laugh— The Duce take me if I did not, laſt Week, aſſiſt at the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of making a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> nay, more Sir, I was, <hi>Honos ſit Auribus,</hi> a <hi>Godfather,</hi> who am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate Friend and Servant,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:175033:53"/>
            <head>Monſ. <hi>BOILEAU</hi>'s LETTERS, TRANSLATED By THO. CHEEK, <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the Duke <hi>DE VIVONE,</hi> upon his Entrance into the Haven of <hi>Meſſina.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>KNow you not, that one of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ways to hinder a Man from being pleaſant, is, to bid him be ſo: Since you forbad me being ſerious, I never found my ſelf ſo grave, and I ſpeak nothing now but Sentences. And, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, your laſt Action has ſomething in it ſo great, that truly it would go againſt my Conſcience to write to you of it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:175033:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>otherwiſe, than in the <hi>Heroick</hi> Style: However, I cannot reſolve, not to obey you, in all, that you command me; ſo that in the Humour that I find my ſelf, I am equally afraid to tire you with a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trifle, or to trouble you with an ill Piece of Wit.</p>
            <p>In fine, my <hi>Apollo</hi> has aſſiſted my this Morning, and in the time that I thought the leaſt of it, made me find upon my Pillow, two Letters; which, for want of mine, may (perhaps) give you an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Amuſement. They are dated from the <hi>Elyſian,</hi> Fields; the one is from <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zac,</hi> and the other from <hi>Voiture,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both charm'd with the Relation of your laſt Fight, write to you from the other World, to congratulate you. This is that from <hi>Balzac:</hi> You will eaſily know it be to his by his Style, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs things ſimply, nor deſcend from its heighth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:175033:54"/>
                  <head>From the <hi>Elyſian</hi> Fields, <hi>June</hi> the 22d.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My LORD,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Report of your Actions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives the Dead; it wakens thoſe, who have ſlept thoſe thirty Years, and were condemn'd to an eternal Sleep; it makes <hi>Silence</hi> it ſelf ſpeak The Brave! the Splendid! The Glorious Conqueſt that you have made over the Enemies of <hi>France!</hi> You have reſtored Bread to a City, which has been accuſtom'd to furniſh it to all others: You have nouriſh'd the Nurſing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Italy;</hi> the thunder of that Fleet, which ſhut you up the <hi>Avenues</hi> of its Port, has done no more than barely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted your Entrance; its Reſiſtance has detained you no longer, than an over civil reception: So far from hindring the Rapidity of your Courſe, it has not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted the Order of your March; you have conſtrain'd, in their their Sight, the South, and North Winds to obey you, without chaſtizing the Sea, as
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:175033:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>Xerxes</hi> did; you have taught it Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; you have done yet more, you have made the <hi>Spaniard</hi> humble. After that, what may not one ſay of you? No, <hi>Nature,</hi> I ſay, <hi>Nature,</hi> when ſhe was young, and in the time that ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd <hi>Alexanders</hi> and <hi>Caeſars,</hi> has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd nothing ſo great, as under the Reign of <hi>Louis</hi> the XIV; ſhe has given to the <hi>French,</hi> in her Declenſion, that which <hi>Rome</hi> could not obtain from her in her greateſt Maturity. She has made appear to the World, in your Age, both in Body and Soul, that perfect <hi>Valour</hi> which we have ſcarce ſeen the <hi>Idea</hi> of in <hi>Romances,</hi> and <hi>Heroick Poems.</hi> Beging the Pardon of one of your <hi>Poets</hi>—he had no reaſon to ſay, That beyond <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus,</hi> Merit is no more known: Yours, My LORD, is extoll'd here, by the common Voice, on both ſides of <hi>Styx.</hi> It makes a continual Remembrance of you, even in the Abodes of <hi>Forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> It finds zealous <hi>Partizans</hi> in the Country of <hi>Indifference.</hi> It puts <hi>Acheron</hi> into the Intereſts of the <hi>Seine.</hi> Nay more, there is no Shade amongſt us, ſo prepoſſeſt with the Principles of the <hi>Porticus,</hi> ſo hardned in the School of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:175033:55"/>
                     <hi>Zeno,</hi> ſo fortified againſt Joy and Grief, that does not hear your Praiſes with pleaſure, that does not clap his Hands, and cry, <hi>A Miracle!</hi> at the moment you are named; and is not ready to ſay with your <hi>Malherbe,</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>A la fin c'est trop de Silence,</l>
                        <l>En ſi beau ſuject de parler.</l>
                     </q> As for me, My LORD, who know you a great deal better, I do nothing but meditate on you in my Repoſe; I fill my Thoughts intirely with your <hi>Idea,</hi> in the long Hours of our Leiſure, I cry continually, <hi>How great a Man is this!</hi> And if I wiſh to live again, 'tis not ſo much, to return to the Light, as to enjoy the ſovereign Felicity of your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and to tell you Face to Face, with how much Reſpect, I am from the whole extent of my Soul,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Lordſhip's most humble, and most obedient Servant. <hi>BALZAC.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:175033:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> I Know not, My LORD, whether theſe violent <hi>Exaggerations</hi> will pleaſe you; and whether you will not find, that the Style of <hi>Balzac</hi> is a little corrupted in the other World; however it be, (in my Opinion) he never laviſh'd his <hi>Hyperboles</hi> more to the purpoſe; 'tis for you to judge of it: But firſt read, (if you pleaſe) the Letter from <hi>Voiture.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:175033:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>From the <hi>Elyſian</hi> Fields, <hi>June</hi> the 22d.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My LORD,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THo' we poor <hi>Devils,</hi> who are dead, do not concern our ſelves much in the Affairs of the Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and are not exceedingly inclin'd to Mirth: Yet I cannot forbear rejoycing at the Great Things you do over our Heads. Seriouſly, your laſt Fight makes the Devil and all of a Noiſe here below; it has made it ſelf heard in a place, where the very <hi>Thunder</hi> of Heav'n is not heard; and has made your Glory known in a Country where even the <hi>Sun</hi> is not known. There are a great many <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> come hither, who were in the Action, and have inform'd us of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. I ſee no reaſon why the People of that Nation ſhou'd paſs for <hi>Bullies;</hi> for I can aſſure you they are very civil Perſons, and the <hi>King</hi> ſent 'em hither t'other Day very mild and quiet. To tell you the truth, my LORD, you have
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:175033:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>manag'd your Affairs very well of late. To ſee with what ſpeed you fly o're the <hi>Mediterranean-Sea,</hi> wou'd make one think you abſolutely Maſter of it: There is not at preſent, in all its extent, one ſingle <hi>Privateer</hi> in ſafety, and, if you go on at this rate, I can't ſee how you'd have <hi>Tunis</hi> and <hi>Algiers</hi> ſubſiſt. We have here the <hi>Caeſars,</hi> the <hi>Pompeys,</hi> and the <hi>Alexanders;</hi> they all agree, that you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly follow their Conduct in your way of fighting; But <hi>Caeſar</hi> believes you to be ſuperlatively <hi>Caeſar.</hi> There are none here, ev'n to the <hi>Alaricks,</hi> the <hi>Genſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks,</hi> the <hi>Theodoricks,</hi> and all the other Conquerors in <hi>icks,</hi> who don't ſpeak ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well of this Action; and in <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf (I know not whether you are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with that Place) there is no <hi>Devil,</hi> my LORD, who does not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs ingeniouſly, That at the head of an Army, you are a greater <hi>Devil</hi> than himſelf: This is a truth that your very Enemies agree in. But to ſee the good that you have done at <hi>Meſſina,</hi> for my part, I believe you are more like an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> than a <hi>Devil;</hi> only <hi>Angels</hi> have a more airy ſhape, and do not carry their Arms in a Scarf. Railery a-part, <hi>Hell</hi> is
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:175033:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>extreamly byaſs'd in your, Favour, There is but one thing to be objected to your Conduct, and that is the little Care, that you ſometimes take of your Life. You are ſo well belov'd in this Country, that they don't deſire your Company. Believe me, my LORD, I have already ſaid it in the other World, a <hi>Demi-god,</hi> is but a <hi>very little thing</hi> when he is dead; he's nothing like what he was, when he was alive. And as for me, who know already by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, what it is <hi>to be no more,</hi> I ſet the beſt Face on the Matter I can; but to hide nothing from you, I die with <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience</hi> to return to the World; were it only to have the <hi>Pleaſure</hi> to ſee you there; in purſuance of this intended Voyage, I have already ſent ſeveral times to find out the ſcatter'd Parts of my Body to ſet 'em together, but I could never recover my Heart, which I left at parting with, thoſe ſeven Miſtreſſes, that I ſerv'd (as you know) ſo faithfully, the whole ſeven at once. As for my Wit, unleſs you have it, I am told, 'tis not to be found in the World. To tell you the truth, I ſhrewdly ſuſpect, that you have at leaſt the <hi>Gaiety</hi> of it: For I have
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:175033:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>been told here four or five Sayings of your Turn of <hi>Expreſſion,</hi> which I wiſh with all my Heart, I had ſaid; and for which I would willingly give the <hi>Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick</hi> of <hi>Pliny,</hi> and two of my beſt Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Suppoſing then, that you have it, I beg you to ſend it me back as ſoon as poſſibly you can; for indeed you can't imagine how inconvenient it is, not to have all one's Wit about one, eſpecially when one writes to ſuch a Man as you are; this is the Cauſe that my Style, at preſent, is ſo alter'd: Were it not for that, you ſhou'd ſee me merry again, as formerly, with my Comrade <hi>Le Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet.</hi> And I ſhould not be reduc'd to the neceſſity of ending my Letter trivially, as I do in telling you, that I am,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Lordſhip's most Humble and Obedient Servant, <hi>VOITURE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:175033:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Theſe are the two Letters, juſt as I receiv'd 'em: I ſend them you writ in my own Hand, becauſe you would have had too much trouble to read the Characters of the other World, if I had ſent 'em you in the Original. Do not fancy, my LORD, that this is only a trial of Wit, and an imitation of the Style of theſe two Writers. You know very well, that <hi>Balzac</hi> and <hi>Voiture</hi> are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imitable. However, were it true, that I had recourſe to this Invention to divert you, ſhou'd I be ſo much in the wrong of it, or rather ought I not to be eſteem'd, for having found Out this way to make you read the Praiſes, which you wou'd never have ſuffer'd other ways? In a word, cou'd I better make appear with what Sincerity, and with what Reſpect I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:175033:59"/>
            <head>A LETTER, Writ by Mr. DENNIS, Sent with the following <hi>SPEECH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have here ſent you inclos'd, what I promis'd you by the laſt Poſt, and I think my ſelf oblig'd to give you ſome account of it. In the late <hi>Appendix</hi> to the new <hi>Obſervator,</hi> I find the Author reaſonably complaining of the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hiſtory by the <hi>French,</hi> and giving
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:175033:59"/>a reaſonable gueſs, how falſe the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of this Age (as far as it is writ by them) is like to come out in the next. And particularly what Monſieur <hi>Peliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s Hiſtory of the preſent <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France</hi> is like to be, which is now writing by that <hi>King</hi>'s own Order. Monſieur <hi>Boileau,</hi> who writ the enclos'd, has at leaſt as great a ſhare in that Hiſtory, as Monſieur <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſon:</hi> And therefore you have in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>closed, in the which he has very artfully inſerted a <hi>Panegyrick</hi> of his Prince, a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of what his part of the Hiſtory will be. For having flatter'd his Maſter in this ſmall <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> we have all the reaſon in the World to believe, That he will flatter him too in his <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> And that he has flatter'd him here, you will plainly find; not only by <hi>Exaggerations,</hi> which are in ſome meaſure to be allow'd to an <hi>Orator;</hi> but in affirming things which are directly contrary to the Truth. Such are thoſe two remarkable Paſſages of the <hi>French King</hi>'s Offering <hi>Peace</hi> to the late <hi>Confederacy,</hi> for the general Good of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> (which not ſo much as a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> who has Common-ſenſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves) and of his Bombarding <hi>Genoa,</hi> only to be reveng'd of its <hi>Inſolency</hi> and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:175033:60"/>of its <hi>Perfidiouſneſs,</hi> which every Man, who has heard the Story of Mr. <hi>Valdryon,</hi> muſt laugh at. Now ſince it is to be preſum'd, that Monſieur <hi>Boileau</hi> will flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him in his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> becauſe it is plain that he has flatter'd him in his <hi>Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick;</hi> what are we to expect from Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Peliſſon,</hi> whoſe Sincerity is by no means ſo much talk'd of as the other's? I thought to have concluded here: But it comes into my Mind to make two <hi>Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> upon the <hi>Panegyrical</hi> part of the enclos'd. The firſt is this, That ſince Monſieur <hi>Boileau,</hi> who is in the main a Man of <hi>Sincerity,</hi> and a lover of Truth, could not but flatter <hi>Lewis the Fourteenth,</hi> when he commended him; we may conclude, that it is impoſſible to give him a general Commendation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Flattery. For, where a <hi>Satyrick Poet</hi> paints, what other Man muſt not daub? The ſecond <hi>Reflection</hi> is this, That ſince this <hi>Panegyrick</hi> is ſcarce to be ſupported, notwithſtanding the moſt admirable <hi>Genius</hi> of the Author, which ſhines throughout it; and an <hi>Art</hi> to which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be added, (remember that I ſpeak of the <hi>Original</hi>) and beyond which nothing can be deſir'd; you may eaſily
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:175033:60"/>conclude how extreamly fulſom the reſt of the <hi>Panegyricks</hi> upon <hi>Lewis the Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth</hi> muſt needs be, whoſe Authors fall infinitely ſhort of <hi>Boileau</hi>'s, either <hi>Genius, Art,</hi> or <hi>Vertue.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:175033:61"/>
            <head>THE SPEECH OF Monſ. <hi>BOILEAU,</hi> Upon his Admiſſion into the French Academy.</head>
            <byline>
               <hi>Tranſlated by Mr:</hi> DENNIS.</byline>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLEMEN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Honour this Day conferr'd upon me, is ſomething ſo great, ſo extraordinary, ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle expected; and ſo many ſeveral ſorts of reaſons ought to have for ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded me from it, that at this very Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in which I return my Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments, I am doubtful if I ought to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:175033:61"/>believe it. Is it then poſſible, can it be true; <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> that you have in effect judg'd me worthy to be admitted into this <hi>Illuſtrious Society,</hi> whoſe Famous Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment does no leſs honour to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>Cardinal Richlieu,</hi> than all the reſt of the Numerous Wonders of his matchleſs Miniſtry? And what muſt be the thoughts of that Great Man? What muſt be the thoughts of that wiſe <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour,</hi> who after him enjoy'd the Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your <hi>Protectorſhip;</hi> and after whom it was your Opinion, that none but your <hi>King</hi> had right to be your <hi>Protector?</hi> What muſt be their thoughts, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> if they ſhould behold me this Day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Part of this <hi>Glorious Body,</hi> the Object of their eternal Care and Eſteem; and into which by the Laws, which they nave eſtabliſh'd, by the Maxims which they have maintain'd, no one ought to be receiv'd, who is not of a ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Merit, ail extraordinary Wit, and comparable even to you? But farther, whom do I ſucceed in the Place, which you are pleas'd to afford me here?<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Monſieur</hi> De Beſons.</note> Is it not a Man who is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renown'd for his great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and his profound Capacity?
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:175033:62"/>Is it not a Magiſtrate, who fill'd one of the foremoſt Seats in the Council; and who, in ſo many Important Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, has been Honoured by his <hi>Prince,</hi> with his ſtricteſt Confidence? A Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate no leſs Wiſe than Experienc'd, Watchful, Laborious; with whom the more I compare my ſelf, the leſs Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I find</p>
            <p>I know very well, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> (and who can be ignorant of it) that in the Choice which you make of Men, who are proper to ſupply the Vacancies of your Learned Aſſembly, you have no regard either to Place or to Dignity: That Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneſs, Learning, and an Acquaintance with all the more Genteel Arts, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways uſher'd in naked Merit to you, and that you do not believe it to be unbecom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of you, to ſubſtitute in the room of the higheſt Magiſtrate, of the moſt exalted Miniſter, ſome Famous <hi>Poet,</hi> or ſome Writer, whom his Works have render'd Illuſtrious, and who has very often no other Dignity, than that which his Deſert has given him upon <hi>Parnaſſus.</hi> But if you barely conſider me as a Man of Learning, what can I offer you that may
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:175033:62"/>be worthy of the Favour, with which you have been pleas'd to honour me? Is it a wretched Collection of <hi>Poetry,</hi> ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful rather by a happy Temerity, and a dexterous Imitation of the Ancients, than by the Beauty of its Thoughts, or the Richneſs of its Expreſſions? Is it a Tranſlation that falls ſo far ſhort of the Great Maſter-Pieces, with which you every Day ſupply us; and in the which you ſo gloriouſly revive <hi>Thucydides, Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon, Tacitus,</hi> and all the reſt of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd <hi>Heroes</hi> of the moſt Learn'd Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity? No, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> you are too well acquainted with the juſt value of things, to recompence at a rate ſo high, ſuch low Productions as mine, and offer me volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily upon ſo ſlight a Foundation, an Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which the Knowledge of my want of <hi>Merit,</hi> has diſcourag'd me ſtill from demanding.</p>
            <p>What can be the reaſon then, which in my behalf has ſo happily influenc'd you upon this occaſion? I begin to make ſome Diſcovery of it, and I dare engage that I ſhall not make you bluſh in expoſing it. The Goodneſs which the greateſt Prince in the World has ſhewn in employing
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:175033:63"/>me, together with one of the firſt of your Illuſtrious Writers, to make one Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the infinite number of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Actions; the Permiſſion which he has given me to do this, has ſupply'd all my Defects with you.</p>
            <p>Yes, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> whatever juſt Reaſons ought to have excluded me ever from, your <hi>Academy,</hi> you believ'd that you could not with Juſtice ſuffer that a Man who is deſtin'd to ſpeak of ſuch mighty Things, ſhould be depriv'd of the Utility of your Leſſons, or inſtructed in any other <hi>School</hi> than in yours. And, by this, you have clearly ſhewn, That when it is to ſerve your <hi>Auguſt Protector,</hi> whatever Conſideration might otherwiſe reſtrain you, your <hi>Zeal</hi> will not ſuffer you to caſt your Eyes upon any thing, but the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> of your <hi>Maſter</hi>'s Glory.</p>
            <p>Yet ſuffer me, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> to undeceive you, if you believe that that Great <hi>Prince,</hi> at the time when he granted that Favour to me, believ'd that he ſhould meet within me a Writer, who was able to ſuſtain in the leaſt, by the Beauty of Style, or by the magnificent Pomp of Expreſſion, the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:175033:63"/>Grandeur of his Exploits. No, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> it belongs to you, and to Pens like yours, to ſhew the World ſuch <hi>Maſter-pieces;</hi> and he never conceiv'd ſo advantageous a thought of me. But as every thing that he has done in his <hi>Reign</hi> is Wonderful, is Prodigious, he did not think it would be amiſs, that in the midſt of ſo many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd Writers, who with <hi>Emulation</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his Actions in all their Splendour, and with all the Ornaments of the Subli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt Eloquence, a Man without <hi>Artifice,</hi> and accus'd rather of too much <hi>Sincerity</hi> than of <hi>Flattery,</hi> ſhould contribute by his <hi>Labour,</hi> and by his <hi>Advice,</hi> to ſet to ſhew in a proper light, and in all the <hi>Simplicity</hi> of the moſt Natural <hi>Style,</hi> the truth of thoſe <hi>Actions,</hi> which being of themſelves ſo little probable, have rather need to be faithfully related, than to be ſtrongly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aggerated.</p>
            <p>And indeed, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> when <hi>Poets</hi> and <hi>Orators,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorians,</hi> who are ſometimes as daring as <hi>Poets</hi> or <hi>Orators,</hi> ſhall come to diſplay upon ſo Happy a Subject, all the bold Strokes of their Art, all their Force of <hi>Expreſſion;</hi> when they ſhall ſay of <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> more juſtly
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:175033:64"/>than was ſaid of a Famous Captain of old, that he alone has atchiev'd more <hi>Exploits</hi> than other <hi>Primes</hi> have read; that he alone has taken more Towns, than other <hi>Monarchs</hi> have wiſh'd to take: When they ſhall aſſure us, that there is no <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> upon the face of the <hi>Earth,</hi> no not the moſt Ambitious, who in the ſecret Prayers that he puts up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> dares preſume to petition for ſo much <hi>Glory,</hi> for ſo much <hi>Proſperity,</hi> as <hi>Heaven</hi> has freely granted this <hi>Prince:</hi> when they ſhall write, that his <hi>Conduct</hi> is Miſtreſs of <hi>Events;</hi> that <hi>Fortune</hi> dares not contradict his <hi>Deſigns:</hi> When they ſhall paint him at the Head of his Armies, marching with <hi>Gigantick</hi> Strides over great Rivers, and the higheſt Mountains; Thund'ring down <hi>Ramparts,</hi> rending hard <hi>Rocks,</hi> and tearing into ten thouſand pieces every thing that reſiſts his impetuous <hi>Shock:</hi> Theſe Expreſſions will doubtleſs appear Great, Rich, Noble, adapted to the lofty Subjeſt; but at the ſame time that the World ſhall wonder at them, it will not think it ſelf oblig'd to believe them, and the Truth may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily diſown'd or miſtaken, under the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe of its Pompous <hi>Ornaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:175033:64"/>
            <p> But, when Writers Without Artifice, and who are contented faithfully to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late things, and with all the ſimplicity of Witneſſes who depoſe, rather than of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, who make a Narration, ſhall rightly ſet forth, all that has paſs'd in <hi>France,</hi> ever ſince the famous Peace of the <hi>Pyrenees;</hi> all that the King has done in his Dominions, to re-eſtabliſh Order, Diſcipline, Law: when they ſhall reckon up all the Provinces which he has added to his Kingdoms in ſucceeding Wars, all the Advantages, all the Victories which he has gain'd of his Enemies; <hi>Holland, Germany, Spain,</hi> all <hi>Europe</hi> too feeble a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him alone, a War that has been always fruitful in proſperity, and a more glorious Peace: when Pens that are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, I ſay, and a great deal more careful to write the Truth, than to make others admire them, ſhall rightly articulate all theſe Actions, diſpoſed in their order of time, and attended with their real cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; who is it that can then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from them, I do not ſay of our Neighbours, I do not ſay of Allies; I ſay of our mortal Enemies? And tho' they ſhou'd be unwilling to acknowledge the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:175033:65"/>truth of them, will not their diminiſh'd Forces, their States confin'd within ſtricter Bounds, their Complaints, their Jealouſies, their Furies, their very Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, in ſpight of themſelves, convince them? Can they deny that in that very Year, of which I am ſpeaking, this Prince being reſolv'd to conſtrain them all to accept of a Peace, which he had offer'd them for the good of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> did all at once, and that at a time, when they had publiſh'd, that he was intirely exhauſted of Men and Money: that he did then, I ſay, all at once, in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> cauſe to ſtart up as 'twere out of the ground two mighty Armies, each of them conſiſting of Forty Thouſand Men; and that he provided for them abundant Subſiſtance there, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the ſcarcity of Forrage, and the exceſſive drought of the Seaſon? Can they deny, that whil'ſt with one of theſe Armies; he caus'd his Lieutenants to beſiege <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> himſelf with the other, keeping as it were block'd all the Towns of <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Hainault:</hi> That he did, by this moſt admirable Conduct, or, rather, by a kind of Enchantment, like that of the Head ſo renown'd in the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:175033:65"/>ancient Fables, whoſe Aſpect tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd the Beholders to Stones, render the <hi>Spaniards</hi> unmov'd Spectators of the taking of that important place, in the which they had repos'd their utmoſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge? That by a no leſs admirable effect of the ſame prodigious Enchantment, that obſtinate Enemy to his Glory, that induſtrious Contriver of Wars and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacies, who had labour'd ſo long to ſtir up all <hi>Europe</hi> againſt him, found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if I may uſe the Expreſſion, diſabled and impotent, ty'd up on every ſide, and reduc'd to the wretched Vengeance of diſperſing Libels; of ſending forth Cries and Reproaches: Our very Enemies, give me leave to repeat it, can they deny all this? Muſt not they confeſs, That at the time when theſe wonders were executing in the <hi>Law-Countries,</hi> our Fleet upon the <hi>Mediterranean,</hi> after having forc'd <hi>Algiers</hi> to be a Suppliant for Peace, caus'd <hi>Genoa</hi> to feel, by an Example that will be eternally dreadful, the juſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement of its Inſolence and of its Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſs; burying under the Ruines of Palaces and ſtately Houſes that proud City, more eaſy to be deſtroy'd than humbled? No, without doubt, our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:175033:66"/>dare not give the Lie to ſuch known Truths, eſpecially when they ſhall ſee them writ with that ſimple and natural Air, and with that Character of Sincerity and Probability, with which whate'er my Defects are, I do not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely deſpair to be able at leaſt in part to ſupply the Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>But ſince this very Simplicity, all Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as it is to Oſtentation and Pageantry, has yet its Art, its Method, its Beauties; from whence can I better derive that Art, and thoſe Beauties, than from the ſource of all Delicacies, this fam'd Academy, which has kept poſſeſſion, for ſo many Years, of all the Treaſures, of all the Riches of our Tongue? Theſe, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, are the things which I am in hopes to find among you; this is what I come to ſtudy with you; this is what I come to learn of you. Happy, if by my aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity in frequenting you, by my addreſs in bringing you to ſpeak of theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I can engage you to conceal nothing of all your moſt ſecret Skill from me: Your Skill to render Nature decent and chaſte at the very time when ſhe is moſt alluring; and to make the Colours and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:175033:66"/>Paint of Art, appear to be the genuine Beauties of Nature. Thrice happy! if by my Reſpects, and by my ſincere Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, can perfectly convince you of the extream Acknowledgment, which I ſhall make all my Lite-time for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected Honour you have done me.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:175033:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Letters of</hi> COURTSHIP TO A Woman of Quality.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <p>IF it be a Crime in me, <hi>Madam,</hi> to love, 'tis your fair Self that's the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of it; and if it be a Crime in me to <hi>tell</hi> you I do, 'tis my ſelf only that's faulty. I confeſs, 'twas in my Power to have forborn writing, but I am ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd I cou'd never have ſeen you, but the Language of my Looks wou'd have <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed the Secret;</hi> and to what purpoſe is it to pretend to conceal a Flame <hi>that will diſcover it ſelf by its own Light?</hi> In my mind there's more Confeſſion in diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Actions, frequent Sighs, or a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining Countenance, than in all the Artful Expreſſions the Tongue can utter; I have been ſtrugling with my ſelf this three Months to diſcover a thing which I
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:175033:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>now muſt do in three words, and that is, that <hi>I adore you;</hi> and I am ſure if you'll be juſt to your ſelf, you cannot be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to me, as to queſtion the reality of this Diſcovery, for 'tis impoſſible for you to be ignorant of the Charms you poſſeſs, no body can be rich, and yet <hi>unacquainted with their Stores.</hi> And therefore, ſince 'tis certain, you have every thing wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully engaging, you muſt not take it ill that my Taſte is as curious as another's, I ſhou'd do an injury to my own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment if it were not; I am not, <hi>Madam,</hi> ſo vain as to believe, that any thing I can act or utter ſhou'd ever perſwade you to retain the leaſt kind regard, in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the pain I ſuffer; I only beg leave and liberty to complain: They that are hurt in Service, are permitted to ſhew their Wounds; and the more gallant the Conquerour, <hi>the more generous is his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion.</hi> I ventur'd laſt night to faulter out my Misfortune, 'twas almoſt dark, and I attempted it with greater boldneſs, nay, you your ſelf (cruel and charming as you are) muſt needs take notice of my diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; your Sentences were ſhort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving; your Anſwers cold; and your Manner (contrary to your uſual and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:175033:68" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſweetneſs) was <hi>severe</hi> and <hi>forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> yet in ſpight of all the Awe and chill Aſpect you put on, you muſt always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear moſt adorable too,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your most lost and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfortunate humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:175033:68"/>
               <head>By the ſame Hand.</head>
               <p>YOu need not have laid an Obligation on me of writing, who am ſo incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable of my own accord, to tire you with Letters; 'tis the moſt agreeable thing I can do, and cou'd wiſh you thought it ſo too; but when I reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the harſhneſs of my Expreſſions, I muſt needs conclude, I have a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to my own ſatisfaction in writing, than to your patience in reading; the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way I know to make me write better, wou'd be to receive more frequent Letters from <hi>you,</hi> which would inſtruct me to do it; and I ſhou'd think it the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of my Pen to imitate even the <hi>faults</hi> of yours (if there were any.) I have the ſatisfaction left me, that I am writing to one, that, tho' her Judgment be nice and diſcerning, her Interpretation <hi>is eaſy</hi> and <hi>candid; One</hi> that has not only the <hi>brightneſs of Heaven</hi> to make me adore her, but alſo the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of it to forgive my offences; elſe I ſhou'd deſpair of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for this too long Letter.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:175033:69"/>
               <p> I confeſs, if I were to make a Recital of your Divine Qualities, an Age would be too ſmall a time to be employ'd in the Work: I ſhou'd endeavour to paint your gay airy Temper, and yet ſhadow it with all the Modeſty and cautious Reſerv'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; you have an Humour ſo very <hi>taking,</hi> that, as it fires the <hi>serious,</hi> and <hi>dull,</hi> ſo it checks, and reſtrains the too <hi>forward;</hi> and as your Charms give <hi>Encouragement,</hi> ſo your wakeful Conduct creates <hi>deſpair.</hi> If the Paper and your Patience wou'd not fail me, I cou'd live upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; but whilſt I do juſtice to your <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> I offend your <hi>Modeſty;</hi> and every offence againſt you, <hi>Madam,</hi> muſt be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided as much as poſſible by him, all whoſe Happineſs depends on pleaſing you, as does that of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your humble Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:175033:69"/>
               <head>By the ſame Hand.</head>
               <p>AS I cannot reflect upon the <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Appearance</hi> of things on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> and <hi>Monday</hi> laſt, without an affliction inexpreſſible, ſo I cannot think on the happy Change, without the moſt grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Pleaſure. Heavens! how my. Heart ſunk, when I found the tendereſt part of my Soul ſeiz'd with an Indiſpoſition, her Colour faded, the uſual Gayety of her Temper eclips'd, her Tongue faultering, her Air languiſhing, and the charming Luſtre of her Eyes ſetting and decay'd! Inſtead of kind Expreſſions full of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Endearments,</hi> I could hear nothing but <hi>Complaints,</hi> and the melancholy Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of a <hi>growing Illneſs.</hi> 'Tis true, (my deareſt Life) tho' you are as beautiful as <hi>Light,</hi> tho' ſweet and tender as a <hi>Flower in Spring,</hi> tho' gay and cheerful <hi>dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Youth,</hi> yet <hi>all</hi> theſe Perfections, that <hi>captivate others,</hi> cannot ſecure you againſt the <hi>tyranny</hi> of <hi>Diſtempers;</hi> Sickneſs has <hi>no</hi> regard to <hi>your Innocence,</hi> but the ſame
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:175033:70"/>ruffling Tempeſt that tears up the <hi>common Weeds,</hi> blaſts alſo the <hi>fragrant bluſhing Roſe:</hi> But now, to the Eternal Peace of my ſatisfy'd Mind, the Feaveriſh Heat is extinguiſh'd, and your Charms recover their uſual heavenly Brightneſs; I am the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Wretch</hi> that feels their force, and conſumes of a Feaver <hi>never</hi> to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh'd, but with the Life of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:175033:70"/>
               <head>By the ſame Hand.</head>
               <p>THis Morning I diſcover'd the <hi>Happy</hi> Signal at your Window, which was as welcome to me as a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial to fainting Spirits: Heavens grant the Deſign be real, <hi>Love</hi> is never free from <hi>Fears;</hi> and my preſaging Mind bids me not be too confident. If there be any Sympathy in our Souls, as there is in our Manners and Humours, I am ſure you muſt be very much indiſpos'd; for, all Night long, dreadful Fancies haunted me, and drove all ſoft and pleaſing Idea's from me: The ſame Reſt which guilty deſpairing Wretches and Feaveriſh Souls find in the midſt of their Agonies, was my lot all Night long: I could not, durſt not ſlumber; and, as my Love grew more outragious, my Apprehenſions about you were more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting. I cannot be well till I ſee you, which, if it be with your uſual
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:175033:71"/>Charming Gayety, I ſhall be the moſt bleſs'd of Mortals: But if pale Sickneſs ſit upon your Lips, Heavens grant it may alſo freeze the Blood of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>YOURS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:175033:71"/>
               <head>By the ſame Hand.</head>
               <p>IF <hi>Diſtraction</hi> be an Argument of <hi>Love,</hi> I need no other to convince you of my <hi>Paſſion:</hi> All my paſt Actions have diſcover'd it, ſince I had the honour to know you; tho' not any ſo ſenſibly as my Behaviour on <hi>Sunday</hi>-night: My Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on it, gives me more pain than I can expreſs, or you imagine; tho' in my Mind thoſe Actions may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, that proceed from <hi>Exceſs of Love.</hi> My Letter will diſcover the Loſs of my Senſes, which I never had ſo much oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for as now, eſpecially when I preſume to write to one of ſo much <hi>Judgment</hi> as your ſelf; but you, my <hi>Dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Creature,</hi> muſt look upon the Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Diſtreſs of a <hi>Love-ſick Wretch,</hi> with the ſame <hi>Candour</hi> and <hi>Mildneſs</hi> that Heaven does upon you; and let <hi>all</hi> my Faults be forgiven by your tender Heart, that is deſign'd for nothing but <hi>Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> and all the <hi>gentle Actions of ſoftest Love.</hi> Whil'ſt I am preaching up Pity, I
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:175033:72"/>muſt remember to practiſe it my ſelf, and not to perſecute you with more Words, than to tell you, that I love you to Death; and, when I ceaſe to do it, may Heaven juſtly puniſh my broken Vows, and may I be as <hi>miſerable</hi> as now I think my ſelf <hi>happy.</hi> But as the greateſt Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are diſcover'd by Silence, ſo that muſt direct me to conclude.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>YOURS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:175033:72"/>
               <head>By the ſame Hand.</head>
               <p>I Am troubled at the Soul, to find my <hi>Dearest Life</hi> expreſs her ſelf with ſo much Concern: I am ſure, till <hi>Death</hi> makes me <hi>cold,</hi> I ſhall <hi>never</hi> be ſo to one whoſe I <hi>entirely</hi> am, not ſo much, by <hi>Vows</hi> as by the <hi>ſincerest Paſſion</hi> and <hi>Inclination.</hi> No, my <hi>kind</hi> Dear, <hi>engaging</hi> Creature, ſooner than utter <hi>one</hi> Sigh which is not for You, I would chuſe to be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Mankind,</hi> and an Abhorrer of my own <hi>loathd Being.</hi> Your Perſon is <hi>too charming,</hi> your Manner <hi>too winning,</hi> your Principles <hi>too honourable,</hi> ever to let a Heart eſcape, that you have <hi>once</hi> made entirely your own; and, when mine is not ſo, may it feſter in the Breaſt of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>YOURS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:175033:73"/>
               <head>By the ſame Hand.</head>
               <p>TO expreſs the grateful ſenſe of the Obligation I have to You, cannot be effectually done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I had your Pen. If You obſerve my Style, You will have reaſon to conclude I have not received Your ingenious Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Yeſterday, which ſhou'd have been a Precedent to me, and a Rule to write by; I aſſure You I am as well ſatisfyd of the Reality of the Contents of it, as I am of its Ingenuity. Your Senſe is clear, like Your Actions; and that Spirit that glows in Your Eyes, ſhines in Your Lines. I may venture to ſay, that Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is not the leaſt of Your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and if any thing cou'd perſwade me to ſtay longer than <hi>Friday</hi> or <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday</hi> here, it would be in Expectation of a ſecond Letter from You. 'Tis my greateſt pleaſure to hear You are well, and to have the happineſs of poſſeſſing in Thought, what is deny'd to my Eyes;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:175033:73"/>deſiring the continuance of them for no other end, than to gaze upon my dear Conquereſs, who, after a moſt enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging manner, has the way of kindly killing</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Her humble and eternally obliged Servant.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:175033:74"/>
               <head>By the ſame Hand.</head>
               <p>I Hope, my deareſt Life, will excuſe this impertinence, tho' I received her Commands not to write; but when I tell her, that the Tumult of my Mind was ſo extream, upon the Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of my late Folly, that I cou'd not reſt, till I had acknowledg'd my Raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; I hope ſhe'll continue her uſual Goodneſs of forgiving one, that cannot forgive himſelf. When I think of my Unworthineſs, I rave. I have been treated by the deareſt and beſt of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, with all the Honour and Sincerity imaginable, and my Return has been Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and ill Manners. 'Tis You alone, Madam, that have ſweet engaging ways peculiar to Your ſelf, You are eaſy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Levity; Courteous and Affable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Flattery; You have Wit without Ill-nature, and Charms without being vain. I cannot think of all Your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Qualifications, without upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf for making ſuch barbarous
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:175033:74"/>and unjuſt Returns. I cannot think of what I have done, without a juſt Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence; I loath and deteſt my ſelf, and muſt needs own, I ought not to ſubſcribe my ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by any other Title, than,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:175033:75"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> of Reproach to a Woman of Quality.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am ſorry I muſt change my Style, and tell You I am now fully ſatisfyd that your Ladiſhip never will be ſo; I always fear'd your Deſires wou'd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed your Returns: But when I heard You were ſupplied by three Nations, I thought You might have been modeſtly contented. And I have even yet good nature enough to pity your unfortunate Condition, or rather Conſtitution, that obliges half the Town of neceſſity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline all ſorts of Commerce with You; I cou'd have wiſh'd you had had Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation enough left for me to have juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, tho' You have cruelly robb'd me of the Joy of Loving, without making your ſelf any reaſonable Advantage of it: had your Soul conſulted my Deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I ſhould have had fairer play for my Paſſion, and not have been thus ſacrific'd to your moſt Egregious Follies; yet,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:175033:75"/>ſince better late than never, take, <hi>Madam,</hi> this time, now the Town is disbanded, the Seaſon moderate, and your Ladiſhip's common Practice prorogued, to conſider if there be any way left You, in ſome meaſure, to ſave the Confuſion of your ſelf, and that of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>Your real humble Servant.</signed>
               <date>Auguſt <hi>the</hi> 10th. 95.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:175033:76"/>
            <head>A <hi>LETTER</hi> of Buſineſs to a Merchant's Wife in the City.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Can forgive you the Difficulty you made of paſſing an Ev'ning with me; nay, even the affected Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence You entertain'd me with, when You might have employ'd Your time much better; I knew Your Character, and gueſs'd what wou'd be the end of our firſt Meeting, but deſire it may not be the beginning of the Second: for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, prithee, dear <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> (do not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Your ſelf) and ſo often engage me to Love tenderly, and yet conjure me to hope for no Return; but do me the Favour to make a better uſe of the next Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, leſt You carry on too far the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Jeſt, and contrive to force Your ſelf out of the Inclinations of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your real humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:175033:76"/>
            <head>LETTERS, By the late Celebrated <hi>Mrs.</hi> KATHERINE PHILLIPS.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Fam'd <hi>Orinda,</hi> to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Berenice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Ladiſhip's laſt Favour from Col. <hi>P</hi>—'s was truly obliging, and carried ſo much of the ſame great Soul of Yours, which loves to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it ſelf in Expreſſions of Friendſhip to me, that it merits a great deal more Acknowledgment than I am able to pay at my beſt Condition, and am leſs now when my Head akes, and will give me no leave to enlarge, tho' I have ſo much Subject and Reaſon; but really if my Heart ak'd too, I cou'd be ſenſible of a very great Kindneſs and Condeſcention
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:175033:77"/>in thinking me worthy of Your Concern, tho' I viſibly perceive moſt of my Letters have loſt their way to Your Ladiſhip. I beſeech You, be pleas'd firſt to believe I have written every Poſt; but, ſecondly, ſince I came, and then to enquire for them, that they may be commended into Your Hands, where alone they can hope for a favourable reſidence: I am very much a Sharer by <hi>Sympathy,</hi> in Your Ladiſhip's Satisfaction in the Converſe You had in the Country, and find that to that ingenious Company Fortune had been juſt, there being no Perſon fitter to receive all the Admiration of Perſons beſt capable to pay them, than the great <hi>Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice:</hi> I hope Your Ladiſhip will ſpeak me a real Servant of Dr. <hi>Wilkins;</hi> and all that converſe with You, have enrich'd all this Summer with Yours. I humbly thank Your Ladiſhip for Your Promiſe of Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Book, which indeed merits a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, not View only, but Univerſal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, if my Vote be conſiderable in things ſo much above me. If it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, oblige me with the Sight of one of them, which (if Your Ladiſhip com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it) ſhall be very faithfully return'd You. And now (Madam) why was
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:175033:77"/>that a cruel Queſtion, When will You come to <hi>Wales?</hi> 'Tis cruel to me, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that it is yet in queſtion; but I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg Your Ladiſhip to unriddle that part of Your Letter, for I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand why You, Madam, who have no Perſons alive, to whom Your Birth hath ſubmitted You, and have already by Your Life ſecur'd to Your ſelf the beſt Opinion the World can give You, ſhould create an Awe upon Your own Actions, from imaginary Inconveniencies: Happineſs, I confeſs, is twofac'd, and one is Opinion; but that Opinion is certainly <hi>our own;</hi> for it were equally ridiculous and impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſhape our <hi>Actions</hi> by others <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</hi> I have had ſo much (and ſome ſad) Reaſon to diſcuſs this Principle, that I can ſpeak with ſome Confidence, That <hi>none will ever be happy, who make their Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to conſist in, or be govern'd by the Votes of other Perſons.</hi> I deny not but the Approbation of wiſe and good Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is a very neceſſary Satisfaction; but to forbear innocent Contentments, only becauſe it's poſſible ſome Fancies may be ſo capricious as to diſpute, whether I ſhould have taken them, is, in my Belief, neither better nor worſe, than to faſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:175033:78"/>becauſe there are ſome ſo ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in the World, that will abſtain from Meat, upon ſome Score or other, upon every day in the Year, that is, ſome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome Days, and others upon others, and ſome upon all. You know, <hi>Madam,</hi> there is nothing ſo various as <hi>Vulgar Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> nothing ſo untrue to it ſelf: Who ſhall then pleaſe, ſince none can fix it? 'Tis a <hi>Hereſy</hi> (this of ſubmitting to every blaſt of popular Extravagancy) which I have combated in Perſons very dear to me: <hi>Dear Madam,</hi> let them not have Your Authority for a Relapſe, when I had almoſt committed them; but conſider it without a Byaſs, and give Sentence as You ſee cauſe; and in that <hi>Interim</hi> put me not off, <hi>Dear Madam,</hi> with thoſe <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera's,</hi> but tell me plainly what Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience is it to come? If it be one in earneſt, I will ſubmit, but otherwiſe I am ſo much my own Friend, and my Friend's Friend, as not to be ſatisfy'd with Your Ladiſhip's taking meaſure of Your Actions by others Opinion, when I know too that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt could find nothing in this Journey that they could condemn, but your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Charity to me, and that Cenſure You have already ſupported with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:175033:78"/>and (notwithſtanding my own conſciouſneſs of no ways deſerving Your ſufferance upon that ſcore) I cannot beg You to recover the Reputation of Your Judgment in that particular, ſince it muſt be my Ruine. I ſhould now ſay very much for Your moſt obliging Commands to me to write, and ſhould beg frequent Letters from Your Ladiſhip with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible importunity, and ſhould by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from my <hi>Lucaſia</hi> excuſe her laſt Rudeneſs (as ſhe calls it) in giving You account of her Honour for You under her own Hand, but I muſt beg Your Pardon now, and out-believing all, I can ſay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every one of theſe accounts, for really, <hi>Madam,</hi> You cannot tell how to imagine any Perſon more to any one than I am,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your Ladiſhip's moſt faithful Servant, And paſſionate Friend, <hi>ORINDA.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>June <hi>the</hi> 25th,</date> 
                     <hi>Priory of</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digan.</dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:175033:79"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lucaſia</hi> is moſt faithfully Your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant: I am very glad of Mr. <hi>Cowley</hi>s ſucceſs, and will concern my ſelf ſo much as to thank your Ladiſhip for your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in it.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:175033:79"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> BERENICE.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have been ſo long ſilent, that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs I am now aſham'd almoſt to beg your Pardon, and were not Confidence in your Ladiſhip's Goodneſs a greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect than the beſt Addreſs in the World, I ſhould ſcarce believe my ſelf capable of remiſſion; but when Your Ladiſhip ſhall know more fully than Papers can expreſs, how much and how many ways I have ſuffered, you will rather wonder that I write at all, than that I have not written in a Week; when You ſhall hear that my Dear <hi>Lucaſia,</hi> by a ſtrange unfortunate Sickneſs of her Mother's, has been kept from me, for three Weeks logger than I expected, and is not yet come: I have had ſome difficulty to live, and truly, <hi>Madam,</hi> ſo I have, and more difficulty to be ſilent to You, but that in earneſt my diſorder was too great to write: <hi>Dear Madam,</hi> pardon and pity me, and, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:175033:80"/>that You do both, be pleas'd to haſten hither, where I ſhall pour all my Trouble into your Boſom, and receive thence all that conſolation which I never in my life more needed than I now do. You ſee, <hi>Madam,</hi> my preſumption, or rather Diſtraction to leap from Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions into Petitions, and thoſe for advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages ſo much above my merit: But what is that, that the dear great <hi>Berenice</hi> can deny her faithful <hi>Orinda?</hi> And what is it that <hi>Orinda</hi> would not do or ſuffer, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that ſweet and deſired Converſe, ſhe now begs of You? I am confident my <hi>Lucaſia</hi> will ſuddenly be here, to thank You for Your Charity, which You will, by coming, expreſs to me, and the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation You will put upon her by it; both which ſhall be equally and conſtantly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged (if You will pleaſe to haſten it) by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your faithfully affectionate Friend, and humble Servant, <hi>ORINDA.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 2. 1658.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:175033:80"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> BERENICE.</head>
               <p>I Muſt confeſs my ſelf extreamly trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to miſs a Letter from your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhip in a whole fortnight, but I muſt beg You to believe your Silence did not occaſion mine; for my Ambition to converſe with You, and advantage in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allow'd it, is too great for me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline any opportunity which I can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove to obtain ſo much happineſs: But really the Box of Gloves and Ribbons miſs'd a conveniency of going, and a Letter that attended them partakd in the ſame misfortune; and by this time, and ſome days before it, I hope they have reach'd You, for they were ſent away a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a Week ago; and if ſo, all that I can tell You of my Deſire to ſee Your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will be repetition, for I had with as much earneſtneſs as I was capable of, begg'd it then, and yet have ſo much of me Beggar in me, that I muſt redouble that importunity now, and tell you, That I gaſp for You with an impatience that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:175033:81"/>is not to be imagin'd by any Soul wound up to a leſs concern in Friendſhip than Yours is, and therefore I cannot hope to make others ſenſible of my vaſt deſires to enjoy You, but I can ſafely appeal to Your own illuſtrious Heart, where I am ſure of a Court of Equity to relieve me in all the complaints and ſupplications my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip can put up: Madam, I am aſſured You love me, and that being once grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, 'tis out of diſpute, that your <hi>Love</hi> muſt have nobler circumſtances than mine, but becauſe the greatneſs and reality of it muſt be always diſputed with You, by me there muſt of neceſſity remain the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligingneſs of Your Love to weigh down the Ballance, and give You that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over me in Friendſhip, which You unqueſtionably have in all things elſe, and if this reaſoning be true, (as ſure there are all Sciences in Friendſhip, and then <hi>Logick</hi> cannot be excluded) I have argued my ſelf into handſom neceſſity of being eternally on the receiving hand, but let me qualifie that ſeeming mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by aſſuring You, that even that is the greateſt teſtimony of my eſteem for Your Ladiſhip, that ever I can give; for I have a natural Pride (that I cannot
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:175033:81"/>much repent of) which makes me very unwilling to be oblig'd, and more cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious from whom I receive kindneſſes than where I confer them; ſo that being contented to be perpetually in Your debt, is the greateſt Confeſſion I can make of the Empire You have over me, and really that Priviledge is the laſt which I can ſubmit to part withal, to be juſt done in Acts of Friendſhip, and that I do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yield You in all my Life paſt, but can beg to have it continued by Your doing me the greateſt favour that ever I receiv'd from You, by reſtoring me my dear and honoured <hi>Berenice:</hi> This, Madam, is but one Action, but like the Summ of an Account, it contains the Value of all the reſt, and will ſo oblige and refreſh me, that I cannot expreſs the ſatisfaction I ſhall receive in it; I humbly thank Your Ladiſhip for the aſſurance You have given me, that You ſuddenly intend it, and that You were pleas'd to be account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to me for Your ſtay till <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> which being now at hand, I hope You will have neither Reaſon, Importunity, nor Inclinations to retard the Happineſs You intend me: Really, Madam, I ſhall and muſt expect it in theſe Holidays, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:175033:82"/>a diſappointment to me is the greateſt of Miſeries; and then, Madam, I truſt you will be convinc'd of this neceſſity there is of your Life and Health, ſince Heaven it ſelf appears ſo much concern'd in it, as to reſtore it by a Miracle: And, truly had you been ſtill in danger, I ſhould have look'd upon that as more ominous than the <hi>Blazing-ſtar,</hi> ſo much diſcours'd of; but you are one of thoſe extraordinary Bleſſings which are the Publick Concernments, and are, I truſt, reſerv'd to be yet many Years an Example of Honour and Ornament to Religion.</p>
               <p>Oh, Madam, I have abundance to tell you and ask you, and if you will not haſten to hear it, you will be almoſt as cruel as <hi>Arſaces;</hi> but you will come, and, if you find any thing in this Letter that ſeems to queſtion it, impute it to the continual diſtruſt of my own Merit, which will not permit me eaſily to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve my ſelf favoured: Dear Madam, if you think me too timerous, confute me by the welcome Experiment of your Company, which, really, I perpetually long for, and again beg, as you love me, and claim as you would have me
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:175033:82"/>believe it; I am glad your Ladiſhip has pitch'd on a place ſo near me, you ſhall be ſufficiently perſecuted with <hi>Orinda.</hi> I know you will pardon me, for not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting you with the News you heard from other hands, when I tell you, there is nothing of it true, and the Town is now full of very different Diſcourſe; but I ſhall tell you more particularly, when I have the honour to ſee you; and, till then, cannot with conveniency do it. I eaſily believe <hi>Dous</hi> factious; but in thoſe Diſputes, I think he diſcovers more Wit than Wiſdom, and your Ladiſhip knows they are inſeparable; I ſhall loſe the Poſt, if I do not now haſten to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, what I am always ready to make good, that I am more than any one living,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Ladiſhip's most faithful and most paſſionate Friend and Servant, <hi>ORINDA.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <date>Decemb. 30 1658.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:175033:83"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi> BERENICE.</head>
               <p>WIth the greateſt Joy and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the World, I receiv'd, <hi>Dear Madam,</hi> your Ladiſhip's moſt obliging Letter from <hi>Kew,</hi> and thus far I am recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd to my own Omiſſions, that they have produc'd a <hi>Shame,</hi> which ſerves me now to allay a <hi>Tranſport,</hi> which had otherwiſe been exceſſive at the knowledge that I am to receive, that notwithſtanding all my Failings, you can look upon me with ſo generous a Concern: I could make many Apologies for my ſelf, and with truth tell you, That I have ventured Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to kiſs your Ladiſhip's Hand, ſince I receiv'd one from it; but really, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> I had rather owe my Reſtitution wholly to your Bounty, than ſeem to have any pretence to it my ſelf, and I will therefore allow my ſelf utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of having any room in your Thoughts, in that I have not perpetually begg'd it of you, with that Aſſiduity as is ſuitable to ſo great and ſo valu'd a Bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:175033:83"/>and I know that tho' a Sea has di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided our Perſons, and many other Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents made your Ladiſhips Reſidence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain to me, yet I ought to have been reſtleſs in my Enquiries how to make my Approaches to you; and all the Varieties, and Wandrings, and Troubles that I have undergone ſince I had the honour to ſee your Ladiſhip, ought not to have diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me one moment from the payment of that Devotion to you, which, if you pleaſe, I will ſwear never to have been one jot leſſen'd in my Heart, as ill and as ſeldom as I have expreſs'd it; but now, that my good Fortune has brought me once more ſo near your Ladiſhip, I hope to redeem my Time, by ſo conſtant and ſervent Addreſſes to you, as ſhall both witneſs how unalterably I have ever lov'd and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd you, and how extreamly glad I am ſtill to be preſerv'd in ſo noble and ſo priz'd a Heart as yours; and, that I may the ſooner be ſecur'd of that, and reſtor'd to your Converſe, I muſt beg your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to find ſome occaſion that may bring you to <hi>London,</hi> where I may caſt my ſelf at your Feet, both in repentance of my own <hi>Faults,</hi> and acknowledgment of your <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> and aſſure you that neither <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſia,</hi>
                  <pb n="152" facs="tcp:175033:84"/>nor any other Perſon, ever had the Will, the Power, or the Confidence to hinder the Juſtice of my moſt affectionate Service to your Ladiſhip, and tho' you fright me with telling me how much you have conſidered me of late, yet I will venture upon all the Severity that Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction can produce; and if it be as great as I may reaſonably fear, yet I will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to it for the Expiation of my Fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and think my ſelf ſufficiently happy if after any Penance, you will once more receive me into your Friendſhip, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me to be that ſame <hi>Orinda,</hi> whom with ſo much goodneſs you were once pleaſed to own as moſt faithfully yours, and who have ever been, and ever will be ſo: And, Dear dear Madam,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Ladiſhip's most affectionate humble Servant and Friend <hi>K. PHILLIPS.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This was wrote but a Month before</hi> Orin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da <hi>died.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:175033:84"/>
            <head>To Mr. <hi>HERBERT.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Receiv'd your two Letters againſt <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> but I muſt tell you, they have made me no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert from Women, and their Favourite; for who, like <hi>Simonides,</hi> wou'd give nine ſcandalous Origins to Womankind, for one good one, meerly becauſe the Follies and Vices of that Sex deſerve it, and yet hope ever to make your Account of them? Or who, with <hi>Petronius Arbiter,</hi> would tell the <hi>Lawyers,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Quid faciunt Leges ubi ſola pecunia regnat?</l>
               <l>Aut ubi paupertas vincere nulla potest,</l>
               <l>Ipſi qui Cynica traducunt tempora cena,</l>
               <l>Nonnunquam nummis vendere verba ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</l>
               <l>Ergo judicium, nihil est niſi publica Merces</l>
               <l>At<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eques in cauſe qui ſedet empt a probat.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Thus Engliſh'd by Mr. <hi>Barnaby.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Laws bear the Name, but Money has the Power;</l>
               <l>The cauſe is bad when e'er the Client's Poor;</l>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:175033:85"/>
               <l>Thoſe ſtrict-liv'd Men that ſeem above our World,</l>
               <l>Are oft too modest to reſist our Gold:</l>
               <l>So Judgment, like our other Wares, is ſold;</l>
               <l>And the Grave Knight that nods upon the Laws,</l>
               <l>Wak'd by a Fee, Hems, and approves the Cauſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That the Bar is but a Market for the Sale of Right, and that the Judge ſits there only to confirm what the <hi>Bribe</hi> had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd before, and yet hope ever to eſcape when you come into their Hands? Or what Man that has his Intereſt before his Eyes, wou'd tell this dangerous Truth, <hi>That Prieſts of all Religions are the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, no, Plain-dealing muſt be leſt to <hi>Manly,</hi> and confin'd to the Theatre, and permit <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> and <hi>Nonſence</hi> to prevail with thoſe pretty Amuſements, Women, that like their own Pleaſure too well, to be fond of Sincerity. You declaim againſt Love on the uſual <hi>Topicks,</hi> and have ſcarce any thing new to be anſwer'd by me, their profeſs'd Advocate, if by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance you mean the Pain that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies <hi>Love;</hi> all other Pleaſures are mixt
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:175033:85"/>with that, as well as Love, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves in his ſecond Book <hi>de Oratore, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus rebus, voluptatibus maximis faſtidium finitimum est: In all things where the greatest Pleaſures are found, there borders a ſatiety and uneaſie pain.</hi> And <hi>Catullus, Non est dea neſcia noſtri, quae dulcem curis miſcet amaritiem: Nor am I unknown to that bright Goddeſs, who with my Cares mingles a ſweet pleaſing Bitter.</hi> But I take this Pain in Love to proceed from the imperfection of our Union with the Object belov'd, for the Mind forms a thouſand entran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Idea's,</hi> but the Body is not capable of coming up to that ſatisfaction the Mind propoſes; but this Pain is in all other Pleaſures that we have, none of which afford that fulneſs of Pleaſure, as Love, which bears ſome proportion to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemence of our Deſires: Speak therefore no more againſt Love, as you hope to die in the Arms of <hi>Sylvia,</hi> or not periſh wretchedly in the Death of a Pumpkin. I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:175033:86"/>
            <head>LETTERS, BY Mr. <hi>THO. BROWN.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>To</hi> C. G. <abbr>
                     <hi>Eſq</hi>
                  </abbr> 
                  <hi>in</hi> Covent Garden.</head>
               <p>MAY I be forced to turn News-monger for a wretched Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, and beat up fifty Coffee-houſes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Morning, to gather Scraps of Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and fatherleſs Scandal; or, (to Curſe my ſelf more emphatically) may I live the reſtleſs Life of ſome gay youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Brother's ſtarving Footman of the <hi>Temple,</hi> who between his Maſter's Debts and Fornication, viſits once a Day half the Shop-keepers in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> and half the Whores in <hi>Drury-lane,</hi> if I am not as
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:175033:86"/>utterly weary of hunting after you any longer, as ever Stateſman was of ſerving the Publick, when the Publick forgot to bribe his private Intereſt. Shou'd I but ſet down how many tireſome Leagues I have travell'd, how often I have ſhot all the City-gates, croſs'd <hi>Lincolns-inn Fields,</hi> paſs'd the two Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Exchange,</hi> and doubled the Cape of <hi>Covent-garden</hi> Church to ſee you, I ſhou'd grow more voluminous than <hi>Coryat,</hi> and you'd fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy your ſelf, without doubt, engag'd in <hi>Purchaſe</hi>'s or <hi>Hackluyt</hi>'s Itineraries. As you are a Perſon of half Buſineſs, and half Pleaſure, (which the Wiſe ſay, is the beſt Compoſition in the World) I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd you in your two Capacities, and order'd my Viſits accordingly. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I call'd upon you betimes in a Morning, when nothing was to be met in the Streets, but grave Tradeſmen, ſtalking in their Slippers to the next Coffee-houſe; Midnight-drunkards, reel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing home from the <hi>Roſe;</hi> induſtrious Harlots, who had been earning a Penny over-Night, tripping it on foot to their Lodgings; Ragmen, picking up Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials for <hi>Grubſtreet;</hi> in ſhort, nothing
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:175033:87"/>but Bailiffs, Chimney-ſweepers, Cinder-women, and other People of the ſame early Occupations, and yet, as my ill Stars contriv'd it, you were ſtill gone out before me. At other times I have call'd at Four in Afternoon, the Sober Hour, when other diſcreet Gentlemen were but newly up, and dreſſing to go to the Play; but to as little purpoſe as in the Morning. Then, towards the Evening, I have a hundred times examin'd the Pit and Boxes, the Chocolate-houſes, the Taverns, and all places of publick reſort, except a Church, (and there, I confeſs, I cou'd no more expect to meet you, than a Right <hi>Beau</hi> of the laſt <hi>Paris</hi> Edition in the <hi>Bear-garden</hi>) but ſtill I fail'd of you every where, tho' ſometimes you 'ſcaped me, as narrowly as a Quibble does ſome mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Stateſmen I cou'd name to you. Is it not ſtrange, thought I to my ſelf, that every paltry <hi>Aſtrologer</hi> about the Town, by the help of a fooliſh <hi>Teleſcope,</hi> ſhould be able to have the Seven Planets at a Minute's warning, nay, and their very Attendants, their <hi>Satellites</hi> too, tho' ſome of them are ſo many hundred thouſand Miles diſtant from us, to know preciſely when they go to Bed, and what Rambles
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:175033:87"/>they take, and yet that I with all my pains and application ſhou'd never take you in any of your <hi>Orbits,</hi> who are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably nearer to me? But, for my part, I believe a Man may ſooner find out a true Key to the <hi>Revelations,</hi> than diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your By-haunts, and ſolve every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem in <hi>Euclid</hi> much eaſier than your ſelf. With all Reverence be it ſaid, Your Ways are as hard to be traced as thoſe of Heaven; and the Dean of <hi>P</hi>—, who in his late Hiſtory of Providence has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd all the ſeveral <hi>Phaenomena's</hi> of it, but his own Converſions, is the fitteſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I know of in the World to account for your Eclipſes. Some of your and my good Friends, (whom I need not mention to you) have croſs'd the <hi>German</hi> Ocean, made the <hi>Tour</hi> of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> ſeen the Elector of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and Prince <hi>Vaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and might, if they pleas'd, have got drunk with a dozen of <hi>German</hi> Princes, in half the time, I have been beating the Hoof up and down <hi>London,</hi> to find out you:—So that at laſt, after a World of mortifying Diſappointments, taking a <hi>Martial</hi> in my hands, I happen'd to light upon an Epigram of his, addreſs'd to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cianus,</hi> a very honeſt Gentleman it ſeems,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:175033:88"/>but one that was as hard to be met with as your ſelf: And this Epigram, ſuiting my own caſe exactly, I here ſend you a Paraphraſe or Imitation of it, call it which you pleaſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Ne valeam, ſi non totis <hi>Deciane</hi> Diebus.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Lib. 2. Ep. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In ſome vile Hamlet let me live forgot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Small-Beer my Portion, and no Wine my lot:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſome worſe Jilt in Church-Indentures bound,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Than ancient</hi> Job, <hi>or modern</hi> Sh—<hi>found,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And with more Aches viſited, and Ills,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Than fill up</hi> Salmon's <hi>Works, or</hi> Tilburgh<hi>'s Bills:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If 'tis not ſtill the Burden of my Prayer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Day with you, with you the Night to ſhare.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But, Sir, (and the Complaint, you know, is true)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Two damn'd long Miles there lye 'twixt me and you:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And theſe two Miles, with little Calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Make four, by that I've reach'd my Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:175033:88"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You near</hi> Sage Will<hi>'s, the Land of Mirth and Claret,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I live, ſtow'd up in a</hi> White-chappel <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oft, when I've come ſo far your Hands to kiſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Flatter'd with Thoughts of the ſucceeding Bliſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'm told, you're gone to the Vexatious Hall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where, with eternal Lungs, the Lawyers bawl,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or elſe ſtole out, a Female Friend to ſee;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or, what's as bad, you're not at Home for me.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Two Miles I've at your Service, and that's civil,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But to trudge four, and miſs you, is the Devil.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>And now, if you are not incurably loſt to all ſence of Humanity, ſend me word where it is you paſs your Evenings, or in one of your beloved <hi>Catullus</hi>'s Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</p>
               <q>Demonſtres ubi ſunt tuae tenebrae.</q>
               <p>But if you think that too hard upon you, for I wou'd not be thought to invade your Privacies, appoint ſome common
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:175033:89"/>Meeting-place, the <hi>Griffin,</hi> or the <hi>Dog;</hi> where, with two or three more ſelect Friends, we may paſs a few Hours over a Righteous Bottle of Claret. As you ever hope that Heaven will be merciful, or <hi>Sylvia</hi> true to you, let this happy Night be ſome time this Week. I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most obliged Servant, <hi>T. BROWN.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>London, <date>June 20. 1695</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:175033:89"/>
               <head>To the Perjur'd Mrs.—</head>
               <p>THis Morning I receiv'd the News, (which, knowing you to be a Woman, I confeſs, did not much ſtartle me) that is, ſpight of all your Promiſes, your Vows, and Obligations, nay, and in ſpight of your Intereſt too, (which you Women ſo ſeldom ſin againſt) you had ſacrificed my worthy Friend Mr.—, and are to be married next Week to that nauſeous, that inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, that everlaſting Beaſt—. Upon which I immediately repair'd to my Friend's Lodgings; and, becauſe I knew but too well how nearly he had taken you into his Heart, I carried him to that bleſſed Sanctuary of diſappointed Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, a Tavern, the better to prepare him for the News of your <hi>Infidelity;</hi> I plied him warmly with the Juice of the generous Grape, and entertain'd him all the while with the moſt horrible Stories of your Sex, that my malice cou'd ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt to me; which, Heaven be prais'd,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:175033:90"/>was fruitful enough upon this occaſion; for I don't believe I forgot one ſingle In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Female Treachery, from Mother <hi>Eve,</hi> of wheedling Memory, down to your Virtuous ſelf. At laſt, when Matters were ripe, I diſclos'd the unwelcome Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret to him—. He raved, and wept, and, after ſome interval, wept and raved again; but, thanks to my pious Advice, and the kind influence of t'other Bottle, it was not long before the <hi>Paroxyſm</hi> was over. I cou'd almoſt wiſh you had been by, to ſee how Heroically he threw off your Chains; with what Alacrity he tore you from his Boſom; and, in fine, with what a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Self-denial he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd you; more heartily, I dear ſwear, than his Godfather abjur'd the Devil for him at his <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, Madam, tho' I confeſs you have prevented my Curſes, by your choice of ſuch a Coxcomb, and 'tis not good Manners to ſolicite a Judgment from Heaven on every ſuch Accident as this, (for Providence wou'd have a fine time on't, to be at the expence of a Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt, for every Woman that forſwears herſelf) yet ſo much do I reſent the ill
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:175033:90"/>uſage of my Friend, that I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to give you this Conviction, how earneſtly I can pray, when I ſet my ſelf to't. Therefore give me leave, Madam, to throw theſe hearty <hi>Ejaculations</hi> at your Head, now, ſince I ſhall not have the honour to throw a Stocking at you on the fatal Night of Conſummation.</p>
               <p>May the Brute, your Husband, be as jealous of you, as Uſurpers are of their new Subjects, and, to ſhew his good opinion of your Judgment, as well as your Virtue, may he ſuſpect you of a Commerce with nothing of <hi>God</hi>'s mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; nothing like a Gentleman that may ſerve to excuſe the Sin, but louſie Buſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begotten Vagabonds, and hideous Rogues in Rags and Tatters, or Monſters that ſtole into the World, when Nature was aſleep, with Ulcers all over them, and Bunches on their Backs as large as Hillocks. May you never actually Cuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>old him, (for that were to wiſh you ſome Pleaſure, which, <hi>God</hi> knows, I am far from being guilty of) but what will ſerve to torment him as effectually: May the Wretch imagine you've injur'd him that way; under which prepoſſeſſion
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:175033:91"/>may he never open his Mouth, but to Curſe, nor lift up his Hands, but to Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe you. May that execrable Day be for ever baniſhed out of the <hi>Almanack,</hi> in which he does not uſe his beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to beat one into your Bones; and may you never go to Bed, without an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion that he'll cut your Throat: May he too have the ſame diſtruſt of you. Thus may your Nights be ſpent in eternal Quarrels, and your Nuptial-ſheets boaſt of no honourable Blood but what's owing to theſe Nocturnal Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes. May he lock you up from the ſight of all Mankind, and leave you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but your ill Conſcience to keep you company, till at laſt, between his penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious allowance, and the ſenſe of your own guilt, you make ſo terrible a figure, that the worſt Witch in <hi>Mackbeth</hi> wou'd ſeem an Angel to you. May not even this diſmal Solitude protect you from his Suſpicions, but may ſome Good-natured <hi>Devil</hi> whiſper into his Ear, That you have committed Wickedneſs with a Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaff, and, in one of his frantick Fits, may he beat out your Brains with that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Inſtrument of your Luſt. May your Hiſtory be tranſmitted to all Ages
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:175033:91"/>in the Annals of <hi>Grubſtreet,</hi> and, as they fright Children with <hi>Raw-head,</hi> and <hi>Bloody-bones,</hi> may your Name be quoted to deter People from committing of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony. And to ratifie all this, (upon my Knees I moſt devoutly beg it) may Heaven hear the Prayers of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>T. BROWN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:175033:92"/>
               <head>TO THE <hi>Honourable</hi>— <hi>In the</hi> Pallmall.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>LAſt Night I had the following Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which, for my part, I confeſs, I never ſaw before, given me by a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who aſſur'd me they were written by my late Lord <hi>Rocheſter;</hi> and, knowing what a juſt Value you have for all the Compoſitions of that <hi>Incomparable</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I was reſolv'd to ſend 'em to you by the firſt opportunity. 'Tis indeed very ſtrange how they could be continued in private Hands all this while, ſince the great care that has been taken to print every Line of his Lordſhip's Writing that would endure a publick view: But I am not able to aſſign the reaſon for it. All that you need know concerning the occaſion of them, is, that they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in a Lady's Prayer-Book.</p>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:175033:92"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Fling this uſeleſs Book away,</l>
                  <l>And preſume no more to pray;</l>
                  <l>Heav'n is just, and can beſtow</l>
                  <l>Mercy on none but thoſe that mercy ſhow:</l>
                  <l>With a proud Heart, maliciouſly inclin'd,</l>
                  <l>Not to increaſe, but to ſubdue Mankind.</l>
                  <l>In vain you vex the Gods with your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition,</l>
                  <l>Without Repentance, and ſincere Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</l>
                  <l>You're in a Reprobate Condition;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phillis,</hi> to calm the angry Powers,</l>
                  <l>And ſave my Soul as well as yours,</l>
                  <l>Relieve poor Mortals from Deſpair,</l>
                  <l>And juſtifie the Gods that made you fair;</l>
                  <l>And in thoſe bright and charming Eyes</l>
                  <l>Let Pity firſt appear, then Love;</l>
                  <l>That we by eaſie ſteps may riſe</l>
                  <l>Through all the Joys on Earth, to thoſe Above.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I cannot ſwear to their being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine; however, there's ſomething ſo delicate in the Thought, ſo eaſie and beautiful in the Expreſſion, that I am without much difficulty to be perſwaded that they belong to my Lord. Beſides, I cannot imagine with what proſpect any Gentleman ſhould diſown a Copy of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:175033:93"/>Verſes, which might have done him no ill Service with the Ladies to father them upon his Lordſhip, whoſe Reputation was ſo well eſtabliſh'd among them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, by a numerous and lawful Iſſue of his own begetting. The Song that comes along with them, was written by Mr. <hi>Gl</hi>—of <hi>Lincoln's-Inn;</hi> and, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, you'll applaud my Judgment, for ſeeking to entertain you out of my Friend's Store, who underſtands the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ode ſo well, ſince I have nothing of mine own that deſerves tranſcribing.</p>
               <lg n="1">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <l>Phillis <hi>has a gentle Heart,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Willing to the Lover's Courting;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wanton Nature, all the Art,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To direct her in her Sporting:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In th' Embrace, the Look, the Kiſs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All is real Inclination;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No falſe Raptures in the Bliſs;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No feignd Sighing in the Paſſion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="2">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But oh! who the Charms can ſpeak,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who the thouſand ways of toying,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When ſhe does the Lover make</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All a God in her enjoying?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:175033:93"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who the Limbs that round him move,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And conſtrain him to the Bliſſes?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who the Eyes that ſwim in Love,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or the Lips that ſuck in Kiſſes?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg n="3">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh the Freaks, when mad ſhe grows,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Raves all wild with the poſſeſſing!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh the ſilent Trance! which ſhows</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Delight above expreſſing.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Every way ſhe does engage,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Idly talking, ſpeechleſs lying:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She tranſports me with the Rage,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And ſhe kills me in her Dying.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>I could not but laugh at one Paſſage in your Letter, where you tell me, that you, and half a dozen more, had like to have been talk'd to death t'other day, by— upon the Succeſs of his late Play. For my part, I don't pity you at all; for why the Devil ſhould a Man run his Head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Brick-wall, when he may avoid it? On the other hand, I wonder why you Gentlemen of <hi>Will</hi>'s Coffee-houſe, who pretend to ſtudy Pleaſure above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther People, ſhould not as naturally ſcam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per out of the Room, when your perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor appears, as Monſieur <hi>Miſſon</hi> tell us,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:175033:94"/>the Dogs in <hi>Italy</hi> ran out of Church as ſoon as ever they ſee a <hi>Capuchin</hi> mount the Pulpit. I find by you, that the above-mention'd everlaſting <hi>Babillard</hi> plagued you with his Songs, and talked of out-doing <hi>Don Quixot</hi> of Melodious Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; ſo far I agree with him, that if he has any Genius, it lies wholly in Sonnet. But (Heaven be prais'd) notwithſtanding all the feeble Efforts of his Enemies to depoſe him, Mr. <hi>D'<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>urfey</hi> ſtill continues the only Legal, Rightful, and Undoubted King of <hi>Lyrick-land,</hi> whom God grant long to reign over all his Hamlets, and may no <hi>Gallic</hi> Attempt againſt his Crown or Perſon, ever proſper. So wiſhes</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most obliged Servant, <hi>T. BROWN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:175033:94"/>
               <head>To My Lady—</head>
               <p>I Found a Letter of your Ladiſhip's own Hand left for me laſt Night at my Lodgings. This Morning a Porter viſited me with another of the ſort, and juſt now going to dine with ſome Friends at the <hi>Blue-poſts,</hi> you ſend me a third to refreſh my Memory. I vow to God, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> if you continue to draw your Bills ſo faſt upon me, I muſt be forc'd to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt them in my own Defence, or fly my Country. But, with ſubmiſſion, methinks the Language of all three was very ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing: You complain of my Abſence, and Coldneſs, and the Lord knows what, tho' 'tis but four days ago ſince I gave you the beſt convictions of my Love I cou'd, and you flatter'd me ſtrangely, if you were not ſatisfied with them: May I be as unacceptable to all Womankind as an old <hi>Eunuch</hi> with <hi>Jo. Haynes</hi>'s Voice, if there's a Perſon in the Univerſe whom I adore above your ſelf; but the devouteſt Lover upon Earth may ſometimes be
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:175033:95"/>without an Offering, and then certainly he's excuſed by all <hi>Love</hi>'s <hi>Canon-Law</hi> in the World, for not coming to the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</hi> There are People I know that love to hear the ratling of the Boxes, and ſhew themſelves at the Groom-Porter's, when they have not a Farthing in their Pockets: but for my part, I cou'd never endure to be an idle Looker-on. I have a thouſand Obligations to your Ladiſhip, and till I am in a capacity to repay them, ſhou'd be as uneaſy to ſee you, as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creditor, when I have no Money to ſend him going. I am ſo very honeſt in my own nature, that I wou'd not put you off with half Payments, and if I were not, your Ladiſhip is ſo diſcerning, that I might much eaſier palm Clipt-money upon a <hi>Jew,</hi> than ſucceed in ſuch a trick with ſo nice a Judge. Perhaps, <hi>Madam,</hi> you are ſcrupulous in this matter, even to a Fault. 'Tis not enough for you, that your Money is <hi>Parliamentary,</hi> and that other People wou'd be glad on't, for if it is not of the largeſt ſize, or wants one Grain of its due weight, you reject it with indignation. But, what is the hardeſt caſe of all, (and you muſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me, <hi>Madam,</hi> if I take this occaſion
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:175033:95"/>to reproach You with it) You are for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſing a Man's whole Caſh to Your ſelf, and, by Your good will, wou'd not leave him one ſolitary <hi>Teſtar</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute among the Needy elſewhere, tho' you don't know what Objects of Charity he may meet abroad. This, in truth, is very ſevere uſage: 'Tis the ſame as if the Government ſhou'd only take care to pay off the Soldiers in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and ſuffer the poor Seamen to ſtarve. Even the <hi>Royal-Oak Lottery,</hi> who are fit to be imitated by You in this particular, never ſtrip a Man intirely of all, but let him march off decently with a Crown or two to carry him home. If this Example won't work upon You, pray learn a piece of <hi>Tartarian-Mercy;</hi> they are none of the beſt bred People in the World, I confeſs, but are ſo civil when they come to a place, not to eat out the Heart of the Soil, but, having ſerved a preſent turn, ſhift their Quarters, and forbear to make a ſecond Viſit, till the Graſs is grown up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Nay, a <hi>Nonconformist</hi> Parſon, who is a kind of rambling a <hi>Church-Tartar,</hi> but of the worſer ſort, after he has graz'd a beloved Text as bare as the back of one's Hand, is glad for his own convience,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:175033:96"/>to remove to another. Both theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, you'll ſay, look as if I adviſed you to ſupply my defect in another place; I leave that to your own diſcretion; but really your humble Servant's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent exigencies are ſuch, that he muſt be forc'd to ſhut up his <hi>Exchequer</hi> for ſome time.</p>
               <p>I have a hundred times wiſhed, That thoſe unnatural Rogues, the Writers of Romances, had been all hanged, (<hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tague</hi> before me did the ſame for the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaries) for giving you, Ladies, ſuch wrong Notions of things. By repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>Heroes</hi> ſo much beyond Nature, they put ſuch extravagant <hi>Idea's</hi> into your Heads, that every Woman, unleſs ſhe has a very deſpicable Opinion of her own Charms, which not one in a Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion has, expects to find a Benefit-Ticket, a <hi>Pharamond,</hi> or an <hi>Oroondates,</hi> to come up for her ſhare, and nothing below ſuch a Monſter will content her. You think the Men cou'd do infinitely more, if they pleaſed; and, as 'tis a fooliſh Notion of the <hi>Indians,</hi> that the <hi>Apes</hi> wou'd ſpeak, if it were not for fear of being made ſlaves to the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> ſo you, forſooth, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:175033:96"/>that we, for ſome ſuch reaſon, are afraid of going to the full length of our Abilities. We cannot be ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in our hopes of your Conſtancy, as you are diſappointed in our Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances: ſo that 'twere happy for the World, I think, if Heaven wou'd either give us the Vigour of thoſe Brawny Long-liv'd Fellows, our Anceſtors, or elſe abridge the Deſires of the Women: But, <hi>Madam,</hi> don't believe a word, that thoſe Romance Writers, or their Brethren in Iniquity, the <hi>Poets,</hi> tell you. The latter prate much of one <hi>Hercules,</hi> (a Plague take him) that run the Gauntlet through fifty Virgin-ſiſters in one Night. 'Tis an impudent Fiction, <hi>Madam.</hi> The Devil of a <hi>Hercules,</hi> that there ever was upon the face of the Earth, (let me beg of you therefore, not to ſet him up for a Knight of the Shire, to repreſent the reſt) or, if part of his Hiſtory is true, he was a down right Madman, and proſper'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: For you know he died raving and impenitent upon a Mountain. Both he and his whole Family have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct theſe two thouſand Years and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Some Memoirs tell us, That the Country roſe upon them, and diſpatch'd
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:175033:97"/>them all in a Night, as the <hi>Glencow</hi>-men were ſerved in <hi>Scotland.</hi> I won't juſtifie the truth of this; but, after you, have tried the whole Race of us, one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, if you find one Man thrt pretends to be related to this <hi>Hercules,</hi> tho' at the diſtance of a <hi>Welch</hi> Genealogy, let me die the Death of the Wicked.</p>
               <p>Therefore, <hi>Madam,</hi> take my Advice, and I'll engage you ſhall be no loſer by it. If your Neceſſities are ſo preſſing, that you can't ſtay, you muſt e'n borrow of a Neighbour; ſince <hi>Cheapſide</hi> fails you, a God's Name, try your Fortune in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-ſtreet.</hi> But if you could order mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Otherwiſe, and allow me a Week or ſo longer, to make up my Sum, you ſhou'd then be repaid with Intereſt, by</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>LYSANDER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:175033:97"/>
               <head>A Conſolatory Letter to an <hi>Eſſex Divine,</hi> upon the Death of his Wife.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>OLD FRIEND,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>A Gentleman, that lives in your Neighbourhood, told me this Morning, after we had had ſome ſhort Diſcourſe about you, that you have buried your Wife. You and I, Doctor, knew one another, I think, pretty well at the College; but being abſolutely a ſtranger to your Wife's Perſon and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, the Old Gentleman in Black take me, if I know how to behave my ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this occaſion: that is to ſay, whether to be Sad or Merry; whether to Condole, or Congratulate you. But, ſince I muſt do one or t'other, I think it beſt to go on the ſurer ſide: And ſo, Doctor, I give you Joy of your late great Deliverance. You'll ask me, perhaps, why I choſe this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? To which I ſhall only reply. That your Wife was a Woman; and 'tis an hundred to one that I have hit on the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:175033:98"/>right. But if this won't ſuffice, I have Argument to make uſe of, that you can no more anſwer, than you can confute <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> I don't mean the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of that Name, (for, I believe, you have oftner laid him upon his Back, than Mrs. Mary, deceas'd) but an ungodly Veſſel holding about ſix Gallons, which, in ſome parts of <hi>England,</hi> goes by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Name (the more's the pity 'tis ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd) and is call'd, a <hi>Jeroboam.</hi>— And thus I urge it— Mrs. <hi>Mary,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct, was either a very good, or a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad; or an indifferent, a between Hawk and Buzzard Wife; tho' you know the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> for the four firſt Ages of the Church, were all of Opinion, that there were no indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Wives: however, <hi>diſputandi gratia,</hi> I allow them here. Now, if ſhe was a good Wife, ſhe's certainly gone to a better place; and then St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> and in ſhort, a whole Cart-load of <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers (whom 'tis not your Intereſt, by any means, to diſoblige) ſay poſitively, That you ought not to grieve. If ſhe was a bad one, your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will ſuggeſt the ſame to you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:175033:98"/>going to Councils and Schoolmen. So now it only remains upon my hands to prove, that you ought not to be concern'd for her Death, if ſhe was an indifferent Wife; and Publick Authority having not thought fit as yet, to oblige us to mourn for Wives of that denomination, it follows, by the Doctrin of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> about things indifferent, that you had better let it alone, for fear of giving Scandal to weak Brethren.</p>
               <p>Therefore, Doctor, if you'll take my Advice, in the firſt place, Pluck up a good Heart; ſecondly, Smoak your Pipe, as you uſed to do; thirdly, Read mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately; fourthly, Drink plentifully; fifthly and laſtly, When you are diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting Spoon-meat to the People next Sunday from your Pulpit, caſt me a Hawk's Eye round your Congregation, and, if you can, ſpy out a Farmer's Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, plump and juicy, one that's likely to be a good Breeder, and whoſe Father is of ſome Authority in the Pariſh (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that may be neceſſary for the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of holy Church) ſay no more, but pelt her with Letters, Hymns and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Sonnets, till you have gain'd your
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:175033:99"/>Carnal Point of her. Follow this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and I'll engage your late Wife will riſe no more in your Stomach; for, by the unerring Rule of <hi>Kitchin-Phyſick,</hi> which, I am apt to think, is the beſt in all Caſes, one Shoulder of Mutton ſerves beſt to drive down another. I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours, <hi>T. BROWN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:175033:99"/>
               <head>To the Fair <hi>LUCINDA, at</hi> Epſom.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Wiſh I were a Parliament-man for your ſake. Another now wou'd have wiſh'd to have been the <hi>Great Mogul,</hi> the <hi>Grand Seignior,</hi> or at leaſt ſome Sovereign Prince; but you ſee I am no ambitious Perſon, any farther than I aſpire to be in your good Graces. Now, if you ask me the Reaſon, why I wiſh to be ſo; 'tis nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bellow my ſelf into a good Place at Court, nor to avoid paying my Debts; 'tis to do a Publick Service to my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, 'tis to put the fam'd <hi>Magna Charta</hi> in force: In ſhort, <hi>Madam,</hi> 'tis to get a Bill paſs, whereby every pretty Woman in the Kingdom, (and then I am ſure you'll be included in it) ſhou'd under the ſevereſt Penalties imaginable, be prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to appear in Publick without her Mask on. I have often wonder'd why our <hi>Senators</hi> flatter us with being a free People, and pretend they have done ſuch mighty things to ſecure our <hi>Liberty,</hi> when
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:175033:100"/>we are openly plunder'd of it by the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and that in the face of the Sun, and on His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Highway. I am a ſad Inſtance, <hi>Madam,</hi> of this Truth. I that, but twelve Hours ago, was as free as the wildeſt Savage in either <hi>Indies,</hi> that Slept eaſily, Talk'd cheerfully, took my Bottle merrily, and had nothing to rob me of one Minute's Pleaſure, now love to be alone, make anſwers when no Body ſpeaks to me; Sigh when I leaſt think on't; and, tho' I ſtill drag this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy lifeleſs Carcaſe about me, can give no more account of my own Movements, than of what the two Armies are doing this very moment in <hi>Flanders.</hi> By all theſe wicked <hi>Symptoms,</hi> I terribly ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect I am in Love. If that is my caſe, and <hi>Lucinda</hi> does not prove as merciful as ſhe is Charming, the Lord have mercy on poor</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>MIRTILLO.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:175033:100"/>
               <head>To the Same at <hi>LONDON.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>AT laſt, but after a tedious Enquiry, I have found out your Lodgings in Town, and am pleas'd to hear you're kept by — who, according to our laſt Advices from <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> is Rich and Old, two as good Qualities as a Man cou'd deſire in a <hi>Rival:</hi> May the whole World (I heartily wiſh it) conſent to pay Tribute to all your Conveniences, nay, to your Luxury; while I, and none but I, have the honour to adminiſter to your Love. Don't tell me your Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to him won't give you leave to be complaiſant to a Stranger. You are his Sovereign, and 'tis a ſtanding Rule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> that under that capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city you can do him no wrong. But you imagine he loves you, becauſe he preſents you with ſo many fine Things: After this rate, the moſt impotent Wretches wou'd be the greateſt Lovers; for none are found to bribe Heaven or
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:175033:101"/>Women ſo high, as thoſe that have the moſt defects attone for. You may take it for granted, that half the Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-drones about the Town, do it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to follow the Mode, or to pleaſe a vain Humour, than out of Love to the Party they pretend to admire ſo, and this fooliſh Affectation attends them in other things. I cou'd tell you of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Lord, that keeps a Chaplain in his Houſe, and allows him plentifully, yet this Noble <hi>Peer</hi> is a rank <hi>Atheist</hi> in his Heart, and believes nothing of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: I know another, that has a fine Stable of Horſes; and a third, that va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues himſelf upon his great Library, yet one of them rides out but once in half a Year, and t'other never looked on a Book in all his Life. Admit your City-Friend loved you never ſo well, yet he's old, which is an incurable Fault, and looking upon you as his Purchaſe, comes with a Secure, that is with a Sickly Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite; while a vigorous Lover, ſuch as I am, that has honourable Difficulties to paſs through; that knows he's upon his good Behaviour, and has nothing but his Merits to recommend him, is nothing but <hi>Rapture,</hi> and <hi>Extaſie,</hi> and <hi>Devotion.</hi>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:175033:101"/>But oh, your are afraid it will come to <hi>Old Limberham</hi>'s Ears; that is to ſay, You apprehend I ſhall make Diſcoveries; for 'tis not to be ſuppoſed you'll turn Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt your ſelf. Prithee, Child, don't let that frighten you. Not a bribed Parliament-man, nor a drubb'd <hi>Beau,</hi> nor a breaking Tradeſman; nay, to give you the laſt ſatisfaction of my Secreſie, not a <hi>Parſon</hi> that has committed <hi>Symony,</hi> nor a forraging <hi>Author</hi> that has got a private Stealing-place, ſhall be half ſo ſecret, as you'll find me upon this occaſion. I'll always come the back-way to your Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and that in the Evening, with as much prudent religious Caution, as a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Clergyman ſteals into a Tavern on <hi>Sundays;</hi> and tho' it be a difficult Leſſon for <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> to practiſe, yet, to convince you, <hi>Madam,</hi> how much I va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue your <hi>Reputation,</hi> above my own Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I'll leave you a Mornings before <hi>Scandal</hi> it ſelf is up; that is, before any of the cenſorious Neighbourhood are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. If I ſee you in the Street, or at the <hi>Play-houſe,</hi> I'll know you no more than two Sharpers, that deſign to bob a Country-fellow with a dropp'd <hi>Guinea,</hi> know one another when they meet in the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:175033:102"/>Tavern. I'll not diſcover my Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with you by any <hi>Overt-acts</hi> of my <hi>Loyalty,</hi> ſuch as Drinking your Health in all Companies, and Writing your Name in every Glaſs-window, nor yet betray you by too ſuperſtitious a Care to conceal the Intrigue.</p>
               <p>Thus, <hi>Madam,</hi> I have anſwered all the Scruples that I thought cou'd affect you upon this matter. But, to ſatisfie your Conſcience farther, I am reſolv'd to viſit you to Morrow-night; therefore muſter up all the Objections you can, and place them in the moſt formidable po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, that I may have the Honour to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack and defeat them. If you don't wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully oppoſe your own Happineſs, I'll convince you, before we part, that there's a greater Difference than you imagine, between your Man of <hi>Phlegm,</hi> and ſuch a Lover as</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>MIRTILLO.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:175033:102"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>To</hi> W. KNIGHT, <abbr>
                     <hi>Eſq</hi>
                  </abbr> at <hi>Raſcomb,</hi> in <hi>Berkſhire.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu deſir'd me, when I ſaw you laſt, to ſend you the News of the Town, and to let you ſee how punctually I have obey'd your Orders, ſcarce a Day has paſs'd over my Head ſince, but I have been enquiring after the freſheſt Ghoſt and Apparitions for you, Rapes of the neweſt date, dexterous Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and fantaſtical Marriages, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Steeples demoliſh'd by Lightning, Whales ſtranded in the North, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a large Account of all which you may expect when they come in my way, but at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent be pleas'd to take up with the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing News.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Tueſday</hi> laſt, that walking piece of <hi>Engliſh Mummy,</hi> that <hi>Sybil</hi> incarnate, I mean my Lady <hi>Courtall,</hi> who has not had one Tooth in her Head, ſince King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Reſtauration, and looks old e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to paſs for Venerable <hi>Bede</hi>'s Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:175033:103"/>was Married—Cou'd you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it?—To young <hi>Liſanio.</hi> You muſt know I did my ſelf the Honour now and then to make her Ladiſhip a Viſit, and found that of late ſhe affected a youthful Air, and ſpruc'd up her Carcaſe moſt egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly; but, the Duce take me, if I ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected her of any lewd Inclinations to Marry: I thought that <hi>Devil</hi> had been laid in her long ago. To make my Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits more acceptable, I us'd to compliment her upon her Charms and all that; where by the by, my dear Friend, you may take it for a general Rule, that the Uglier your Women are, and the Duller your Men, they are the eaſier to be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd into a Belief of their Beauty and Wit. I told her, ſhe was reſolv'd to act <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s part, and kill more People in the laſt Scene of her Life, than other La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies cou'd pretend to do in the whole five Acts of theirs. By a certain awkard Joy, that diſplay'd it ſelf all over her Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and glow'd even through her Cheeks of Buff; I cou'd perceive this nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeous Incenſe was not unwelcome to her. 'Tis true, ſhe had the Grace to deny all this; and told me, I rallied her, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd it ſo, as intriguing <hi>Sparks</hi> deny they
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:175033:103"/>have lain with fine Women, and ſome <hi>Wou'd-be Poets</hi> deny their Writing of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſs <hi>Lampoons,</hi> when they have a mind at the ſame time to be thought they did what they coldly diſown. I cou'd not but obſerve upon this, and ſeveral other occaſions, how merciful <hi>Heaven</hi> has been to us, in weaving <hi>Self-love</hi> ſo cloſely into our <hi>Natures,</hi> in order to make Life palatable. The <hi>Divines</hi> indeed arraign it as a Sin; that is, they wou'd make us more miſerable than <hi>Providence</hi> ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd us, tho' were it not for this very Sin, not one of them in a hundred wou'd have Courage enough to talk in publick. For my part, I always conſider'd it as the beſt Friend, and greateſt Bleſſing we have, without which, all thoſe merry Farces that now ſerve to entertain us wou'd be loſt, and the World it ſelf be as ſilent and melancholly a sa <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court. 'Tis this bleſſed <hi>Vanity</hi> that makes all Mankind eaſie and chearful at home, (for no Body's a <hi>Fool,</hi> or a <hi>Raſcal,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gly,</hi> or <hi>Imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent</hi> in his own Eyes) that makes a <hi>Miſer</hi> think himſelf <hi>Wiſe,</hi> an affected <hi>Coxcomb</hi> think himſelf a <hi>Wit,</hi> a thriving gay <hi>Villain</hi> think himſelf a <hi>Politician;</hi> and in ſhort, that makes my Lady <hi>Court-all</hi> believe
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:175033:104"/>her ſelf. But to quit this Digreſſion, and purſue my <hi>Story.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the Day abovemention'd, this dry <hi>Puſs</hi> of Quality, that had ſuch a furious longing to be <hi>Matrimonially</hi> larded, ſtole out of her Houſe, with two of her Grave Companions; and never did a Country Juſtice's <hi>Oatmeal-eating</hi> Daughter of fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen uſe more Diſcretion to be undone with her Father's <hi>Clarke,</hi> or <hi>Chaplain. Gray's Inn Walks</hi> was the place of <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous;</hi> where, after they had taken a few Turns, <hi>Liſanio</hi> and ſhe walked ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately to the <hi>Chappel,</hi> and the Holy <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician</hi> Conjur'd them into the <hi>Circle.</hi> From thence they drove home in ſeveral Coaches, Din'd together, but not a <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable</hi> of the <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> they had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, till towards Night, becauſe then I ſuppoſe their <hi>Bluſhes</hi> were beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, they thought fit to own all. Upon this, ſome few Friends were invited, and the <hi>Fiddles</hi> ſtruck up, and my <hi>Old Lady</hi> frisk'd about moſt notably; but was as much overtopp'd, and put out of <hi>Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> by the Young Women, at <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-houſe</hi> with the New <hi>Buildings.</hi> Not to enter into a <hi>Detail</hi> of all that happen'd, the ruſty <hi>Gammon of Bacon</hi> at laſt was
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:175033:104"/>diſhed up between a pair of clean Sheets, ſoon after the <hi>Bridegroom</hi> follow'd, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to act <hi>Curtius</hi>'s Story, and leap alive into a Gulf. Let others envy his fine Equipage, and Brace of Footmen, that think it worth the while; as for me, I ſhall always pity the Wretch, who, to fill his Guts at Noon, obliges himſelf to work in a Mine all Night. A poor <hi>Knight</hi> of <hi>Alſatia,</hi> that Dines upon good whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Air in the Temple-Walks, is a <hi>Prince</hi> to him.</p>
               <p>I met <hi>Liſanio</hi> this Morning at the <hi>Rain-bow,</hi> and whether 'twas his <hi>Pride,</hi> or <hi>Ill-humour,</hi> ſince <hi>Marriage,</hi> I can't tell; but he looked as grum as a <hi>Fanatick</hi> that fancies himſelf to be in the State of Grace. I have read ſomewhere, that the <hi>Great Mogul</hi> weighs himſelf once a Year, and that the Courtiers rejoyce or grieve, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Royal Body increaſes or diminiſhes. I wonder why ſome of our Nice <hi>Beaux,</hi> that are married, don't do the like, to know exactly what depreda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions a <hi>Spouſe</hi> makes upon the Body Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural. As for <hi>Liſanio,</hi> I wou'd adviſe him never to do it, becauſe if he waſtes proportionably to what he has done this
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:175033:105"/>Week, a <hi>Skeleton</hi> will out-weigh him by the Year's End. But this is not half the <hi>Mortification</hi> that a Man muſt expect, who, to ſhew his <hi>Courage,</hi> ventures up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Widow. Tho' he mounts the Guard every Night, and wears out his Carcaſe in her Service, till at laſt, like <hi>Withering<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> in the <hi>Ballad,</hi> he fights upon his Stumps, yet he's never thank'd for his Pains; but labours under the ſame ill Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances with a <hi>King</hi> that comes after one that is depos'd, for he's ſure to be told of his Predeceſſor upon all occaſions. The ſecond Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, a Noble Structure, and yet we find the Old Fellows wept, and ſhook their Heads at it: Every Widow is ſo far a <hi>Jew</hi> in her Heart, that as long as the World laſts, the ſecond Houſe will fall ſhort of the Glory of the firſt. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I am apt to imagine the Complaint is juſt; for a Maid and Widow are two different things; and how can it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that a Man ſhou'd come with the ſame Appetite to a Second-hand Diſh, as he brought with him when it was firſt ſerv'd upon the Table?</p>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:175033:105"/>
               <p> And now, Mr. <hi>Knight,</hi> I am upon the Chapter of Widows, give me leave to add a word or two more. A true Widow is as ſeldom unfurniſh'd of an Excuſe to marry again, as a true <hi>Toper</hi> is without an Argument for <hi>Drinking.</hi> Let it rain or ſhine, be hot or cold, 'tis all one, a true Son of <hi>Bacchus</hi> never wants a good Reaſon to puſh about the Glaſs. And ſo a Widow, if ſhe had a good Husband, thinks her ſelf oblig'd in meer Gratitude to <hi>Providence,</hi> to venture again; and if he was a bad one, ſhe only tries to mend her hand in a ſecond Choice. It was not ſo with the People of <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi> The former had a <hi>King</hi> that loſt his Life in their Quarrel, and they wou'd have no more, becauſe he was too good for them, as the latter, becauſe theirs was an ill one. But <hi>Common-wealths,</hi> you know, are Whimſical things. I have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one thing more to ſay, before I have done, which tho' it looks like a <hi>Paradox</hi> at firſt ſight, yet after you have conſider'd a while upon it, I fancy you'll grant to be true: 'Tis in ſhort this, that a Man in the decay of his Vigour, when he begins to miſtruſt his Abilities, had much better
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:175033:106"/>marry a Widow than a Maid: For, as Sir <hi>John Suckling</hi> has long ago obſerv'd, a Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow is a ſort of <hi>Quag-mire,</hi> and you know the fineſt <hi>Racer</hi> may be as ſoon founder'd there, as the heavieſt Dray-horſe. I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt obliged Servant, <hi>T. BROWN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I believe I ſhall ſee you in the Country, before you hear from me again. Lest I ſhould come down a <hi>Barbarian</hi> to you <hi>Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hunters,</hi> I have been learning all your noble Terms of Art for this Month; and now, <hi>God</hi> be prais'd, am a great <hi>Proficient</hi> in the <hi>Language,</hi> and can talk of <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Horſes</hi> half an hour, without committing one <hi>Soleciſm.</hi> I have liv'd as ſober too all this while, as a <hi>Parſon</hi> that ſtands <hi>Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date</hi> for a Living, and with this Month's <hi>Sobriety</hi> in my Belly, deſign to do <hi>Wonders</hi> among you in the Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:175033:106"/>
               <head>To a Gentleman that fell deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately in Love, and ſet up for a <hi>Beau,</hi> in the <hi>45th</hi> Year of his Age.</head>
               <p>I Never was a <hi>Predeſtinarian</hi> before, but now begin to think better of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> and <hi>John Calvin</hi> than ever, and to be convinc'd there's a <hi>Fatality</hi> attends us. What leſs cou'd have made— once the Gay, the Brave, the Witty (ſix Months ago I ſhou'd have added the <hi>Wiſe</hi>) at the approach of <hi>Gravity,</hi> and <hi>Gray Hairs,</hi> forfeit his Character, fall in Love with <hi>Traſh,</hi> and languiſh for a <hi>Green Codling,</hi> that ſticks ſo cloſe to the <hi>Stem,</hi> that he may ſooner ſhake down the <hi>Tree,</hi> than the <hi>Fruit?</hi> 'Tis true, the <hi>fooliſh</hi> Hours of our Lives are generally thoſe that give us the greateſt ſhare of <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> but yours is ſo extravagant, ſo unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a <hi>Frolick,</hi> that I wonder you don't make your Life all of a piece, and learn at theſe Years to jump through a <hi>Hoop,</hi>
                  <pb n="198" facs="tcp:175033:107"/>and practiſe other laudable Feats of <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</hi> Oh, what a Conflict there is in your Breaſt, between <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion!</hi> 'Tis a motly Scene of <hi>Mirth</hi> and <hi>Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> to ſee you taking as much pains to conceal your <hi>Paſſion</hi> from the prying ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious <hi>World,</hi> as a baſhful young <hi>Sinner</hi> does to hide her <hi>Great Belly,</hi> and to as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe, for 'twill out.—You muſt be a <hi>Touchwood</hi>-Lover, forſooth, and <hi>burn</hi> without <hi>Blaze</hi> or <hi>Smoak.</hi> But why wou'd you feel all the <hi>Heat,</hi> yet want the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter <hi>Light?</hi> Such ſullen Fires may ſerve to kindle your Miſtreſs's <hi>Vanity,</hi> but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to warm her <hi>Heart.</hi> Well, <hi>Love</hi> I find operates with the <hi>Grave,</hi> like <hi>Drink</hi> with <hi>Cowards,</hi> it makes 'em moſt <hi>valiant,</hi> when leaſt <hi>able.</hi> But why's the <hi>Hair</hi> cut off? Can you <hi>dock</hi> any Years with it? Or are you the Reverſe of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the <hi>ſtronger</hi> for <hi>ſhaving?</hi> If ſo, let me ſee you ſhake off theſe <hi>Amorous Fetters</hi> to ſhew your Power. But you are <hi>Bucaneering</hi> for a Prize, and wou'd ſurprize a Heart under falſe <hi>Colours.</hi> Take my word for't, that <hi>Stratagem</hi> won't do, for the <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace</hi> you deſign upon, knows you have but a craſie <hi>Hulk,</hi> in ſpight of your new <hi>Rigging</hi> and <hi>Careening.</hi> Wearing of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rukes,</hi>
                  <pb n="199" facs="tcp:175033:107"/>like advancing more <hi>Standards</hi> than there are Troops in an Army, is a ſtale Artifice, that rather betrays your weakneſs to the Enemy, than alarms them: For tho' powder'd <hi>Vallancee,</hi> like <hi>Turkiſh Horſe-tails,</hi> may at a diſtance make a <hi>Terrible</hi> Shew of Strength, yet, my dear Friend, like them too, they are but very <hi>unſerviceable Weapons</hi> at a cloſe Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. After all, if you're reſolv'd to play a <hi>French</hi> Trick, and wear a <hi>Half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhirt</hi> in <hi>January,</hi> to ſhew your Courage, have a little of the <hi>Frenchman</hi>'s <hi>Prudence</hi> too, and line it with a <hi>Swanskin Waſtcoat:</hi> That is, if you muſt needs at this Age make <hi>Love,</hi> to ſhew your <hi>Vigour,</hi> take care to provide ſtore of <hi>Comforters</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port your <hi>Back.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:175033:108"/>
               <head>The Anſwer.</head>
               <p>WEll, but heark you, Friend <hi>Harry!</hi> And do you think now that <hi>forty</hi> Years (if a Man ſhou'd ever come to it) is as <hi>fumbling</hi> a doting Age in <hi>Love,</hi> as <hi>Dryden</hi> ſays it is in <hi>Poetry?</hi> Why then, what will become of <hi>Thee,</hi> who haſt made ſuch <hi>wicked Anticipations</hi> upon thy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's <hi>Revenue,</hi> that thou art utterly <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvent</hi> to any <hi>Matrimonial</hi> Expectations? Thou that in thy <hi>Post-haſte</hi> of Town-Riot and Exceſs, <hi>overleapest</hi> all the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Time,</hi> and art got to be <hi>Fifty</hi> in <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> before thy Age writes <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty!</hi> Enjoy thy acquir'd <hi>Jubilee,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thy wonted <hi>Courſe,</hi> but be aſſur'd no Body will ever be able to enjoy thee. The <hi>Woman-Prodigals,</hi> feed upon <hi>Husks,</hi> when they have any thing to do with thee, thou <hi>empty'd, raky, dry Bones.</hi> My <hi>Rheumatical Perſon,</hi> as ſuch, will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd ſome <hi>Moiſture,</hi> and <hi>Gray Hairs</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell you, the <hi>Sap</hi> is gone down to the <hi>Root,</hi> where it <hi>ſhou'd</hi> be, and from whence
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:175033:108"/>thine has been long ſince <hi>exhauſted</hi> into every Strumpets <hi>Cavern</hi> about the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs; confound your <hi>Widows,</hi> and put your own <hi>Farthing</hi> Candle, lighted at <hi>both Ends,</hi> under one of their <hi>Buſhels,</hi> if you pleaſe: I find I have <hi>Proweſs</hi> enough for the beſt <hi>Maidenhead</hi> in Town, and reſolve to <hi>Attempt</hi> nothing under that <hi>Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Difficulty.</hi> And ſo much for the Women—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:175033:109"/>
               <head>To his Honour'd Friend, Doctor <hi>BAYNARD,</hi> at the <hi>Bath.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>
                     <hi>My Dear</hi> DOCTOR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have not writ to you theſe two Months, for which I expect to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely reprimanded by you, when you come to Town. And yet why ſhou'd you wonder at ſuch a poor Fellow as I am, for being backward in my Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if you conſider 'tis the Caſe of <hi>Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> nay of the <hi>Bank,</hi> and the <hi>Exchequer</hi> it ſelf (you ſee I ſupport my ſelf by very honourable Examples) at this preſent melancholy juncture, when, with a little alteration of Mr. <hi>Cowley</hi>'s Words, a Man may truly ſay,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nothing of <hi>Ready Caſh</hi> is found,</l>
                  <l>But an Eternal <hi>Tick</hi> goes round.</l>
               </q>
               <p>However, to make you ſome amends for ſo long a Delay, I come to viſit you now, like <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove, with an Olive-branch in my Mouth; that is, in plain
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:175033:109"/>
                  <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I bring you news of a Peace, of a firm, a laſting, and a general Peace (for after this merry rate our <hi>Coffee-houſe Politicians</hi> talk) and pray do but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, if it were only for the Pleaſure of ſuch an Amuſement, what will be the happy Effect of it.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place, this Peace will ſoon beget good ſtore of Money, (the want of which, though we are ſinful enough in all Conſcience, is yet the moſt Crying Sin of the Nation) and this Money will naturally end in a great deal of <hi>Riot</hi> and <hi>Intemperance;</hi> and <hi>Intemperance</hi> will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a jolly <hi>Race</hi> of brave <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> with new Names and Titles; and then, <hi>My dear Doctor,</hi> you <hi>Phyſicians</hi> will have a Bleſſed Time on't.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Lawyers,</hi> who, were it not for two or three Noble Peers, ſome of their <hi>Never-failing Clergy-Friends,</hi> a few well-diſpos'd <hi>Widows,</hi> and ſtirring Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitors, that keep up the Primitive Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of <hi>Weſtminſter-hall,</hi> wou'd per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly forget the Uſe of their Lungs, they too will ſee glorious Days again. I was told a Melancholy Story t'other Day of two hopeful young Attorneys, who, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the general Decay of their Profeſſion,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:175033:110"/>were glad to turn <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Divines; and that you'll ſay is a damn'd Time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, when <hi>Lawyers</hi> are forc'd to turn <hi>Peace-makers.</hi> But as the World grows richer, People will recover by degrees out of this State of Lazineſs; Law Suits will multiply, and Diſcord make as ſplendid a Figure in the Hall as ever. Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong Squires will Rebel againſt their Lady Mothers, and the Church no longer connive at the abominable Sacrilege of Tythe-Pigs and Eggs converted to Lay Uſes.</p>
               <p>And then, as for the honeſt Good-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of the Town, whoſe Souls have mourn'd in Secret, ever ſince the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Abdication of <hi>Claret;</hi> how will they rejoyce to ſee their old Friend ſold at Twelve-pence a Quart again? What matter of Joy will it be to his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi>'s Liege-People, that they can get drunk with half the Coſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently with half the Repentance next Morning? This will in a particular man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner revive the drooping Spirits of the City <hi>Sots;</hi> for nothing goes ſo much againſt a true <hi>Cheapſide</hi> Conſcience, as an expenſive Sin. As times go now, a young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Brother can hardly peep into a Tavern
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:175033:110"/>without entailing a Week's Sobriety up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf; which, conſidering what Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion there may be to drink away the Publick and Private Calamities, is a ſad Mortification. <hi>Wine</hi> indeed is grown a ſullen Miſtreſs, that will only be enjoy'd by Men of ſome Fortune, and not by them neither, but upon Solemn Days; ſo that if theſe wicked Taxes continue, <hi>Canary</hi> it ſelf, tho' a Confederate of ours, is like to meet the Fate of condemn'd Criminals, to return to the diſmal Place from whence it came, an <hi>Apothecary</hi>'s Shop; and to be distributed about by diſcreet Nurſes in the Primitive ſneaking Gill. 'Tis true, the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as it became thoſe to whom the People had delegated their Power, thought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate theſe grievances, by the <hi>Six-penny</hi> Act, and laying a Five hundred Pound Fine upon Cellar Adultery; but the Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners (an impudent Generation) broke through theſe Laws as eaſily as if they had been Senators themſelves; nay, had the Boldneſs to raiſe new Exactions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Subject: This obliged one half of the Town, at leaſt, to come down a Story lower, and take up with dull <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Manufacture,</hi> ſo that half our Wit
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:175033:111"/>lies buried in execrable Flip, or fulſome <hi>Nottingham.</hi> To this may be aſcribed all thoſe Phlegmatick, Sickly Compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that have loaded of late both the Theatres, moſt of which puny Butter-prints, like Children begot by Pockey Parents, were ſcarce able to endure the Chriſtening; and others, with mighty pains and difficulty, lived juſt long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough (a <hi>Methuſelah</hi>'s Age!) to be Crown'd with Damnation on the third Day. But when Money circulates mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and <hi>Claret</hi> is to be had at the old Price, a new Spirit will appear abroad, Wit and Mirth will ſhake off their Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; and <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> that has made ſuch heavy returns of late Years, will trade conſiderably. It would be too tedious to reckon up all the other Advantages that the Kingdom will receive by this joyful Turn of the Scene; but there are ſome behind, which I muſt not omit, becauſe the Publick is ſo nearly concern'd in them. We have a World of Married Men now, that, to ſave Charges, take St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Advice in the Literal Sence; and, having Wives, live as if they had none at all, and ſo defraud both them and the Government; but upon the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:175033:111"/>Arrival of Peace, they'll vigorouſly ſet their Hands to the Plough again, and the Stale Batchelors too will find Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to marry, and leave behind them a pious Race of Fools, that, within theſe Twenty Years, will be ripe to be knock'd in the Head, in Defence of the Liberty of the Subject, and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion.</p>
               <p>We hear there's ſuch a thing as New Money in the City, but it only viſits the Elect, for the Generality of People are ſuch Reprobates to the Government, that they may ſooner get <hi>God</hi>'s Grace, than a Mill'd Crown Piece. To inflame our Reckoning, tho' there's ſo little Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſtirring in the Nation, that Dr. <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain</hi> is in greater hopes than ever of making his Paper-project take, yet the World was never ſo unſeaſonably ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous. What an Uſurer wou'd have leap'd at in <hi>King Charles</hi>'s Time, our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Porters now reject; which is full as ridiculous, as if in the preſent Difficulty of raiſing Recruits, a Captain ſhou'd reſolve to take no Men, but ſuch as were eight Foot high; or a Gentleman in the laſt Ebb of his Fortune, when he can ſcarcely pay for <hi>Small-beer,</hi> ſhou'd then,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:175033:112"/>and never before, fall in Love with <hi>Champagne.</hi> The laſt Year we had Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney enough, ſuch as it was, merrily Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, the <hi>Lord</hi> knows, however it made a ſhift to find us <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Harlots:</hi> Now 'tis all ſilenc'd, and in the room of it, (but that too, will ſoon ſuffer Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion) Faith paſſes for current, and never was there a Time of more Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Chalk, ſince the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Ages. This, among other Evils, cannot but have an ill Effect, <hi>My dear Doctor,</hi> upon the Gentlemen of your Profeſſion; for People at preſent, are ſo taken up with the Publick Tranſactions, or their own Loſſes, that they have no Leiſure, or are ſo poor, that they have no fancy to be Sick. The generality of thoſe that are, Chriſten a Diſtemper as they do Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracks in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> by the Name of <hi>God</hi>'s Bleſſing, and tho' a Legion of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes inveſt them, don't think it worth the while to ſend for a <hi>Phyſician</hi> to raiſe the Siege: If they do, 'tis for none of the College, 'tis for ſome Half-Crown <hi>Chirurgeon,</hi> who has cheated the World into an Opinion of his Skill, by putting <hi>Greek</hi> into his Sign, or for a Twelve-penny Seventh Son, that preaches on
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:175033:112"/>Horſeback in the Streets; hut in the Caſe of Chronical Diſeaſes, <hi>Let the World rub,</hi> is the general Language. Men put off the mending of their Bodies, as they do of Ill-tenanted Cottages, till they have Money to ſpare. There's a Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Bawd in <hi>Covent-garden,</hi> that had her Windows demoliſh'd laſt <hi>Shrove-Tueſday,</hi> and ſhe won't repair them nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till there's a General Peace.</p>
               <p>I believe no Body in the Nation will be averſe to it, but only our Friends in Red, and theſe find their Account ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly in the continuance of the War, that if they ever pray, which, I believe, is but ſeldom, we muſt excuſe 'em if 'tis againſt that Petition, <hi>Da pacem, Domine, in diebus noſtris.</hi> Some of 'em quitted <hi>Cook</hi> upon <hi>Littleton,</hi> and ſome aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don'd other Stations to go into the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and theſe upon a Change of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, muſt either turn <hi>Padders</hi> upon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi>'s, or the <hi>King</hi>'s High-road, and ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turn Authors, or <hi>Grands Voleurs,</hi> in their own Defence. But <hi>Paul</hi>'s will be built in a ſhort time; and then a <hi>Low-Country</hi> Captain will make as buſie a Figure in the middle Iſle, as ever his Predeceſſors did in the Days of <hi>Ben.
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:175033:113"/>Johnſon.</hi> Some of them may fight over the Battels of <hi>Steenkirk</hi> and <hi>Landen</hi> in Ordinaries, or demonſtrate how <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur</hi> was taken, by ſcaling the walls of a <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> Pye; and others ſet up Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing-Schools, to inſtruct the City Youth. The latter, indeed will act moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally: For I obſerve, that when People are forc'd to change their Profeſſions, they keep to 'em as nigh as they can, tho' they act in a lower Sphere: So, for inſtance, a batter'd Harlot makes a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet Bawd; and a broken Cutler, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Grinder of Knives. As for the Poets, I believe they are the moſt indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Men in the Kingdom, as to what happens: They have loſt nothing by the <hi>French</hi> Privateers, ſince the Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; nor are like to do, if the War laſts Seven Years longer, ſo it may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed they will not be angry to ſee the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Calumny of their Profeſſion, I mean their Poverty made univerſal; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if to pay People with fair words, and no Performance, be Poetical, there's more Poetry in <hi>Grocers-Hall,</hi> than in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſus</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p>But, <hi>My dear Doctor,</hi> after all this mighty Diſcourſe of a Peace, for my
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:175033:113"/>part, I ſhou'd believe as little of it, as I do of moſt of Mr. <hi>Aubrey</hi>'s Apparition Stories, but that we have not Money enough to carry on this great Law-Suit much longer, (for in effect <hi>War</hi> is no other, only you muſt fee more Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and give greater Bribes) and the <hi>Lord</hi> have mercy, ſay I, on a Man that Sues, or a Prince that fights for his Right in <hi>Forma pauperis.</hi> This, and nothing but this, makes me imagine we ſhall have a Peace, and not the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Piety of one or t'other ſide. And to ſay the truth, half the Vertue in the World, if traced to the Cradle, will be found to be the lawful Iſſue of meer Neceſſity. People lay aſide their Vices, to which their Vertues ſucceed, juſt as they do their Cloaths, ſometimes when they are Unfaſhionable, but generally when they are worn Thread-bare, and will hang about them no longer. A Godly Raſcal of the City leaves off Cheating, when the World will truſt him no longer; and a Rakehell turns Sober, when his Purſe fails, or his Carcaſe leaves him in the Lurch: And laſtly, which word, I don't doubt, ſounds as comfortably to you, as ever it did to a hungry Sinner
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:175033:114"/>in a long-winded Church; 'tis for want of more Paper, more Ink, and more Candle, that I perſecute you no longer, who am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>T. BROWN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="213" facs="tcp:175033:114"/>
               <head>To Mr. <hi>RAPHSON,</hi> Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Send you by the Bearer hereof, Mr. <hi>Aubrey</hi>'s Book, that you have ſo much long'd to ſee: 'Tis a Collection of <hi>Omens, Voices, Knockings, Apparitions, Dreams,</hi> &amp;c. which, whether they are agreeable to your <hi>Syſtem</hi> of <hi>Theology,</hi> I cannot tell. And now I talk of <hi>Dreams,</hi> I have often wonder'd how they came to be in ſuch requeſt in the <hi>East:</hi> Whether their Imaginations in thoſe hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are more rampant than ours, or whether the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> for their own ends, cultivated this <hi>Superſtition</hi> in the People, which I am rather inclin'd to believe; yet 'tis certain, that Affairs of the laſt Conſequence, have been deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by them. An Interpreter of <hi>Dreams,</hi> was, in ſome ſort, a Miniſter of State in thoſe Nations; and an <hi>Eaſtern King</hi> cou'd no more be without one of that Profeſſion in his Court, than an <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ropean</hi> Prince without his Chaplain, or Confeſſor, <hi>Homer</hi> too, the Father of the
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:175033:115"/>
                  <hi>Bards,</hi> had a great Veneration for Dreams. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He makes them all <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> you ſee; had he liv'd in Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi>'s Time, he cou'd not have ſaid more for <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopacy.</hi> If you can pardon this fooliſh Digreſſion, (for which I can plead no other Excuſe than the <hi>Dog-days</hi>) I have ſomething of another nature to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to you, which I am confident will highly pleaſe a Gentleman of your Curioſity.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Connor,</hi> of the College of <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> and Fellow of the <hi>Royal Society,</hi> hath now publiſh'd in <hi>Latin,</hi> his <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Medici, ſeu Medicina Myſtica de Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis Naturae Legibus, ſive de Miraculis.</hi> He deſigns in this Book to ſhew by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Phyſick;</hi> as likewiſe by <hi>Chymiſtry</hi> and <hi>Anatomy,</hi> that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural State of any Body can never be ſo much over-turn'd, or the Scituation of its parts ſo extreamly alter'd, but it may be conceiv'd in our Mind. He treats of Organical Bodies, and the Human in particular: But becauſe ſome Perſons, who never gave themſelves the Trouble, to be fully informed of what he means, have been pleas'd to cenſure his Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:175033:115"/>as very Extravagant, I have his leave to lay open his Tenets before you, who are own'd by all that know you, to be ſo great a Maſter in all parts of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and chiefly the <hi>Mathematical.</hi> Now the chief Heads of the Matters that he treats of, are as follows.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Of the Nature of a Body, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Organical one, where the Structure and Natural State of the Human Body is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>How many ways the Natural State of the Human Body, is ſaid to have been Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally alter'd.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Of the Laws of Motion, and of the three different Suſpenſions of the ſame, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to explain all Miracles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>How it can be conceiv'd, that Water can be changed into Wine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>V. <hi>How it can be conceiv'd, that a Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Body can be Invulnerable, Immortal, and can live for ever without Meat, as after the Reſurrection.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VI. <hi>How a Human Body can be conceived to be in a Fire without burning.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>VII. <hi>How we can conceive that an Army can paſs through the Sea without drowning, or walk upon the Water without Sinking.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:175033:116"/>
                  <item>VIII. <hi>How it can be conceived, that a Man can have a Bloody Sweat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IX. <hi>Of the different ways a Human Body can come into the World; where is given an Account of its Generation by Concourſe of Man and Woman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>X. <hi>How we can conceive a Human Body can be form'd of a Woman without a Man, as</hi> Chriſt<hi>'s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>XI. <hi>How to conceive a Human Body to be made without Man or Woman, as</hi> Adam<hi>'s.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>XII. <hi>How to conceive a Human Body dead, ſome Ages ſince, to be brought to Life again, as in the Reſurrection.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>XIII. <hi>How many ways it cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, that a Human Body can he Intire and Alive in two places at the ſame time.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>XIV. <hi>Of the Natural State of the Soul, and its Influence upon the Body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>XV. <hi>Of the Supernatural, or Miraculous State of the Soul united to the Body.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The Doctor deſires, and I'm ſure you'll own 'tis a very reaſonable Requeſt, that Gentlemen wou'd be pleas'd to ſuſpend their Judgments, till they ſee his Reaſons, which he will ingenuouſly ſubmit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Preſumption on his ſide, to their better Undeſtanding. He is the more
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:175033:116"/>encouraged to publiſh his Thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout theſe Matters, becauſe ſome of his Friends, to whom he has communicated his Reaſons, have told him, That none but ſuch as will not rightly underſtand him, (and People of that Complexion are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be convinc'd) cou'd deny what he maintains; becauſe his Reaſons are not grounded upon any <hi>Metaphysical</hi> Abſtract, or <hi>Hypothetical</hi> Notions, but entirely upon the viſible Structure of the Humane Body. When your Affairs will permit you to come to <hi>London,</hi> you and I will take an Opportunity to wait upon the Doctor, who I know will give you what farther Satisfaction you can deſire.</p>
               <p>And now, Mr. <hi>Raphſon,</hi> I hope you have finiſh'd in your Country Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, your Treatiſe <hi>de Spatio Infinito, Reali,</hi> which the Learn'd World has ſo long expected from your Hands. All your Friends here earneſtly long to ſee you in Town, and particularly my ſelf, who am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your most Obliged Friend and Servant, <hi>T. BROWN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb n="218" facs="tcp:175033:117"/>
            <head>TWO LETTERS BY CAPT. <hi>AYLOFFE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the Lord <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Grey.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOU ſeem to wonder, what ſhou'd be the reaſon that Men in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Gallantry,</hi> generally have incurr'd the Cenſure of Inconſtancy, when Women prove Faithful even to an Inconveniency. One reaſon I believe is, that we hate to be long confin'd, and their Converſation ſoon palls; tho' what may be aſſign'd, with greater plauſibleneſs, I think is, that thoſe very Favours a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man grants to her Lover, increaſe and continue her Affection, but withal leſſen his. Mens Paſſion almoſt always extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:175033:117"/>with Poſſeſſion; and what is the Parent of a Woman's Tenderneſs is the Paricide of ours: We ſeldom adore lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than we deſire, and what we aim at moſt can be conferr'd but once. In our Sex there is not that fatal Diſtinction: but as a Virgin, after yielding, has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs'd her ſelf of that Jewel, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one was willing to have purchas'd, and only courted her for. I believe the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of <hi>Love</hi> from Women, are more real than ours; there being too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently more of <hi>Vanity</hi> than <hi>Verity,</hi> more of <hi>Study</hi> than <hi>Affection</hi> in our Pretences: But it's no ſmall wound in a Woman's Heart, that conſtrains her to ſpeak, and I really am of Opinion, that ſhe can hardly love more violently, who confeſſes ſhe loves at all. A word ſometimes drops from their Mouths, which, as it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſign'd, gives a clearer Evidence of a growing Inclination, than all the Elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Actions and Affected Languiſhings, the greateſt part of <hi>Gallants</hi> put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. A Lovely Face is certainly the moſt agreeable Object our Eyes can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and the very Sound of the Voice of one we dearly love, is beyond the ſofteſt Harmony: Yet, by I know not what
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:175033:118"/>Fate, I have ſeen the Juncture when both were without any effect, and this more than once. The Latitude (I fancy) which we take in our Addreſſes, makes the Impreſſion but feeble: Variety of Objects diſtracts the Choice, and we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our Liberty, while we are pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a Tyrant. The Indulgence of one Woman, who is not extreamly charming, makes ſome ſort of Repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſlighted Vows we vainly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to a cruel <hi>Beauty.</hi> Few Men are ſo much in Love, as to be Proof againſt the continued Scorn of the moſt agreeable <hi>Phillis:</hi> We ask to obtain, not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd; and that can find the ſame Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in every place, will hardly be long confin'd to any one. Not but that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſpeaking generally, are not ſo perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious as Men; and it is Injuſtice, are well as Malice in us, to treat 'em as we do. They deſerve really more than <hi>Policy</hi> will permit us to ſhew 'em they do.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Lordſhip's humble Servant, <hi>AYLOFFE.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="221" facs="tcp:175033:118"/>
               <head>To a Friend in the Country.</head>
               <p>YOU have now, at length, left ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Watch,</hi> and teizing the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change-women,</hi> bid adieu to <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and taken up with <hi>Barrel-ale.</hi> You are all the Morning galloping after a <hi>Fox;</hi> all the Evening in a ſmoaky Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-corner, recounting whoſe Horſe leap'd beſt, was ofteneſt in with the Dogs, and how readily <hi>Lightfoot</hi> hit the cooling Scent, and reviv'd your drooping Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits with a proſpect of more Diverſion; which ſome Men, who think themſelves as wiſe in the Enjoyment of this World, as all the Men in <hi>Oxfordſhire,</hi> are pleas'd to term meer fatigue. And I believe your own Footman would not ride ſo far and ſo hard, to fetch a good Dinner, as both of you do, to ſee the Death of a ſtinking Beaſt. Has not the <hi>Roſe</hi> as good Accommodation as your <hi>Catherine-wheel</hi> Inn? And does not a Maſque give a more Chriſtian-like chaſe, and conclude in more ſatisfaction than the Animal you wot of? I ſaw your Letters to ſome of
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:175033:119"/>our <hi>Club,</hi> and laugh'd not a little at the ſtrangeneſs of your Style; it ſmelt of fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Tobacco,</hi> and was ſtain'd with your dropping Tankard. You acquainted 'em at large with the Scituation of your Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion-houſe; how a knot of branching <hi>Elms</hi> defended it from the <hi>North-wind;</hi> that the <hi>South-Sun</hi> gave you good <hi>Grapes,</hi> and moſt ſort of <hi>Wall-fruits;</hi> your <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> came on apace, and you had hopes of much good Fruit this <hi>Summer.</hi> After all, in <hi>Covent-garden</hi> Market, we can buy, in one quarter of an Hour, better <hi>Plants</hi> than your's, and richer <hi>Melons,</hi> for <hi>Groats</hi> apiece, than you have been poring over this three Months. You thank'd 'em for ſome News, that was ſo old we hardly could imagine what you meant, till <hi>Tom,</hi> who has all the <hi>Gazets</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets</hi> lock'd up in his Heart, as <hi>David</hi> did the Commandments, diſclos'd the Myſtery to us. I pity your new State indeed: Your <hi>Gazets</hi> are as ſtale as your Drink; which, tho' brew'd in <hi>March,</hi> is not broach'd till <hi>December.</hi> The chief <hi>Topicks</hi> of Diſcourſe, (for Converſation you have none) are <hi>Hawks, Horſes,</hi> and <hi>Hounds;</hi> every one of 'em as much <hi>God</hi>'s Image, as he that keeps them, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:175033:119"/>the <hi>Creator</hi> in a greater degree, and to more purpoſe. This you call a ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able retreat from the <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> to enjoy a Calm and Quiet Life: <hi>Heaven</hi> knows, you drink more there, and more ignoble and ungenerous Liquors than we in Town; for yours is down-right <hi>Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> Your <hi>Whoring</hi> I will allow ſafer, but it is meer <hi>Brutality</hi> too; there is no ſuch thing as Intrigue in all your County, which is like an exquiſite Sawce to good Meat, qualifying the Palate more vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſly: Well, 'tis Six, and I muſt to the <hi>Club,</hi> where we will pity your So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, and drink your Proſperity, in a Cup that is worth a Stable of <hi>Horſes,</hi> and a Kennel of <hi>Hounds.</hi> So adieu.</p>
               <trailer>The End of the First Volume.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:120"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:120"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PLAYS,</hi> lately printed for, and ſold by <hi>Richard Wellington.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>PLain-dealer.</item>
               <item>Triumphs of Virtue</item>
               <item>Town Fop.</item>
               <item>Plot, and no Plot.</item>
               <item>Ganterbury Gueſt.</item>
               <item>State of Innocence.</item>
               <item>Richmond Heireſs.</item>
               <item>Rival Ladies.</item>
               <item>Abdelazor, or the Moor's Revenge.</item>
               <item>London Cuckolds.</item>
               <item>Wild Gallant.</item>
               <item>Ibrahim 13. Emperour.</item>
               <item>Libertine.</item>
               <item>Love for Money.</item>
               <item>Oedipus.</item>
               <item>Debauchee, or Credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Cuckold.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Carlos.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Marriagehater Match'd</item>
               <item>Sacrifice, a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>Unnatural Brother.</item>
               <item>Spaniſh Wives.</item>
               <item>Love's Laſt-ſhift.</item>
               <item>Trick to cheat the Devil.</item>
               <item>Love in Ruines.</item>
               <item>Innocent Miſtreſs.</item>
               <item>Rule a Wife, and have a Wife.</item>
               <item>City Heireſs, or Sir <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy Treat-all.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir Anthony Love, or <hi>The Rambling Lady.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Younger Brother, or <hi>The Amorous Jilt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>Oroonoko.</item>
               <item>Country Wake.</item>
               <item>Old Bachelor.</item>
               <item>Humorous Lieutenant</item>
               <item>Country Wife.</item>
               <item>Princeſs of <hi>Cleves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>Anatomiſt, or <hi>Sham Doctor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Round-heads, or <hi>The Good Old Cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>Young King, or <hi>The Miſtake.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rover, or <hi>Baniſh'd Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>valier<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caligula,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Crown.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Relapſe, or <hi>Vertue in Danger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Quixot,</hi> in Two Parts.</item>
               <item>Empreſs of <hi>Morocco.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>True Widow.</item>
               <item>Cheats.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Agnes de Caſtro.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Provok'd Wife.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:121"/>
            <head>Books printed for, and ſold by <hi>R. Wellington.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Hiſtory of <hi>Polybius</hi> the <hi>Megalopolitan,</hi> containing an Account of the Tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the whole World, but principally of the <hi>Roman</hi> People, in 3 Vol. tranſlated by Sir <hi>Henry Sheers</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dryden,</hi> the like never before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant: Price ten Shillings.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Nature and Faculties of Man, in ſeveral <hi>Eſſays,</hi> with ſome Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Occurrences of Human Life; by <hi>Tim. Nourſe,</hi> Gent. price 4 Shillings.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory and Novels of the late Ingenious Mrs. <hi>Behn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> collected into one Vol. viz. <hi>Oroonoko,</hi> or <hi>The Royal Slave:</hi> The Fair Jilt, or <hi>Prince Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin: Agnes de Caſtro,</hi> or <hi>The Force of Generous Love:</hi> The Lover's Watch, or the Art of Make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Love: The Ladies Looking-glaſs to dreſs themſelves by: The Lucky Miſtake: Memoirs of the Court of the King of <hi>Bantam:</hi> The Nun, or the Perjur'd Beauty: The Adventures of the Black Lady. Theſe 3 never before publiſh'd, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with her Life and Memoirs, written by one of the <hi>Fair Sex;</hi> interwoven with ſeveral Love-Letters, which paſſed beeween her and <hi>Myn Heer Van Bruin,</hi> a <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchant, the the Edition enlarged; price 5 Shillings.</p>
            <p>A brief and eaſy Method to underſtand the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Hiſtory, with an exact Chron. of the Reign of the Emperors, and an Account of the moſt Eminent Authors, when they flourish'd; and an Abridgement of <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, by way of Dialogue, for the uſe of the Duke of <hi>Burgundy:</hi> Done out of <hi>French,</hi> with large Additions, by Mr. <hi>Tho. Brown;</hi> price two Shillings.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:175033:121"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
